ENTRY       EC 1.1.9.1                  Enzyme
NAME        alcohol dehydrogenase (azurin);
            type II quinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase;
            quinohaemoprotein ethanol dehydrogenase;
            QHEDH;
            ADHIIB
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With a copper protein as acceptor
SYSNAME     alcohol:azurin oxidoreductase
REACTION    a primary alcohol + azurin = an aldehyde + reduced azurin [RN:R09480]
ALL_REAC    R09480
SUBSTRATE   primary alcohol [CPD:C00226];
            azurin
PRODUCT     aldehyde [CPD:C00071];
            reduced azurin [CPD:C05358]
COMMENT     A soluble, periplasmic PQQ-containing quinohemoprotein. Also contains a single heme c. Occurs in Comamonas and Pseudomonas. Does not require an amine activator. Oxidizes a wide range of primary and secondary alcohols, and also aldehydes and large substrates such as sterols; methanol is not a substrate. Usually assayed with phenazine methosulfate or ferricyanide. Like all other quinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenases it has an 8-bladed 'propeller' structure, a calcium ion bound to the PQQ in the active site and an unusual disulfide ring structure in close proximity to the PQQ.
HISTORY     EC 1.1.9.1 created 2010 as EC 1.1.98.1; transferred 2011 to EC 1.1.9.1
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3521592]
  AUTHORS   Groen BW, van Kleef MA, Duine JA
  TITLE     Quinohaemoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase apoenzyme from Pseudomonas testosteroni.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 234 (1986) 611-5.
  ORGANISM  Comamonas testosteroni
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q46444] [ctt:CtCNB1_0197]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7626615]
  AUTHORS   de Jong GA, Caldeira J, Sun J, Jongejan JA, de Vries S, Loehr TM, Moura I, Moura JJ, Duine JA
  TITLE     Characterization of the interaction between PQQ and heme c in the quinohemoprotein ethanol dehydrogenase from Comamonas testosteroni.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 34 (1995) 9451-8.
  ORGANISM  Comamonas testosteroni
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:7730276]
  AUTHORS   Toyama H, Fujii A, Matsushita K, Shinagawa E, Ameyama M, Adachi O
  TITLE     Three distinct quinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenases are expressed when Pseudomonas putida is grown on different alcohols.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 177 (1995) 2442-50.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas putida
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q4W6G0 Q8GR64]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:10320337]
  AUTHORS   Matsushita K, Yamashita T, Aoki N, Toyama H, Adachi O
  TITLE     Electron transfer from quinohemoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase to blue copper protein azurin in the alcohol oxidase respiratory chain of Pseudomonas putida HK5.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 38 (1999) 6111-8.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas putida
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9F646 Q8GR64]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:12057198]
  AUTHORS   Chen ZW, Matsushita K, Yamashita T, Fujii TA, Toyama H, Adachi O, Bellamy HD, Mathews FS
  TITLE     Structure at 1.9 A resolution of a quinohemoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase from Pseudomonas putida HK5.
  JOURNAL   Structure. 10 (2002) 837-49.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas putida
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8GR64]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:11714714]
  AUTHORS   Oubrie A, Rozeboom HJ, Kalk KH, Huizinga EG, Dijkstra BW
  TITLE     Crystal structure of quinohemoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase from Comamonas testosteroni: structural basis for substrate oxidation and electron transfer.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 277 (2002) 3727-32.
  ORGANISM  Comamonas testosteroni
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q46444] [ctt:CtCNB1_0197]
ORTHOLOGY   K17760  quinohemoprotein ethanol dehydrogenase
GENES       PPW: PputW619_2696
            PMK: MDS_2680
            PSZ: PSTAB_2905
            PSR: PSTAA_3020
            PSH: Psest_1423
            ADI: B5T_04379(exaA1)
            REU: Reut_A1461 Reut_B4160
            REH: H16_A1884(h16_A1884)
            CNC: CNE_1c18660(qheDH) CNE_BB1p04310(adh)
            CTI: RALTA_A1577(exaA1)
            POL: Bpro_5302
            VEI: Veis_0427
            DAC: Daci_3352
            DEL: DelCs14_3417
            VAP: Vapar_5018
            VPE: Varpa_5729
            VPD: VAPA_1c52090
            CTT: CtCNB1_0197 CtCNB1_1388
            MPT: Mpe_A0877 Mpe_A0905
            AZO: azo2844(exaA1) azo3022(exaA4)
            PLA: Plav_1306
            BBT: BBta_5502
            RPA: RPA3188
            RPB: RPB_2355
            RPD: RPD_3110
            RPE: RPE_3525
            RPT: Rpal_3601
            RPX: Rpdx1_2242
            HMC: HYPMC_4861(adh)
            PZU: PHZ_c3112
            HNE: HNE_0129(adhA)
            NAR: Saro_2878
            NPP: PP1Y_AT11408 PP1Y_AT11547 PP1Y_Mpl5286
            SAL: Sala_0379
            SWI: Swit_0721 Swit_2227 Swit_5136
            SJP: SJA_C1-02010 SJA_C1-02070 SJA_C2-04000
            SCH: Sphch_2127
            SSY: SLG_05620 SLG_07280 SLG_12260 SLG_20920
            ELI: ELI_14570
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.9.1
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.9.1
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.9.1
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.9.1
///
