ENTRY       EC 1.1.2.6                  Enzyme
NAME        polyvinyl alcohol dehydrogenase (cytochrome);
            PVA dehydrogenase;
            PVADH
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With a cytochrome as acceptor
SYSNAME     polyvinyl alcohol:ferricytochrome-c oxidoreductase
REACTION    polyvinyl alcohol + ferricytochrome c = oxidized polyvinyl alcohol + ferrocytochrome c + H+ [RN:R03136]
ALL_REAC    R03136
SUBSTRATE   polyvinyl alcohol [CPD:C00980];
            ferricytochrome c [CPD:C00125]
PRODUCT     oxidized polyvinyl alcohol [CPD:C01166];
            ferrocytochrome c [CPD:C00126];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     A quinoprotein. The enzyme is involved in bacterial polyvinyl alcohol degradation. Some Gram-negative bacteria degrade polyvinyl alcohol by importing it into the periplasmic space, where it is oxidized by polyvinyl alcohol dehydrogenase, an enzyme that is coupled to the respiratory chain via cytochrome c. The enzyme contains a pyrroloquinoline quinone cofactor.
HISTORY     EC 1.1.2.6 created 1989 as EC 1.1.99.23, transferred 2010 to EC 1.1.2.6
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3513704]
  AUTHORS   Shimao M, Ninomiya K, Kuno O, Kato N, Sakazawa C.
  TITLE     Existence of a novel enzyme, pyrroloquinoline quinone-dependent polyvinyl alcohol dehydrogenase, in a bacterial symbiont, Pseudomonas sp. strain VM15C.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 51 (1986) 268-75.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16347841]
  AUTHORS   Shimao M, Onishi S, Kato N, Sakazawa C.
  TITLE     Pyrroloquinoline Quinone-Dependent Cytochrome Reduction in Polyvinyl Alcohol-Degrading Pseudomonas sp. Strain VM15C.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 55 (1989) 275-278.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:18343342]
  AUTHORS   Mamoto R, Hu X, Chiue H, Fujioka Y, Kawai F
  TITLE     Cloning and expression of soluble cytochrome c and its role in polyvinyl alcohol  degradation by polyvinyl alcohol-utilizing Sphingopyxis sp. strain 113P3.
  JOURNAL   J. Biosci. Bioeng. 105 (2008) 147-51.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16804170]
  AUTHORS   Hirota-Mamoto R, Nagai R, Tachibana S, Yasuda M, Tani A, Kimbara K, Kawai F
  TITLE     Cloning and expression of the gene for periplasmic poly(vinyl alcohol) dehydrogenase from Sphingomonas sp. strain 113P3, a novel-type quinohaemoprotein  alcohol dehydrogenase.
  JOURNAL   Microbiology. 152 (2006) 1941-9.
  ORGANISM  Sphingopyxis sp.
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q588Z1]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:18214469]
  AUTHORS   Hu X, Mamoto R, Fujioka Y, Tani A, Kimbara K, Kawai F
  TITLE     The pva operon is located on the megaplasmid of Sphingopyxis sp. strain 113P3 and is constitutively expressed, although expression is enhanced by PVA.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 78 (2008) 685-93.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:19590867]
  AUTHORS   Kawai F, Hu X
  TITLE     Biochemistry of microbial polyvinyl alcohol degradation.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 84 (2009) 227-37.
ORTHOLOGY   K05889  polyvinyl alcohol dehydrogenase (cytochrome)
GENES       XFA: XF2259
            XFT: PD1299
            XFN: XfasM23_1384
            XFF: XFLM_00585
            XCC: XCC4080
            XCB: XC_4171
            XCA: xccb100_4282(mxaF2)
            XCP: XCR_0167
            XCV: XCV4300
            XAC: XAC4199
            XCI: XCAW_00095
            XAX: XACM_4071
            XAO: XAC29_21160
            XOO: XOO0329
            XOM: XOO_0301
            XOP: PXO_02746
            XOR: XOC_0353
            EBA: p2A321(pvaA)
            SUR: STAUR_3610
            SCL: sce5403
            SCU: SCE1572_16470 SCE1572_48810
            BJA: bll5504
            BJU: BJ6T_42530
            PZU: PHZ_c0057
            SWI: Swit_1323
            ICA: Intca_0327
            SUS: Acid_5713
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.2.6
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.2.6
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.2.6
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.2.6
///
