ENTRY       EC 1.1.99.37                Enzyme
NAME        methanol dehydrogenase (nicotinoprotein);
            NDMA-dependent methanol dehydrogenase;
            nicotinoprotein methanol dehydrogenase;
            methanol:N,N-dimethyl-4-nitrosoaniline oxidoreductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With other acceptors
SYSNAME     methanol:acceptor oxidoreductase
REACTION    methanol + acceptor = formaldehyde + reduced acceptor [RN:R09553]
ALL_REAC    R09553
SUBSTRATE   methanol [CPD:C00132];
            acceptor [CPD:C00028]
PRODUCT     formaldehyde [CPD:C00067];
            reduced acceptor [CPD:C00030]
COMMENT     Contains Zn2+ and Mg2+. Nicotinoprotein methanol dehydrogenases have a tightly bound NADP+/NADPH cofactor that does not dissociate during the catalytic process. Instead, the cofactor is regenerated by a second substrate or electron carrier. While the in vivo electron acceptor is not known, N,N-dimethyl-4-nitrosoaniline (NDMA), which is reduced to 4-(hydroxylamino)-N,N-dimethylaniline, can serve this function in vitro. The enzyme has been detected in several Gram-positive methylotrophic bacteria, including Amycolatopsis methanolica, Rhodococcus rhodochrous and Rhodococcus erythropolis [1-3]. These enzymes are decameric, and possess a 5-fold symmetry [4]. Some of the enzymes can also dismutate formaldehyde to methanol and formate [5].
HISTORY     EC 1.1.99.37 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1995642]
  AUTHORS   Vonck J, Arfman N, De Vries GE, Van Beeumen J, Van Bruggen EF, Dijkhuizen L
  TITLE     Electron microscopic analysis and biochemical characterization of a novel methanol dehydrogenase from the thermotolerant Bacillus sp. C1.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 266 (1991) 3949-54.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus sp.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8385013]
  AUTHORS   Van Ophem PW, Van Beeumen J, Duine JA
  TITLE     Nicotinoprotein [NAD(P)-containing] alcohol/aldehyde oxidoreductases. Purification and characterization of a novel type from Amycolatopsis methanolica.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 212 (1993) 819-26.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8449887]
  AUTHORS   Bystrykh LV, Vonck J, van Bruggen EF, van Beeumen J, Samyn B, Govorukhina NI, Arfman N, Duine JA, Dijkhuizen L
  TITLE     Electron microscopic analysis and structural characterization of novel NADP(H)-containing methanol: N,N'-dimethyl-4-nitrosoaniline oxidoreductases from  the gram-positive methylotrophic bacteria Amycolatopsis methanolica and Mycobacterium gastri MB19.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 175 (1993) 1814-22.
  ORGANISM  Amycolatopsis methanolica, Mycobacterium gastri
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12351635]
  AUTHORS   Hektor HJ, Kloosterman H, Dijkhuizen L
  TITLE     Identification of a magnesium-dependent NAD(P)(H)-binding domain in the nicotinoprotein methanol dehydrogenase from Bacillus methanolicus.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 277 (2002) 46966-73.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus methanolicus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:19875438]
  AUTHORS   Park H, Lee H, Ro YT, Kim YM
  TITLE     Identification and functional characterization of a gene for the methanol : N,N'-dimethyl-4-nitrosoaniline oxidoreductase from Mycobacterium sp. strain JC1 (DSM 3803).
  JOURNAL   Microbiology. 156 (2010) 463-71.
  ORGANISM  Mycobacterium sp.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.99.37
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.99.37
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.99.37
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.99.37
///
