ENTRY       EC 1.1.3.45                 Enzyme
NAME        aclacinomycin-N oxidase;
            AknOx (ambiguous);
            aclacinomycin oxidoreductase (ambiguous)
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With oxygen as acceptor
SYSNAME     aclacinomycin-N:oxygen oxidoreductase
REACTION    aclacinomycin N + O2 = aclacinomycin A + H2O2 [RN:R09334]
ALL_REAC    R09334
SUBSTRATE   aclacinomycin N [CPD:C18637];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     aclacinomycin A [CPD:C18638];
            H2O2 [CPD:C00027]
COMMENT     A flavoprotein (FAD). This bifunctional enzyme is a secreted flavin-dependent enzyme that is involved in the modification of the terminal sugar residues in the biosynthesis of aclacinomycins. The enzyme utilizes the same active site to catalyse the oxidation of the rhodinose moiety of aclacinomycin N to the cinerulose A moiety of aclacinomycin A and the oxidation of the latter to the L-aculose moiety of aclacinomycin Y (cf. EC 1.3.3.14, aclacinomycin A oxidase).
HISTORY     EC 1.1.3.45 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:17395717]
  AUTHORS   Alexeev I, Sultana A, Mantsala P, Niemi J, Schneider G.
  TITLE     Aclacinomycin oxidoreductase (AknOx) from the biosynthetic pathway of the antibiotic aclacinomycin is an unusual flavoenzyme with a dual active site.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 104 (2007) 6170-5.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces galilaeus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q0PCD7]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:17242508]
  AUTHORS   Sultana A, Alexeev I, Kursula I, Mantsala P, Niemi J, Schneider G
  TITLE     Structure determination by multiwavelength anomalous diffraction of aclacinomycin oxidoreductase: indications of multidomain pseudomerohedral twinning.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 63 (2007) 149-59.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces galilaeus
PATHWAY     ec01057  Biosynthesis of type II polyketide products
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K15949  aclacinomycin oxidase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.3.45
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.3.45
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.3.45
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.3.45
///
