ENTRY       EC 1.1.99.18                Enzyme
NAME        cellobiose dehydrogenase (acceptor);
            cellobiose dehydrogenase;
            cellobiose oxidoreductase;
            Phanerochaete chrysosporium cellobiose oxidoreductase;
            CBOR;
            cellobiose oxidase;
            cellobiose:oxygen 1-oxidoreductase;
            CDH;
            cellobiose:(acceptor) 1-oxidoreductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With other acceptors
SYSNAME     cellobiose:acceptor 1-oxidoreductase
REACTION    cellobiose + acceptor = cellobiono-1,5-lactone + reduced acceptor [RN:R01443 R06246]
ALL_REAC    R01443 R06246(G) > R01442 R06244(G);
            (other) R02365 R06247(G)
SUBSTRATE   cellobiose [CPD:C00185];
            acceptor [CPD:C00028]
PRODUCT     cellobiono-1,5-lactone [CPD:C01093];
            reduced acceptor [CPD:C00030]
COMMENT     2,6-Dichloroindophenol can act as acceptor. Also acts, more slowly, on cello-oligosaccharides, lactose and D-glucosyl-1,4-beta-D-mannose. Includes EC 1.1.5.1, cellobiose dehydrogenase (quinone), which is now known to be a proteolytic product of this enzyme. The enzyme from the white rot fungus Phanerochaete chrysosporium is unusual in having two redoxin domains, one containing a flavin and the other a protoheme group. It transfers reducing equivalents from cellobiose to two types of redox acceptor: two-electron oxidants, including redox dyes, benzoquinones and molecular oxygen and one-electron oxidants, including semiquinone species, iron(II) complexes and the model acceptor cytochrome c [9].
HISTORY     EC 1.1.99.18 created 1983, modified 2002 (EC 1.1.5.1 created 1983, incorporated 2002; EC 1.1.3.25 created 1986, incorporated 2005)
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:7103940]
  AUTHORS   Coudray MR, Canevascini G, Meier H.
  TITLE     Characterization of a cellobiose dehydrogenase in the cellulolytic fungus Sporotrichum (Chrysosporium) thermophile.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 203 (1982) 277-84.
  ORGANISM  Sporotrichum thermophile
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Dekker, R.F.H.
  TITLE     Induction and characterization of a cellobiose dehydrogenase produced by a species of Monilia.
  JOURNAL   J. Gen. Microbiol. 120 (1980) 309-316.
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   Dekker, R.F.H.
  TITLE     Cellobiose dehydrogenase produced by Monilia sp.
  JOURNAL   Methods Enzymol. 160 (1988) 454-463.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:8392950]
  AUTHORS   Habu N, Samejima M, Dean JF, Eriksson KE.
  TITLE     Release of the FAD domain from cellobiose oxidase by proteases from cellulolytic cultures of Phanerochaete chrysosporium.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 327 (1993) 161-4.
  ORGANISM  Phanerochaete chrysosporium
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:11282631]
  AUTHORS   Baminger U, Subramaniam SS, Renganathan V, Haltrich D.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of cellobiose dehydrogenase from the plant pathogen Sclerotium (Athelia) rolfsii.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 67 (2001) 1766-74.
  ORGANISM  Sclerotium rolfsii
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:11786022]
  AUTHORS   Hallberg BM, Henriksson G, Pettersson G, Divne C.
  TITLE     Crystal structure of the flavoprotein domain of the extracellular flavocytochrome cellobiose dehydrogenase.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 315 (2002) 421-34.
  ORGANISM  Phanerochaete chrysosporium
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:710416]
  AUTHORS   Ayers AR, Ayers SB, Eriksson KE.
  TITLE     Cellobiose oxidase, purification and partial characterization of a hemoprotein from Sporotrichum pulverulentum.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 90 (1978) 171-81.
  ORGANISM  Sporotrichum pulverulentum
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:7144569]
  AUTHORS   Ayers AR, Eriksson KE.
  TITLE     Cellobiose oxidase from Sporotrichum pulverulentum.
  JOURNAL   Methods. Enzymol. 89 Pt D (1982) 129-35.
  ORGANISM  Sporotrichum pulverulentum
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:12686420]
  AUTHORS   Mason MG, Nicholls P, Divne C, Hallberg BM, Henriksson G, Wilson MT.
  TITLE     The heme domain of cellobiose oxidoreductase: a one-electron reducing system.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1604 (2003) 47-54.
  ORGANISM  Phanerochaete chrysosporium
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.99.18
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.99.18
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.99.18
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.99.18
            CAS: 54576-85-1
///
