ENTRY       EC 1.1.1.319                Enzyme
NAME        isoeugenol synthase;
            IGS1;
            t-anol/isoeugenol synthase 1
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With NAD+ or NADP+ as acceptor
SYSNAME     eugenol:NADP+ oxidoreductase (coniferyl acetate reducing)
REACTION    isoeugenol + acetate + NADP+ = coniferyl acetate + NADPH + H+ [RN:R09931]
ALL_REAC    R09931;
            (other) R10289
SUBSTRATE   isoeugenol [CPD:C10469];
            acetate [CPD:C00033];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006]
PRODUCT     coniferyl acetate [CPD:C20225];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     The enzyme acts in the opposite direction. In Ocimum basilicum (sweet basil), Clarkia breweri and Petunia hybrida only isoeugenol is formed [1,2]. However in Pimpinella anisum (anise) only anol is formed in vivo, although the cloned enzyme does produce isoeugenol [3].
HISTORY     EC 1.1.1.319 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:16782809]
  AUTHORS   Koeduka T, Fridman E, Gang DR, Vassao DG, Jackson BL, Kish CM, Orlova I, Spassova SM, Lewis NG, Noel JP, Baiga TJ, Dudareva N, Pichersky E
  TITLE     Eugenol and isoeugenol, characteristic aromatic constituents of spices, are biosynthesized via reduction of a coniferyl alcohol ester.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 103 (2006) 10128-33.
  ORGANISM  Ocimum basilicum
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q15GI3]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:18208524]
  AUTHORS   Koeduka T, Louie GV, Orlova I, Kish CM, Ibdah M, Wilkerson CG, Bowman ME, Baiga TJ, Noel JP, Dudareva N, Pichersky E
  TITLE     The multiple phenylpropene synthases in both Clarkia breweri and Petunia hybrida  represent two distinct protein lineages.
  JOURNAL   Plant. J. 54 (2008) 362-74.
  ORGANISM  Clarkia breweri
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:18987218]
  AUTHORS   Koeduka T, Baiga TJ, Noel JP, Pichersky E
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of t-anethole in anise: characterization of t-anol/isoeugenol synthase and an O-methyltransferase specific for a C7-C8 propenyl side chain.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 149 (2009) 384-94.
  ORGANISM  Pimpinella anisum
PATHWAY     ec00940  Phenylpropanoid biosynthesis
ORTHOLOGY   K17056  isoeugenol synthase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.1.319
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.1.319
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.1.319
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.1.319
///
