ENTRY       EC 1.1.2.7                  Enzyme
NAME        methanol dehydrogenase (cytochrome c);
            methanol dehydrogenase;
            MDH
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With a cytochrome as acceptor
SYSNAME     methanol:cytochrome c oxidoreductase
REACTION    a primary alcohol + 2 ferricytochrome cL = an aldehyde + 2 ferrocytochrome cL + 2 H+
ALL_REAC    (other) R01146 R09127 R09128
SUBSTRATE   primary alcohol [CPD:C00226];
            ferricytochrome cL [CPD:C18233]
PRODUCT     aldehyde [CPD:C00071];
            ferrocytochrome cL [CPD:C18234];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     A periplasmic quinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase that only occurs in methylotrophic bacteria. It uses the novel specific cytochrome cL as acceptor. Acts on a wide range of primary alcohols, including ethanol, duodecanol, chloroethanol, cinnamyl alcohol, and also formaldehyde. Activity is stimulated by ammonia or methylamine. It is usually assayed with phenazine methosulphate. Like all other quinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenases it has an 8-bladed 'propeller' structure, a calcium ion bound to the PQQ in the active site and an unusual disulphide ring structure in close proximity to the PQQ. It differs from EC 1.1.2.8, alcohol dehydrogenase (cytochrome c), in having a high affinity for methanol and in having a second essential small subunit (no known function).
HISTORY     EC 1.1.2.7 created 1972 as 1.1.99.8, modified 1982, part transferred 2010 to EC 1.1.2.7
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:4378696]
  AUTHORS   Anthony C, Zatman LJ
  TITLE     The microbial oxidation of methanol. 2. The methanol-oxidizing enzyme of Pseudomonas sp. M 27.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 92 (1964) 614-21.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:6049934]
  AUTHORS   Anthony C, Zatman LJ
  TITLE     The microbial oxidation of methanol. The prosthetic group of the alcohol dehydrogenase of Pseudomonas sp. M27: a new oxidoreductase prosthetic group.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 104 (1967) 960-9.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:6250827]
  AUTHORS   Duine JA, Frank J, Verwiel PE.
  TITLE     Structure and activity of the prosthetic group of methanol dehydrogenase.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 108 (1980) 187-92.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:471057]
  AUTHORS   Salisbury SA, Forrest HS, Cruse WB, Kennard O.
  TITLE     A novel coenzyme from bacterial primary alcohol dehydrogenases.
  JOURNAL   Nature. 280 (1979) 843-4.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:1311606]
  AUTHORS   Cox JM, Day DJ, Anthony C
  TITLE     The interaction of methanol dehydrogenase and its electron acceptor, cytochrome cL in methylotrophic bacteria.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1119 (1992) 97-106.
  ORGANISM  Methylophilus methylotrophus
  SEQUENCE  [up:P38540]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:7656012]
  AUTHORS   Blake CC, Ghosh M, Harlos K, Avezoux A, Anthony C
  TITLE     The active site of methanol dehydrogenase contains a disulphide bridge between adjacent cysteine residues.
  JOURNAL   Nat. Struct. Biol. 1 (1994) 102-5.
  ORGANISM  Methylobacterium extorquens
  SEQUENCE  [mea:Mex_1p4538 Mex_1p4535]
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:9930981]
  AUTHORS   Xia ZX, He YN, Dai WW, White SA, Boyd GD, Mathews FS
  TITLE     Detailed active site configuration of a new crystal form of methanol dehydrogenase from Methylophilus W3A1 at 1.9 A resolution.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 38 (1999) 1214-20.
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:11502173]
  AUTHORS   Afolabi PR, Mohammed F, Amaratunga K, Majekodunmi O, Dales SL, Gill R, Thompson D, Cooper JB, Wood SP, Goodwin PM, Anthony C
  TITLE     Site-directed mutagenesis and X-ray crystallography of the PQQ-containing quinoprotein methanol dehydrogenase and its electron acceptor, cytochrome c(L).
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 40 (2001) 9799-809.
  ORGANISM  Methylobacterium extorquens
  SEQUENCE  [mea:Mex_1p4538 Mex_1p4535]
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:12686102]
  AUTHORS   Anthony C, Williams P
  TITLE     The structure and mechanism of methanol dehydrogenase.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1647 (2003) 18-23.
REFERENCE   10 [PMID:15608378]
  AUTHORS   Williams PA, Coates L, Mohammed F, Gill R, Erskine PT, Coker A, Wood SP, Anthony C, Cooper JB
  TITLE     The atomic resolution structure of methanol dehydrogenase from Methylobacterium extorquens.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 61 (2005) 75-9.
PATHWAY     ec00010  Glycolysis / Gluconeogenesis
            ec00625  Chloroalkane and chloroalkene degradation
            ec00680  Methane metabolism
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
            ec01120  Microbial metabolism in diverse environments
ORTHOLOGY   K14028  methanol dehydrogenase (cytochrome c) subunit 1
            K14029  methanol dehydrogenase (cytochrome c) subunit 2
GENES       MCA: MCA0299 MCA0779(mxaF) MCA0782(mxaI)
            MMT: Metme_1518 Metme_4317 Metme_4320
            MAH: MEALZ_3445(mxaI) MEALZ_3448(mxaF) MEALZ_3497(xoxF)
            MEJ: Q7A_534 Q7A_537
            MEC: Q7C_2122 Q7C_2125
            VEI: Veis_1826 Veis_1829
            MFA: Mfla_2041 Mfla_2044
            MEI: Msip34_0734 Msip34_0737
            MEP: MPQ_0771 MPQ_0774
            RPC: RPC_1907 RPC_1910
            RPE: RPE_3136 RPE_3139
            SNO: Snov_4188 Snov_4191
            MEX: Mext_4147 Mext_4150
            MEA: Mex_1p4535(mxaI) Mex_1p4538(mxaF)
            MDI: METDI5141(mxaI) METDI5145(mxaF)
            MCH: Mchl_4515 Mchl_4518
            MRD: Mrad2831_4207 Mrad2831_4210
            MPO: Mpop_4629 Mpop_4632
            MNO: Mnod_8037 Mnod_8040
            MSL: Msil_0471 Msil_0474
            HDN: Hden_1320 Hden_1323
            HMC: HYPMC_0485(mxaF) HYPMC_0488(mxaI)
            HNI: W911_14530 W911_14545
            MSC: BN69_2570(mxaF) BN69_2573
            PDE: Pden_2993 Pden_2996
            GBE: GbCGDNIH1_0344 GbCGDNIH1_0347
            ALI: AZOLI_p10948(moxF1) AZOLI_p10951(moxI)
            MIN: Minf_0992(gcd)
            MOX: DAMO_0112(mxaF) DAMO_0115(mxaI)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.2.7
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.2.7
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.2.7
            UM-BBD (Biocatalysis/Biodegradation Database): 1.1.2.7
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.2.7
            CAS: 37205-43-9
///
