ENTRY       EC 1.1.99.36                Enzyme
NAME        alcohol dehydrogenase (nicotinoprotein);
            NDMA-dependent alcohol dehydrogenase;
            nicotinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase;
            np-ADH;
            ethanol:N,N-dimethyl-4-nitrosoaniline oxidoreductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With other acceptors
SYSNAME     ethanol:acceptor oxidoreductase
REACTION    ethanol + acceptor = acetaldehyde + reduced acceptor [RN:R09552]
ALL_REAC    R09552
SUBSTRATE   ethanol [CPD:C00469];
            acceptor [CPD:C00028]
PRODUCT     acetaldehyde [CPD:C00084];
            reduced acceptor [CPD:C00030]
COMMENT     Contains Zn2+. Nicotinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenases are unique medium-chain dehydrogenases/reductases (MDR) alcohol dehydrogenases that have a tightly bound NAD+/NADH cofactor that does not dissociate during the catalytic process. Instead, the cofactor is regenerated by a second substrate or electron carrier. While the in vivo electron acceptor is not known, N,N-dimethyl-4-nitrosoaniline (NDMA), which is reduced to 4-(hydroxylamino)-N,N-dimethylaniline, can serve this function in vitro.
            The enzyme from the Gram-positive bacterium Amycolatopsis methanolica can accept many primary alcohols as substrates, including benzylalcohol [1].
HISTORY     EC 1.1.99.36 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8385013]
  AUTHORS   Van Ophem PW, Van Beeumen J, Duine JA
  TITLE     Nicotinoprotein [NAD(P)-containing] alcohol/aldehyde oxidoreductases. Purification and characterization of a novel type from Amycolatopsis methanolica.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 212 (1993) 819-26.
  ORGANISM  Amycolatopsis methanolica
  SEQUENCE  [up:P80175]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9485460]
  AUTHORS   Piersma SR, Visser AJ, de Vries S, Duine JA
  TITLE     Optical spectroscopy of nicotinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase from Amycolatopsis  methanolica: a comparison with horse liver alcohol dehydrogenase and UDP-galactose epimerase.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 37 (1998) 3068-77.
  ORGANISM  Amycolatopsis methanolica
  SEQUENCE  [up:P80175]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10784035]
  AUTHORS   Schenkels P, Duine JA
  TITLE     Nicotinoprotein (NADH-containing) alcohol dehydrogenase from Rhodococcus erythropolis DSM 1069: an efficient catalyst for coenzyme-independent oxidation of a broad spectrum of alcohols and the interconversion of alcohols and aldehydes.
  JOURNAL   Microbiology. 146 ( Pt 4) (2000) 775-85.
  ORGANISM  Rhodococcus erythropolis
  SEQUENCE  [up:P81747]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:14690248]
  AUTHORS   Piersma SR, Norin A, de Vries S, Jornvall H, Duine JA
  TITLE     Inhibition of nicotinoprotein (NAD+-containing) alcohol dehydrogenase by trans-4-(N,N-dimethylamino)-cinnamaldehyde binding to the active site.
  JOURNAL   J. Protein. Chem. 22 (2003) 457-61.
  ORGANISM  Amycolatopsis methanolica
  SEQUENCE  [up:P80175]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:12827287]
  AUTHORS   Norin A, Piersma SR, Duine JA, Jornvall H
  TITLE     Nicotinoprotein (NAD+ -containing) alcohol dehydrogenase: structural relationships and functional interpretations.
  JOURNAL   Cell. Mol. Life. Sci. 60 (2003) 999-1006.
  ORGANISM  Amycolatopsis methanolica
  SEQUENCE  [up:P80175]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.99.36
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.99.36
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.99.36
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.99.36
///
