ENTRY       EC 1.1.1.266                Enzyme
NAME        dTDP-4-dehydro-6-deoxyglucose reductase;
            dTDP-4-keto-6-deoxyglucose reductase;
            dTDP-D-fucose:NADP+ oxidoreductase;
            Fcf1;
            dTDP-6-deoxy-D-xylo-hex-4-ulopyranose reductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With NAD+ or NADP+ as acceptor
SYSNAME     dTDP-alpha-D-fucopyranose:NAD(P)+ oxidoreductase
REACTION    dTDP-alpha-D-fucopyranose + NAD(P)+ = dTDP-4-dehydro-6-deoxy-alpha-D-glucose + NAD(P)H + H+ [RN:R05687]
ALL_REAC    R05687
SUBSTRATE   dTDP-alpha-D-fucopyranose [CPD:C07277];
            NAD+ [CPD:C00003];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006]
PRODUCT     dTDP-4-dehydro-6-deoxy-alpha-D-glucose [CPD:C11907];
            NADH [CPD:C00004];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     The enzymes from the Gram-negative bacteria Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans and Escherichia coli O52 are involved in activation of fucose for incorporation into capsular polysaccharide O-antigens [1,3]. The enzyme from the Gram-positive bacterium Anoxybacillus tepidamans (Geobacillus tepidamans) is involved in activation of fucose for incorporation into the organism's S-layer [2]. The enzyme from Escherichia coli O52 has a higher catalytic efficiency with NADH than with NADPH [3].
HISTORY     EC 1.1.1.266 created 2001, modified 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10358040]
  AUTHORS   Yoshida Y, Nakano Y, Nezu T, Yamashita Y, Koga T.
  TITLE     A novel NDP-6-deoxyhexosyl-4-ulose reductase in the pathway for the synthesis of thymidine diphosphate-D-fucose.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 274 (1999) 16933-9.
  ORGANISM  Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:17202151]
  AUTHORS   Zayni S, Steiner K, Pfostl A, Hofinger A, Kosma P, Schaffer C, Messner P
  TITLE     The dTDP-4-dehydro-6-deoxyglucose reductase encoding fcd gene is part of the surface layer glycoprotein glycosylation gene cluster of Geobacillus tepidamans GS5-97T.
  JOURNAL   Glycobiology. 17 (2007) 433-43.
  ORGANISM  Anoxybacillus tepidamans
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:19019146]
  AUTHORS   Wang Q, Ding P, Perepelov AV, Xu Y, Wang Y, Knirel YA, Wang L, Feng L
  TITLE     Characterization of the dTDP-D-fucofuranose biosynthetic pathway in Escherichia coli O52.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 70 (2008) 1358-67.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli O52
PATHWAY     ec00523  Polyketide sugar unit biosynthesis
ORTHOLOGY   K13306  dTDP-4-dehydro-6-deoxyglucose reductase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.1.266
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.1.266
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.1.266
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.1.266
///
