ENTRY       EC 1.1.99.29                Enzyme
NAME        pyranose dehydrogenase (acceptor);
            pyranose dehydrogenase;
            pyranose-quinone oxidoreductase;
            quinone-dependent pyranose dehydrogenase;
            PDH
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With other acceptors
SYSNAME     pyranose:acceptor oxidoreductase
REACTION    (1) a pyranose + acceptor = a pyranos-2-ulose (or a pyranos-3-ulose or a pyranos-2,3-diulose) + reduced acceptor [RN:R07347];
            (2) a pyranoside + acceptor = a pyranosid-3-ulose (or a pyranosid-3,4-diulose) + reduced acceptor [RN:R07348]
ALL_REAC    R07347 R07348
SUBSTRATE   pyranose [CPD:C15592];
            acceptor [CPD:C00028];
            pyranoside [CPD:C15594]
PRODUCT     pyranos-2-ulose;
            pyranos-3-ulose;
            pyranos-2,3-diulose;
            reduced acceptor [CPD:C00030];
            pyranosid-3-ulose;
            pyranosid-3,4-diulose
COMMENT     Requires FAD. A number of aldoses and ketoses in pyranose form, as well as glycosides, gluco-oligosaccharides, sucrose and lactose can act as a donor. 1,4-Benzoquinone or ferricenium ion (ferrocene oxidized by removal of one electron) can serve as acceptor. Unlike EC 1.1.3.10, pyranose oxidase, this fungal enzyme does not interact with O2 and exhibits extremely broad substrate tolerance with variable regioselectivity (C-3, C-2 or C-3 + C-2 or C-3 + C-4) for (di)oxidation of different sugars. D-Glucose is exclusively or preferentially oxidized at C-3 (depending on the enzyme source), but can also be oxidized at C-2 + C-3. The enzyme also acts on 1->4-alpha- and 1->4-beta-gluco-oligosaccharides, non-reducing gluco-oligosaccharides and L-arabinose, which are not substrates of EC 1.1.3.10. Sugars are oxidized in their pyranose but not in their furanose form.
HISTORY     EC 1.1.99.29 created 2004
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9042751]
  AUTHORS   Volc J, Kubatova E, Wood DA, Daniel G.
  TITLE     Pyranose 2-dehydrogenase, a novel sugar oxidoreductase from the basidiomycete fungus Agaricus bisporus
  JOURNAL   Arch. Microbiol. 167 (1997) 119-25.
  ORGANISM  Agaricus bisporus
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Volc, J., Sedmera, P., Halada, P., Poikyrlova, V. and Daniel, G.
  TITLE     C-2 and C-3 oxidation of D-Glc, and C-2 oxidation of D-Gal by pyranose dehydrogenase from Agaricus bisporus.
  JOURNAL   Carbohydr. Res. 310 (1998) 151-156.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11086703]
  AUTHORS   Volc J, Sedmera P, Halada P, Prikrylova V, Haltrich D.
  TITLE     Double oxidation of D-xylose to D-glycero -pentos-2,3-diulose (2,3-diketo-D-xylose) by pyranose dehydrogenase from the mushroom Agaricus bisporus.
  JOURNAL   Carbohydr. Res. 329 (2000) 219-25.
  ORGANISM  Agaricus bisporus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:11511865]
  AUTHORS   Volc J, Kubatova E, Daniel G, Sedmera P, Haltrich D.
  TITLE     Screening of basidiomycete fungi for the quinone-dependent sugar C-2/C-3 oxidoreductase, pyranose dehydrogenase, and properties of the enzyme from Macrolepiota rhacodes.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Microbiol. 176 (2001) 178-86.
  ORGANISM  Macrolepiota rhacodes
REFERENCE   5
  AUTHORS   Volc, J., Sedmera, P., Halada, P., Daniel, G., Poikyrlova, V. and Haltrich, D.
  TITLE     C-3 oxidation of non-reducing sugars by a fungal pyranose dehydrogenase: spectral characterization.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Catal., B Enzym. 17 (2002) 91-100.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.99.29
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.99.29
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.99.29
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.99.29
            CAS: 190606-21-4
///
