ENTRY       EC 1.1.1.236                Enzyme
NAME        tropinone reductase II;
            tropinone (psi-tropine-forming) reductase;
            pseudotropine forming tropinone reductase;
            tropinone reductase (ambiguous);
            TR-II
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With NAD+ or NADP+ as acceptor
SYSNAME     pseudotropine:NADP+ 3-oxidoreductase
REACTION    pseudotropine + NADP+ = tropinone + NADPH + H+ [RN:R06734]
ALL_REAC    R06734
SUBSTRATE   pseudotropine [CPD:C02066];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006]
PRODUCT     tropinone [CPD:C00783];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     This enzyme along with EC 1.1.1.206, tropine dehydrogenase, represents a branch point in tropane alkaloid metabolism [3]. Tropine (the product of EC 1.1.1.206) is incorporated into hyoscyamine and scopolamine whereas pseudotropine (the product of EC 1.1.1.236) is the first specific metabolite on the pathway to the calystegines [3]. Both enzymes are always found together in any given tropane-alkaloid-producing species, have a common substrate, tropinone, and are strictly stereospecific [2].
HISTORY     EC 1.1.1.236 created 1992, modified 2007
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Drager, B., Hashimoto, T. and Yamada, Y.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of pseudotropine forming tropinone reductase from Hyoscyamus niger root cultures.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 52 (1988) 2663-2667.
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Couladis, M.M, Friesen, J.B., Landgrebe, M.E. and Leete, E.
  TITLE     Enzymes catalysing the reduction of tropinone to tropine and psi-tropine isolated from the roots of Datura innoxia.
  JOURNAL   Pytochemistry 30 (1991) 801-805.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8415746]
  AUTHORS   Nakajima K, Hashimoto T, Yamada Y.
  TITLE     Two tropinone reductases with different stereospecificities are short-chain dehydrogenases evolved from a common ancestor.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 90 (1993) 9591-5.
  ORGANISM  Datura stramonium
  SEQUENCE  [up:P50163]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16426652]
  AUTHORS   Drager B.
  TITLE     Tropinone reductases, enzymes at the branch point of tropane alkaloid metabolism.
  JOURNAL   Phytochemistry. 67 (2006) 327-37.
  ORGANISM  Atropa belladonna, Datura stramonium, Hyoscyamus niger, Solanum tuberosum
PATHWAY     ec00960  Tropane, piperidine and pyridine alkaloid biosynthesis
ORTHOLOGY   K05354  tropinone reductase
GENES       SLY: 101256174
            SOT: 102589607(TRII)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.1.236
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.1.236
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.1.236
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.1.236
            CAS: 136111-61-0
///
