ENTRY       EC 1.1.1.318                Enzyme
NAME        eugenol synthase;
            LtCES1;
            EGS1;
            EGS2
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With NAD+ or NADP+ as acceptor
SYSNAME     eugenol:NADP+ oxidoreductase (coniferyl ester reducing)
REACTION    eugenol + a carboxylate + NADP+ = a coniferyl ester + NADPH + H+ [RN:R09930]
ALL_REAC    R09930 > R10248;
            (other) R10249
SUBSTRATE   eugenol [CPD:C10453];
            carboxylate [CPD:C00060];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006]
PRODUCT     coniferyl ester [CPD:C20224];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     The enzyme acts in the opposite direction. The enzymes from the plants Ocimum basilicum (sweet basil) [1,3], Clarkia breweri and Petunia hybrida [4] only accept coniferyl acetate and form eugenol. The enzyme from Pimpinella anisum (anise) forms anol (from 4-coumaryl acetate) in vivo, although the recombinant enzyme can form eugenol from coniferyl acetate [5]. The enzyme from Larrea tridentata (creosote bush) also forms chavicol from a coumaryl ester and can use NADH [2].
HISTORY     EC 1.1.1.318 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:16782809]
  AUTHORS   Koeduka T, Fridman E, Gang DR, Vassao DG, Jackson BL, Kish CM, Orlova I, Spassova SM, Lewis NG, Noel JP, Baiga TJ, Dudareva N, Pichersky E
  TITLE     Eugenol and isoeugenol, characteristic aromatic constituents of spices, are biosynthesized via reduction of a coniferyl alcohol ester.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 103 (2006) 10128-33.
  ORGANISM  Ocimum basilicum
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q15GI4]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:17624297]
  AUTHORS   Vassao DG, Kim SJ, Milhollan JK, Eichinger D, Davin LB, Lewis NG
  TITLE     A pinoresinol-lariciresinol reductase homologue from the creosote bush (Larrea tridentata) catalyzes the efficient in vitro conversion of p-coumaryl/coniferyl alcohol esters into the allylphenols chavicol/eugenol, but not the propenylphenols p-anol/isoeugenol.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 465 (2007) 209-18.
  ORGANISM  Larrea tridentata
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:17912370]
  AUTHORS   Louie GV, Baiga TJ, Bowman ME, Koeduka T, Taylor JH, Spassova SM, Pichersky E, Noel JP
  TITLE     Structure and reaction mechanism of basil eugenol synthase.
  JOURNAL   PLoS. One. 2 (2007) e993.
  ORGANISM  Ocimum basilicum
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q15GI4]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:18208524]
  AUTHORS   Koeduka T, Louie GV, Orlova I, Kish CM, Ibdah M, Wilkerson CG, Bowman ME, Baiga TJ, Noel JP, Dudareva N, Pichersky E
  TITLE     The multiple phenylpropene synthases in both Clarkia breweri and Petunia hybrida  represent two distinct protein lineages.
  JOURNAL   Plant. J. 54 (2008) 362-74.
  ORGANISM  Clarkia breweri, Petunia hybrida
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:18987218]
  AUTHORS   Koeduka T, Baiga TJ, Noel JP, Pichersky E
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of t-anethole in anise: characterization of t-anol/isoeugenol synthase and an O-methyltransferase specific for a C7-C8 propenyl side chain.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 149 (2009) 384-94.
  ORGANISM  Pimpinella anisum
PATHWAY     ec00940  Phenylpropanoid biosynthesis
ORTHOLOGY   K17055  eugenol synthase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.1.318
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.1.318
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.1.318
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.1.318
///
