ENTRY       EC 1.1.1.348                Enzyme
NAME        vestitone reductase;
            pterocarpin synthase (incorrect);
            pterocarpan synthase (incorrect)
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With NAD+ or NADP+ as acceptor
SYSNAME     (3R,4R)-4'-methoxyisoflavan-2',4,7-triol:NADP+ 4-oxidoreductase
REACTION    (3R,4R)-4'-methoxyisoflavan-2',4,7-triol + NADP+ = (3R)-vestitone + NADPH + H+ [RN:R07737]
ALL_REAC    R07737
SUBSTRATE   (3R,4R)-4'-methoxyisoflavan-2',4,7-triol [CPD:C16187];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006]
PRODUCT     (3R)-vestitone;
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     This plant enzyme catalyses the penultimate step in the biosynthesis of the pterocarpin phytoalexins medicarpin and maackiain. This activity was previously classified as part of EC 1.1.1.246, pterocarpin synthase, which is now known to be catalysed by two enzymes, vestitone reductase and EC 4.2.1.139, medicarpin synthase.
HISTORY     EC 1.1.1.348 created 1992 as EC 1.1.1.246, part transferred to EC 1.1.1.348 2013
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Bless, W. and Barz, W.
  TITLE     Isolation of pterocarpan synthase, the terminal enzyme of pterocarpan phytoalexin biosynthesis in cell-suspension cultures of Cicer arietinum.
  JOURNAL   FEBS Lett. 235 (1988) 47-50.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8071365]
  AUTHORS   Guo L, Dixon RA, Paiva NL.
  TITLE     Conversion of vestitone to medicarpin in alfalfa (Medicago sativa L.) is catalyzed by two independent enzymes. Identification, purification, and characterization of vestitone reductase and 7,2'-dihydroxy-4'-methoxyisoflavanol  dehydratase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 269 (1994) 22372-8.
  ORGANISM  Medicago sativa
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q40316]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:7805842]
  AUTHORS   Guo L, Dixon RA, Paiva NL
  TITLE     The 'pterocarpan synthase' of alfalfa: association and co-induction of vestitone  reductase and 7,2'-dihydroxy-4'-methoxy-isoflavanol (DMI) dehydratase, the two final enzymes in medicarpin biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 356 (1994) 221-5.
  ORGANISM  Medicago sativa
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q40316]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:7625843]
  AUTHORS   Guo L, Paiva NL
  TITLE     Molecular cloning and expression of alfalfa (Medicago sativa L.) vestitone reductase, the penultimate enzyme in medicarpin biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 320 (1995) 353-60.
  ORGANISM  Medicago sativa
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q40316] [mtr:MTR_7g074710] (Medicago truncatula)
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:17433362]
  AUTHORS   Shao H, Dixon RA, Wang X
  TITLE     Crystal structure of vestitone reductase from alfalfa (Medicago sativa L.).
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 369 (2007) 265-76.
  ORGANISM  Medicago sativa
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q40316]
PATHWAY     ec00943  Isoflavonoid biosynthesis
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K13265  vestitone reductase
GENES       GMX: 100793687
            MTR: MTR_7g074710
            CAM: 101514431
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.1.348
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.1.348
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.1.348
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.1.348
            CAS: 118477-70-6
///
