ENTRY       EC 1.1.99.35                Enzyme
NAME        soluble quinoprotein glucose dehydrogenase;
            soluble glucose dehydrogenase;
            sGDH;
            glucose dehydrogenase (PQQ-dependent)
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With other acceptors
SYSNAME     D-glucose:acceptor oxidoreductase
REACTION    D-glucose + acceptor = D-glucono-1,5-lactone + reduced acceptor [RN:R10411]
ALL_REAC    R10411
SUBSTRATE   D-glucose [CPD:C00031];
            acceptor [CPD:C00028]
PRODUCT     D-glucono-1,5-lactone [CPD:C00198];
            reduced acceptor [CPD:C00030]
COMMENT     Soluble periplasmic enzyme containing PQQ as prosthetic group, bound to a calcium ion. Electron acceptor is not known. It is assayed with Wurster's Blue or phenazine methosulphate. It has negligible sequence or structure similarity to other quinoproteins. It catalyses an exceptionally high rate of oxidation of a wide range of aldose sugars, including D-glucose, galactose, arabinose and xylose, and also the disaccharides lactose, cellobiose and maltose. It has been described only in Acinetobacter calcoaceticus.
HISTORY     EC 1.1.99.35 created 2010
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Geiger, O. and Gorisch, H.
  TITLE     Crystalline quinoprotein glucose dehydrogenase from Acinetobacter calcoaceticus.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry 25 (1986) 6043-6048.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:3800975]
  AUTHORS   Dokter P, Frank J, Duine JA
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of quinoprotein glucose dehydrogenase from Acinetobacter calcoaceticus L.M.D. 79.41.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 239 (1986) 163-7.
  ORGANISM  Acinetobacter calcoaceticus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:2834325]
  AUTHORS   Cleton-Jansen AM, Goosen N, Wenzel TJ, van de Putte P
  TITLE     Cloning of the gene encoding quinoprotein glucose dehydrogenase from Acinetobacter calcoaceticus: evidence for the presence of a second enzyme.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 170 (1988) 2121-5.
  ORGANISM  Acinetobacter calcoaceticus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:2551369]
  AUTHORS   Matsushita K, Shinagawa E, Adachi O, Ameyama M
  TITLE     Quinoprotein D-glucose dehydrogenase of the Acinetobacter calcoaceticus respiratory chain: membrane-bound and soluble forms are different molecular species.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 28 (1989) 6276-80.
  ORGANISM  Acinetobacter calcoaceticus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:10933491]
  AUTHORS   Oubrie A, Dijkstra BW
  TITLE     Structural requirements of pyrroloquinoline quinone dependent enzymatic reactions.
  JOURNAL   Protein. Sci. 9 (2000) 1265-73.
  ORGANISM  Acinetobacter calcoaceticus
REFERENCE   6
  AUTHORS   Matsushita, K., Toyama, H., Ameyama, M., Adachi, O., Dewanti, A. and Duine, J.A.
  TITLE     Soluble and membrane-bound quinoprotein D-glucose dehydrogenases of the Acinetobacter calcoaceticus : the binding process of PQQ to the apoenzymes.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 59 (1995) 1548-1555.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.99.35
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.99.35
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.99.35
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.99.35
///
