ENTRY       EC 1.1.5.5                  Enzyme
NAME        alcohol dehydrogenase (quinone);
            type III ADH;
            membrane associated quinohaemoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-OH group of donors;
            With a quinone or similar compound as acceptor
SYSNAME     alcohol:quinone oxidoreductase
REACTION    ethanol + ubiquinone = acetaldehyde + ubiquinol [RN:R09479]
ALL_REAC    R09479
SUBSTRATE   ethanol [CPD:C00469];
            ubiquinone [CPD:C00399]
PRODUCT     acetaldehyde [CPD:C00084];
            ubiquinol [CPD:C00390]
COMMENT     Only described in acetic acid bacteria where it is involved in acetic acid production. Associated with membrane. Electron acceptor is membrane ubiquinone. A model structure suggests that, like all other quinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenases, the catalytic subunit has an 8-bladed 'propeller' structure, a calcium ion bound to the PQQ in the active site and an unusual disulfide ring structure in close proximity to the PQQ; the catalytic subunit also has a heme c in the C-terminal domain. The enzyme has two additional subunits, one of which contains three molecules of heme c. It does not require amines for activation. It has a restricted substrate specificity, oxidizing a few primary alcohols (C2 to C6), but not methanol, secondary alcohols and some aldehydes. It is assayed with phenazine methosulfate or with ferricyanide.
HISTORY     EC 1.1.5.5 created 2009, modified 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:18321602]
  AUTHORS   Gomez-Manzo S, Contreras-Zentella M, Gonzalez-Valdez A, Sosa-Torres M, Arreguin-Espinoza R, Escamilla-Marvan E
  TITLE     The PQQ-alcohol dehydrogenase of Gluconacetobacter diazotrophicus.
  JOURNAL   Int. J. Food. Microbiol. 125 (2008) 71-8.
  ORGANISM  Gluconacetobacter diazotrophicus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16636451]
  AUTHORS   Shinagawa E, Toyama H, Matsushita K, Tuitemwong P, Theeragool G, Adachi O
  TITLE     A novel type of formaldehyde-oxidizing enzyme from the membrane of Acetobacter sp. SKU 14.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 70 (2006) 850-7.
  ORGANISM  Acetobacter sp.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16233574]
  AUTHORS   Chinnawirotpisan P, Theeragool G, Limtong S, Toyama H, Adachi OO, Matsushita K
  TITLE     Quinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase is involved in catabolic acetate production, while NAD-dependent alcohol dehydrogenase in ethanol assimilation in Acetobacter  pasteurianus SKU1108.
  JOURNAL   J. Biosci. Bioeng. 96 (2003) 564-71.
  ORGANISM  Acetobacter pasteurianus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9526036]
  AUTHORS   Frebortova J, Matsushita K, Arata H, Adachi O
  TITLE     Intramolecular electron transport in quinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase of Acetobacter methanolicus: a redox-titration study
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1363 (1998) 24-34.
  ORGANISM  Acetobacter methanolicus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:18838797]
  AUTHORS   Matsushita K, Kobayashi Y, Mizuguchi M, Toyama H, Adachi O, Sakamoto K, Miyoshi H
  TITLE     A tightly bound quinone functions in the ubiquinone reaction sites of quinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase of an acetic acid bacterium, Gluconobacter suboxydans.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 72 (2008) 2723-31.
  ORGANISM  Gluconobacter suboxydans
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:8617755]
  AUTHORS   Matsushita K, Yakushi T, Toyama H, Shinagawa E, Adachi O
  TITLE     Function of multiple heme c moieties in intramolecular electron transport and ubiquinone reduction in the quinohemoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase-cytochrome c complex of Gluconobacter suboxydans.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 271 (1996) 4850-7.
  ORGANISM  Gluconobacter suboxydans
REFERENCE   7
  AUTHORS   Matsushita, K., Takaki, Y., Shinagawa, E., Ameyama, M. and Adachi, O.
  TITLE     Ethanol oxidase respiratory chain of acetic acid bacteria. Reactivity with ubiquinone of pyrroloquinolinequinone-dependent alcohol dehydrogenases purified from Acetobacter aceti and Gluconobacter suboxydans.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 56 (1992) 304-310.
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:7942316]
  AUTHORS   Matsushita K, Toyama H, Adachi O
  TITLE     Respiratory chains and bioenergetics of acetic acid bacteria.
  JOURNAL   Adv. Microb. Physiol. 36 (1994) 247-301.
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:7772016]
  AUTHORS   Cozier GE, Giles IG, Anthony C
  TITLE     The structure of the quinoprotein alcohol dehydrogenase of Acetobacter aceti modelled on that of methanol dehydrogenase from Methylobacterium extorquens.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 308 ( Pt 2) (1995) 375-9.
  ORGANISM  Acetobacter aceti
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.1.5.5
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.1.5.5
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.1.5.5
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.1.5.5
///
