ENTRY       EC 1.10.3.13                Enzyme
NAME        caldariellaquinol oxidase (H+-transporting);
            SoxABCD quinol oxidase;
            SoxABCD complex;
            quinol oxidase SoxABCD;
            SoxM supercomplex;
            aa3-type quinol oxidase;
            aa3 quinol oxidase;
            cytochrome aa3;
            terminal quinol oxidase;
            terminal quinol:oxygen oxidoreductase;
            caldariella quinol:dioxygen oxidoreductase;
            cytochrome aa3-type oxidase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on diphenols and related substances as donors;
            With oxygen as acceptor
SYSNAME     caldariellaquinol:O2 oxidoreductase (H+-transporting)
REACTION    2 caldariellaquinol + O2 + n H+[side 1] = 2 caldariellaquinone + 2 H2O + n H+[side 2] [RN:R10444]
ALL_REAC    R10444
SUBSTRATE   caldariellaquinol [CPD:C20623];
            O2 [CPD:C00007];
            H+[side 1]
PRODUCT     caldariellaquinone [CPD:C20624];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            H+[side 2]
COMMENT     A copper-containing cytochrome. The enzyme from thermophilic archaea is part of the terminal oxidase and catalyses the reduction of O2 to water, accompanied by the extrusion of protons across the cytoplasmic membrane.
HISTORY     EC 1.10.3.13 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9079667]
  AUTHORS   Gleissner M, Kaiser U, Antonopoulos E, Schafer G
  TITLE     The archaeal SoxABCD complex is a proton pump in Sulfolobus acidocaldarius.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 272 (1997) 8417-26.
  ORGANISM  Sulfolobus acidocaldarius
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9023221]
  AUTHORS   Purschke WG, Schmidt CL, Petersen A, Schafer G
  TITLE     The terminal quinol oxidase of the hyperthermophilic archaeon Acidianus ambivalens exhibits a novel subunit structure and gene organization.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 179 (1997) 1344-53.
  ORGANISM  Acidianus ambivalens
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11115638]
  AUTHORS   Gilderson G, Aagaard A, Gomes CM, Adelroth P, Teixeira M, Brzezinski P
  TITLE     Kinetics of electron and proton transfer during O(2) reduction in cytochrome aa(3) from A. ambivalens: an enzyme lacking Glu(I-286).
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1503 (2001) 261-70.
  ORGANISM  Acidianus ambivalens
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12530544]
  AUTHORS   Komorowski L, Verheyen W, Schafer G
  TITLE     The archaeal respiratory supercomplex SoxM from S. acidocaldarius combines features of quinole and cytochrome c oxidases.
  JOURNAL   Biol. Chem. 383 (2002) 1791-9.
  ORGANISM  Sulfolobus acidocaldarius
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15306018]
  AUTHORS   Muller FH, Bandeiras TM, Urich T, Teixeira M, Gomes CM, Kletzin A.
  TITLE     Coupling of the pathway of sulphur oxidation to dioxygen reduction: characterization of a novel membrane-bound thiosulphate:quinone oxidoreductase.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 53 (2004) 1147-60.
  ORGANISM  Acidianus ambivalens
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:16163550]
  AUTHORS   Bandeiras TM, Pereira MM, Teixeira M, Moenne-Loccoz P, Blackburn NJ
  TITLE     Structure and coordination of CuB in the Acidianus ambivalens aa3 quinol oxidase  heme-copper center.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Inorg. Chem. 10 (2005) 625-35.
  ORGANISM  Acidianus ambivalens
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.10.3.13
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.10.3.13
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.10.3.13
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.10.3.13
///
