ENTRY       EC 1.10.3.10                Enzyme
NAME        ubiquinol oxidase (H+-transporting);
            cytochrome bb3 oxidase;
            cytochrome bo oxidase;
            cytochrome bd-I oxidase;
            cytochrome bd-II oxidase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on diphenols and related substances as donors;
            With oxygen as acceptor
SYSNAME     ubiquinol:O2 oxidoreductase (H+-transporting)
REACTION    2 ubiquinol + O2 + n H+[side 1] = 2 ubiquinone + 2 H2O + n H+[side 2] [RN:R09504]
ALL_REAC    R09504
SUBSTRATE   ubiquinol [CPD:C00390];
            O2 [CPD:C00007];
            H+[side 1]
PRODUCT     ubiquinone [CPD:C00399];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            H+[side 2]
COMMENT     Contains a dinuclear centre comprising two hemes, or heme and copper. Reduction of O2 on the periplasmic side of the membrane leads to release of protons in the periplasm, generating a transmembrane proton gradient. In addition, the cytochrome bb3 and cytochrome bo oxidases, but not the cytochrome bd oxidases, contribute to the proton gradient by actively pumping protons across the membrane.
HISTORY     EC 1.10.3.10 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:11017202]
  AUTHORS   Abramson J, Riistama S, Larsson G, Jasaitis A, Svensson-Ek M, Laakkonen L, Puustinen A, Iwata S, Wikstrom M
  TITLE     The structure of the ubiquinol oxidase from Escherichia coli and its ubiquinone binding site.
  JOURNAL   Nat. Struct. Biol. 7 (2000) 910-7.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [up:P0ABI8]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:15728392]
  AUTHORS   Belevich I, Borisov VB, Zhang J, Yang K, Konstantinov AA, Gennis RB, Verkhovsky MI
  TITLE     Time-resolved electrometric and optical studies on cytochrome bd suggest a mechanism of electron-proton coupling in the di-heme active site.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 102 (2005) 3657-62.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:20416270]
  AUTHORS   Yap LL, Lin MT, Ouyang H, Samoilova RI, Dikanov SA, Gennis RB
  TITLE     The quinone-binding sites of the cytochrome bo3 ubiquinol oxidase from Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1797 (2010) 1924-32.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:20392690]
  AUTHORS   Shepherd M, Sanguinetti G, Cook GM, Poole RK
  TITLE     Compensations for diminished terminal oxidase activity in Escherichia coli: cytochrome bd-II-mediated respiration and glutamate metabolism.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 285 (2010) 18464-72.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:21987791]
  AUTHORS   Borisov VB, Murali R, Verkhovskaya ML, Bloch DA, Han H, Gennis RB, Verkhovsky MI
  TITLE     Aerobic respiratory chain of Escherichia coli is not allowed to work in fully uncoupled mode.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 108 (2011) 17320-4.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.10.3.10
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.10.3.10
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.10.3.10
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.10.3.10
///
