ENTRY       EC 1.10.3.14                Enzyme
NAME        ubiquinol oxidase (electrogenic, non H+-transporting);
            cytochrome bd-I oxidase;
            cydA (gene name);
            cydB (gene name)
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on diphenols and related substances as donors;
            With oxygen as acceptor
SYSNAME     ubiquinol:O2 oxidoreductase (electrogenic, non H+-transporting)
REACTION    2 ubiquinol + O2 + 4 H+[side 1] = 2 ubiquinone + 2 H2O + 4 H+[side 2]
SUBSTRATE   ubiquinol [CPD:C00390];
            O2 [CPD:C00007];
            H+[side 1]
PRODUCT     ubiquinone [CPD:C00399];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            H+[side 2]
COMMENT     This terminal oxidase enzyme is unable to pump protons but generates a proton motive force by transmembrane charge separation resulting from utilizing protons and electrons originating from opposite sides of the membrane to generate water. The bioenergetic efficiency (the number of charges driven across the membrane per electron used to reduce oxygen to water) is 1. The bd-I oxidase from the bacterium Escherichia coli is the predominant respiratory oxygen reductase that functions under microaerophilic conditions in that organism. cf. EC 1.10.3.10, ubiquinol oxidase (H+-transporting).
HISTORY     EC 1.10.3.14 created 2014
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3281937]
  AUTHORS   Miller MJ, Hermodson M, Gennis RB
  TITLE     The active form of the cytochrome d terminal oxidase complex of Escherichia coli  is a heterodimer containing one copy of each of the two subunits.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 263 (1988) 5235-40.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:1850294]
  AUTHORS   Puustinen A, Finel M, Haltia T, Gennis RB, Wikstrom M
  TITLE     Properties of the two terminal oxidases of Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 30 (1991) 3936-42.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:15728392]
  AUTHORS   Belevich I, Borisov VB, Zhang J, Yang K, Konstantinov AA, Gennis RB, Verkhovsky MI
  TITLE     Time-resolved electrometric and optical studies on cytochrome bd suggest a mechanism of electron-proton coupling in the di-heme active site.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 102 (2005) 3657-62.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:19019148]
  AUTHORS   Lenn T, Leake MC, Mullineaux CW
  TITLE     Clustering and dynamics of cytochrome bd-I complexes in the Escherichia coli plasma membrane in vivo.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 70 (2008) 1397-407.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.10.3.14
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.10.3.14
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.10.3.14
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.10.3.14
///
