ENTRY       EC 1.11.1.14                Enzyme
NAME        lignin peroxidase;
            diarylpropane oxygenase;
            ligninase I;
            diarylpropane peroxidase;
            LiP;
            diarylpropane:oxygen,hydrogen-peroxide oxidoreductase (C-C-bond-cleaving)
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on a peroxide as acceptor;
            Peroxidases
SYSNAME     1,2-bis(3,4-dimethoxyphenyl)propane-1,3-diol:hydrogen-peroxide oxidoreductase
REACTION    (3,4-dimethoxyphenyl)methanol + H2O2 = 3,4-dimethoxybenzaldehyde + 2 H2O [RN:R04461]
ALL_REAC    R04461
SUBSTRATE   (3,4-dimethoxyphenyl)methanol;
            H2O2 [CPD:C00027]
PRODUCT     3,4-dimethoxybenzaldehyde [CPD:C02201];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     A hemoprotein, involved in the oxidative breakdown of lignin by white-rot basidiomycete fungi. The enzyme from Phanerochaete chrysosporium oxidizes typical peroxidase dye substrates at the heme iron, a reaction involving the formation of Compound II (FeIV=O); it also oxidizes (3,4-dimethoxyphenyl)methanol (veratryl alcohol) to the radical cation. The bound veratryl alcohol radical is proposed to bring about the oxidative cleavage of C-C and ether (C-O-C) bonds in lignin model compounds of the diarylpropane and arylpropane-aryl ether type.
HISTORY     EC 1.11.1.14 created 1992, modified 2006, modified 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:2982828]
  AUTHORS   Kersten PJ, Tien M, Kalyanaraman B, Kirk TK.
  TITLE     The ligninase of Phanerochaete chrysosporium generates cation radicals from methoxybenzenes.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 260 (1985) 2609-12.
  ORGANISM  Phanerochaete chrysosporium
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:3080953]
  AUTHORS   Paszczynski A, Huynh VB, Crawford R.
  TITLE     Comparison of ligninase-I and peroxidase-M2 from the white-rot fungus Phanerochaete chrysosporium.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 244 (1986) 750-65.
  ORGANISM  Phanerochaete chrysosporium
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   Harvey, P.J., Schoemaker, H.E. and Palmer, J.M.
  TITLE     Veratryl alcohol as a mediator and the role of radical cations in lignin biodegradation by Phanerochaete chrysosporium.
  JOURNAL   FEBS Lett. 195 (1986) 242-246.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9790672]
  AUTHORS   Doyle WA, Blodig W, Veitch NC, Piontek K, Smith AT.
  TITLE     Two substrate interaction sites in lignin peroxidase revealed by site-directed mutagenesis.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 37 (1998) 15097-105.
  ORGANISM  Phanerochaete chrysosporium
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:2162833]
  AUTHORS   Wariishi H, Marquez L, Dunford HB, Gold MH.
  TITLE     Lignin peroxidase compounds II and III. Spectral and kinetic characterization of reactions with peroxides.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 265 (1990) 11137-42.
  ORGANISM  Phanerochaete chrysosporium
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:2328240]
  AUTHORS   Cai DY, Tien M.
  TITLE     Characterization of the oxycomplex of lignin peroxidases from Phanerochaete chrysosporium: equilibrium and kinetics studies.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 29 (1990) 2085-91.
  ORGANISM  Phanerochaete chrysosporium
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:8527462]
  AUTHORS   Khindaria A, Yamazaki I, Aust SD
  TITLE     Veratryl alcohol oxidation by lignin peroxidase.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 34 (1995) 16860-9.
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:8639588]
  AUTHORS   Khindaria A, Yamazaki I, Aust SD
  TITLE     Stabilization of the veratryl alcohol cation radical by lignin peroxidase.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 35 (1996) 6418-24.
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:9369491]
  AUTHORS   Khindaria A, Nie G, Aust SD
  TITLE     Detection and characterization of the lignin peroxidase compound II-veratryl alcohol cation radical complex.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 36 (1997) 14181-5.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.11.1.14
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.11.1.14
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.11.1.14
            UM-BBD (Biocatalysis/Biodegradation Database): 1.11.1.14
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.11.1.14
            CAS: 93792-13-3
///
