ENTRY       EC 1.11.1.19                Enzyme
NAME        dye decolorizing peroxidase;
            DyP;
            DyP-type peroxidase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on a peroxide as acceptor;
            Peroxidases
SYSNAME     Reactive-Blue-5:hydrogen-peroxide oxidoreductase
REACTION    Reactive Blue 5 + H2O2 = phthalate + 2,2'-disulfonyl azobenzene + 3-[(4-amino-6-chloro-1,3,5-triazin-2-yl)amino]benzenesulfonate
SUBSTRATE   Reactive Blue 5 [CPD:C19693];
            H2O2 [CPD:C00027]
PRODUCT     phthalate [CPD:C01606];
            2,2'-disulfonyl azobenzene;
            3-[(4-amino-6-chloro-1,3,5-triazin-2-yl)amino]benzenesulfonate
COMMENT     Heme proteins with proximal histidine secreted by basidiomycetous fungi and eubacteria. They are similar to EC 1.11.1.16 versatile peroxidase (oxidation of Reactive Black 5, phenols, veratryl alcohol), but differ from the latter in their ability to oxidize a number of recalcitrant anthraquinone dyes efficiently, and inability to oxidize Mn(II). The model substrate Reactive Blue 5 is converted with high efficiency via a so far unique mechanism that combines oxidative and hydrolytic steps and leads to the formation of phthalic acid. Bacterial TfuDyP catalyses sulfoxidation.
HISTORY     EC 1.11.1.19 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10049859]
  AUTHORS   Kim SJ, Shoda M
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of a novel peroxidase from Geotrichum candidum  dec 1 involved in decolorization of dyes.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 65 (1999) 1029-35.
  ORGANISM  Thanatephorus cucumeris
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:15313183]
  AUTHORS   Sugano Y, Ishii Y, Shoda M
  TITLE     Role of H164 in a unique dye-decolorizing heme peroxidase DyP.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 322 (2004) 126-32.
  ORGANISM  Thanatephorus cucumeris
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:17654547]
  AUTHORS   Zubieta C, Joseph R, Krishna SS, McMullan D, Kapoor M, Axelrod HL, Miller MD, Abdubek P, Acosta C, Astakhova T, Carlton D, Chiu HJ, Clayton T, Deller MC, Duan L, Elias Y, Elsliger MA, Feuerhelm J, Grzechnik SK, Hale J, Han GW, Jaroszewski L, Jin KK, Klock HE, Knuth MW, Kozbial P, Kumar A, Marciano D, Morse AT, Murphy KD, Nigoghossian E, Okach L, Oommachen S, Reyes R, Rife CL, Schimmel P, Trout CV, van den Bedem H, Weekes D, White A, Xu Q, Hodgson KO, Wooley J, Deacon AM, Godzik A, Lesley SA, Wilson IA
  TITLE     Identification and structural characterization of heme binding in a novel dye-decolorizing peroxidase, TyrA.
  JOURNAL   Proteins. 69 (2007) 234-43.
  ORGANISM  Thanatephorus cucumeris
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:19009358]
  AUTHORS   Sugano Y, Matsushima Y, Tsuchiya K, Aoki H, Hirai M, Shoda M
  TITLE     Degradation pathway of an anthraquinone dye catalyzed by a unique peroxidase DyP  from Thanatephorus cucumeris Dec 1.
  JOURNAL   Biodegradation. 20 (2009) 433-40.
  ORGANISM  Thanatephorus cucumeris
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:19099183]
  AUTHORS   Sugano Y
  TITLE     DyP-type peroxidases comprise a novel heme peroxidase family.
  JOURNAL   Cell. Mol. Life. Sci. 66 (2009) 1387-403.
  ORGANISM  Thanatephorus cucumeris
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:19801472]
  AUTHORS   Ogola HJ, Kamiike T, Hashimoto N, Ashida H, Ishikawa T, Shibata H, Sawa Y
  TITLE     Molecular characterization of a novel peroxidase from the cyanobacterium Anabaena sp. strain PCC 7120.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 75 (2009) 7509-18.
  ORGANISM  Anabaena sp.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:19967355]
  AUTHORS   van Bloois E, Torres Pazmino DE, Winter RT, Fraaije MW
  TITLE     A robust and extracellular heme-containing peroxidase from Thermobifida fusca as  prototype of a bacterial peroxidase superfamily.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 86 (2010) 1419-30.
  ORGANISM  Thermobifida fusca
  SEQUENCE  [tfu:Tfu_3078]
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:19756587]
  AUTHORS   Liers C, Bobeth C, Pecyna M, Ullrich R, Hofrichter M
  TITLE     DyP-like peroxidases of the jelly fungus Auricularia auricula-judae oxidize nonphenolic lignin model compounds and high-redox potential dyes.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 85 (2010) 1869-79.
  ORGANISM  Auricularia auricula-judae
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:20495915]
  AUTHORS   Hofrichter M, Ullrich R, Pecyna MJ, Liers C, Lundell T
  TITLE     New and classic families of secreted fungal heme peroxidases.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 87 (2010) 871-97.
ORTHOLOGY   K15733  dye decolorizing peroxidase
GENES       MSM: MSMEG_6567
            MVA: Mvan_2157
            MGI: Mflv_4209
            MSP: Mspyr1_35510
            MAB: MAB_2270c
            MMC: Mmcs_1602
            MKM: Mkms_1626
            MJL: Mjls_1572
            CGL: NCgl1608(Cgl1672)
            CGB: cg1881
            CGT: cgR_1717
            CEF: CE1786
            CDI: DIP1389
            CJK: jk1067
            CUR: cur_0924
            CAR: cauri_1433
            CKP: ckrop_1041
            CPU: cpfrc_01191
            CRD: CRES_1149
            CUL: CULC22_01299
            CVA: CVAR_1560
            NFA: nfa15910 nfa30690
            RER: RER_11620
            ROP: ROP_30550
            REQ: REQ_10240
            SCO: SCO3963(SCD78.30c)
            SMA: SAV_4242
            SGR: SGR_3628 SGR_7076t
            SCB: SCAB_46581
            SSX: SACTE_3382
            SVL: Strvi_9152
            LXX: Lxx21010
            MTS: MTES_2548
            AAI: AARI_30420
            KRH: KRH_03680
            MLU: Mlut_19120
            RDN: HMPREF0733_11291
            BFA: Bfae_31010
            JDE: Jden_1171
            KSE: Ksed_04140
            SKE: Sked_11720
            ICA: Intca_2358
            NCA: Noca_2002
            KFL: Kfla_3710 Kfla_4016
            TFU: Tfu_3078
            NDA: Ndas_1777 Ndas_3579
            TCU: Tcur_2987
            SRO: Sros_3398
            FRA: Francci3_2498
            FAL: FRAAL0168
            NML: Namu_5006
            SVI: Svir_39250
            STP: Strop_2590
            SAQ: Sare_2788
            MAU: Micau_3669
            MIL: ML5_4729
            VMA: VAB18032_06855
            CAI: Caci_3064 Caci_6261
            SNA: Snas_2163
            MCU: HMPREF0573_10175
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.11.1.19
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.11.1.19
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.11.1.19
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.11.1.19
///
