ENTRY       EC 1.11.2.1                 Enzyme
NAME        unspecific peroxygenase;
            aromatic peroxygenase;
            mushroom peroxygenase;
            haloperoxidase-peroxygenase;
            Agrocybe aegerita peroxidase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on a peroxide as acceptor;
            Peroxygenases
SYSNAME     substrate:hydrogen peroxide oxidoreductase (RH-hydroxylating or -epoxidising)
REACTION    RH + H2O2 = ROH + H2O [RN:R09507]
ALL_REAC    R09507
SUBSTRATE   RH [CPD:C01371];
            H2O2 [CPD:C00027]
PRODUCT     ROH [CPD:C01335];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     A heme-thiolate protein (P450). Enzymes of this type include glycoproteins secreted by agaric basidiomycetes. They catalyse the insertion of an oxygen atom from H2O2 into a wide variety of substrates, including aromatic rings such as naphthalene, toluene, phenanthrene, pyrene and p-nitrophenol, recalcitrant heterocycles such as pyridine, dibenzofuran, various ethers (resulting in O-dealkylation) and alkanes such as propane, hexane and cyclohexane. Reactions catalysed include hydroxylation, epoxidation, N-oxidation, sulfooxidation, O- and N-dealkylation, bromination and one-electron oxidations. They have little or no activity toward chloride. Mechanistically, the catalytic cycle of unspecific (mono)-peroxygenases combines elements of the "shunt" pathway of cytochrome P450s (a side activity that utilizes a peroxide in place of dioxygen and NAD[P]H) and the classic heme peroxidase cycle.
HISTORY     EC 1.11.2.1 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:15294788]
  AUTHORS   Ullrich R, Nuske J, Scheibner K, Spantzel J, Hofrichter M
  TITLE     Novel haloperoxidase from the agaric basidiomycete Agrocybe aegerita oxidizes aryl alcohols and aldehydes.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 70 (2004) 4575-81.
  ORGANISM  Agrocybe aegerita
  SEQUENCE  [up:B9W4V6]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16253244]
  AUTHORS   Ullrich R, Hofrichter M
  TITLE     The haloperoxidase of the agaric fungus Agrocybe aegerita hydroxylates toluene and naphthalene.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 579 (2005) 6247-50.
  ORGANISM  Agrocybe aegerita
  SEQUENCE  [up:B9W4V6]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:17601809]
  AUTHORS   Anh DH, Ullrich R, Benndorf D, Svatos A, Muck A, Hofrichter M
  TITLE     The coprophilous mushroom Coprinus radians secretes a haloperoxidase that catalyzes aromatic peroxygenation.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 73 (2007) 5477-85.
  ORGANISM  Coprinellus radians
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:19022254]
  AUTHORS   Ullrich R, Dolge C, Kluge M, Hofrichter M
  TITLE     Pyridine as novel substrate for regioselective oxygenation with aromatic peroxygenase from Agrocybe aegerita.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 582 (2008) 4100-6.
  ORGANISM  Agrocybe aegerita
  SEQUENCE  [up:B9W4V6]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:19039585]
  AUTHORS   Aranda E, Kinne M, Kluge M, Ullrich R, Hofrichter M
  TITLE     Conversion of dibenzothiophene by the mushrooms Agrocybe aegerita and Coprinellus radians and their extracellular peroxygenases.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 82 (2009) 1057-66.
  ORGANISM  Agrocybe aegerita, Coprinellus radians
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:19394224]
  AUTHORS   Kinne M, Poraj-Kobielska M, Aranda E, Ullrich R, Hammel KE, Scheibner K, Hofrichter M
  TITLE     Regioselective preparation of 5-hydroxypropranolol and 4'-hydroxydiclofenac with  a fungal peroxygenase.
  JOURNAL   Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett. 19 (2009) 3085-7.
  ORGANISM  Agrocybe aegerita
  SEQUENCE  [up:B9W4V6]
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:18815784]
  AUTHORS   Kluge M, Ullrich R, Dolge C, Scheibner K, Hofrichter M
  TITLE     Hydroxylation of naphthalene by aromatic peroxygenase from Agrocybe aegerita proceeds via oxygen transfer from H2O2 and intermediary epoxidation.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 81 (2009) 1071-6.
  ORGANISM  Agrocybe aegerita
  SEQUENCE  [up:B9W4V6]
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:19713216]
  AUTHORS   Kinne M, Poraj-Kobielska M, Ralph SA, Ullrich R, Hofrichter M, Hammel KE
  TITLE     Oxidative cleavage of diverse ethers by an extracellular fungal peroxygenase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 284 (2009) 29343-9.
  ORGANISM  Agrocybe aegerita
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:19434406]
  AUTHORS   Pecyna MJ, Ullrich R, Bittner B, Clemens A, Scheibner K, Schubert R, Hofrichter M
  TITLE     Molecular characterization of aromatic peroxygenase from Agrocybe aegerita.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 84 (2009) 885-97.
  ORGANISM  Agrocybe aegerita
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.11.2.1
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.11.2.1
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.11.2.1
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.11.2.1
///
