ENTRY       EC 1.11.1.16                Enzyme
NAME        versatile peroxidase;
            VP;
            hybrid peroxidase;
            polyvalent peroxidase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on a peroxide as acceptor;
            Peroxidases
SYSNAME     reactive-black-5:hydrogen-peroxide oxidoreductase
REACTION    (1) Reactive Black 5 + H2O2 = oxidized Reactive Black 5 + 2 H2O [RN:R07612];
            (2) donor + H2O2 = oxidized donor + 2 H2O [RN:R03532]
ALL_REAC    R03532 R07612
SUBSTRATE   Reactive Black 5 [CPD:C16001];
            H2O2 [CPD:C00027];
            donor [CPD:C00030]
PRODUCT     oxidized Reactive Black 5 [CPD:C16002];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            oxidized donor [CPD:C00028]
COMMENT     A hemoprotein. This ligninolytic peroxidase combines the substrate-specificity characteristics of the two other ligninolytic peroxidases, EC 1.11.1.13, manganese peroxidase and EC 1.11.1.14, lignin peroxidase. It is also able to oxidize phenols, hydroquinones and both low- and high-redox-potential dyes, due to a hybrid molecular architecture that involves multiple binding sites for substrates [2,4].
HISTORY     EC 1.11.1.16 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8647081]
  AUTHORS   Martinez MJ, Ruiz-Duenas FJ, Guillen F, Martinez AT.
  TITLE     Purification and catalytic properties of two manganese peroxidase isoenzymes from Pleurotus eryngii.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 237 (1996) 424-32.
  ORGANISM  Pleurotus eryngii
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9654123]
  AUTHORS   Heinfling A, Ruiz-Duenas FJ, Martinez MJ, Bergbauer M, Szewzyk U, Martinez AT.
  TITLE     A study on reducing substrates of manganese-oxidizing peroxidases from Pleurotus eryngii and Bjerkandera adusta.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 428 (1998) 141-6.
  ORGANISM  Pleurotus eryngii, Bjerkandera adusta
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9987124]
  AUTHORS   Ruiz-Duenas FJ, Martinez MJ, Martinez AT.
  TITLE     Molecular characterization of a novel peroxidase isolated from the ligninolytic fungus Pleurotus eryngii.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 31 (1999) 223-35.
  ORGANISM  Pleurotus eryngii
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9UR19 O94753]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:10187820]
  AUTHORS   Camarero S, Sarkar S, Ruiz-Duenas FJ, Martinez MJ, Martinez AT.
  TITLE     Description of a versatile peroxidase involved in the natural degradation of lignin that has both manganese peroxidase and lignin peroxidase substrate interaction sites.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 274 (1999) 10324-30.
  ORGANISM  Pleurotus eryngii, Phanerochaete chrysosporium
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9UVP6]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:10508113]
  AUTHORS   Ruiz-Duenas FJ, Martinez MJ, Martinez AT.
  TITLE     Heterologous expression of Pleurotus eryngii peroxidase confirms its ability to oxidize Mn(2+) and different aromatic substrates.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 65 (1999) 4705-7.
  ORGANISM  Pleurotus eryngii
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:11004397]
  AUTHORS   Camarero S, Ruiz-Duenas FJ, Sarkar S, Martinez MJ, Martinez AT.
  TITLE     The cloning of a new peroxidase found in lignocellulose cultures of Pleurotus eryngii and sequence comparison with other fungal peroxidases.
  JOURNAL   FEMS. Microbiol. Lett. 191 (2000) 37-43.
  ORGANISM  Pleurotus eryngii
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9UVP6]
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:11356138]
  AUTHORS   Ruiz-Duenas FJ, Camarero S, Perez-Boada M, Martinez MJ, Martinez AT.
  TITLE     A new versatile peroxidase from Pleurotus.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Soc. Trans. 29 (2001) 116-22.
  ORGANISM  Pleurotus eryngii, Bjerkandera adusta, Phanerochaete chrysosporium
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:12884090]
  AUTHORS   Banci L, Camarero S, Martinez AT, Martinez MJ, Perez-Boada M, Pierattelli R, Ruiz-Duenas FJ.
  TITLE     NMR study of manganese(II) binding by a new versatile peroxidase from the white-rot fungus Pleurotus eryngii.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Inorg. Chem. 8 (2003) 751-60.
  ORGANISM  Pleurotus eryngii
  SEQUENCE  [up:O94753]
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:16246366]
  AUTHORS   Perez-Boada M, Ruiz-Duenas FJ, Pogni R, Basosi R, Choinowski T, Martinez MJ, Piontek K, Martinez AT.
  TITLE     Versatile peroxidase oxidation of high redox potential aromatic compounds: site-directed mutagenesis, spectroscopic and crystallographic investigation of three long-range electron transfer pathways.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 354 (2005) 385-402.
  ORGANISM  Pleurotus eryngii
  SEQUENCE  [up:O94753]
REFERENCE   10 [PMID:10049842]
  AUTHORS   Caramelo L, Martinez MJ, Martinez AT.
  TITLE     A search for ligninolytic peroxidases in the fungus pleurotus eryngii involving alpha-keto-gamma-thiomethylbutyric acid and lignin model dimers
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 65 (1999) 916-22.
  ORGANISM  Pleurotus eryngii
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.11.1.16
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.11.1.16
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.11.1.16
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.11.1.16
            CAS: 42613-30-9 114995-15-2
///
