ENTRY       EC 1.11.1.18                Enzyme
NAME        bromide peroxidase;
            bromoperoxidase;
            haloperoxidase (ambiguous);
            eosinophil peroxidase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on a peroxide as acceptor;
            Peroxidases
SYSNAME     bromide:hydrogen-peroxide oxidoreductase
REACTION    RH + HBr + H2O2 = RBr + 2 H2O [RN:R09505]
ALL_REAC    R09505
SUBSTRATE   RH [CPD:C01371];
            HBr [CPD:C13645];
            H2O2 [CPD:C00027]
PRODUCT     RBr [CPD:C00720];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     Bromoperoxidases of red and brown marine algae (Rhodophyta and Phaeophyta) contain vanadate. They catalyse the bromination of a range of organic molecules such as sesquiterpenes, forming stable C-Br bonds. Bromoperoxidases also oxidize iodides.
HISTORY     EC 1.11.1.18 created 2010
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   De Boer, E., Tromp, M.G.M., Plat, H., Krenn, G.E. and Wever, R
  TITLE     Vanadium(v) as an essential element for haloperoxidase activity in marine brown-algae - purification and characterization of a vanadium(V)-containing bromoperoxidase from Laminaria saccharina.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta 872 (1986) 104-115.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:2400770]
  AUTHORS   Tromp MG, Olafsson G, Krenn BE, Wever R
  TITLE     Some structural aspects of vanadium bromoperoxidase from Ascophyllum nodosum.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1040 (1990) 192-8.
  ORGANISM  Ascophyllum nodosum
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10843856]
  AUTHORS   Isupov MN, Dalby AR, Brindley AA, Izumi Y, Tanabe T, Murshudov GN, Littlechild JA
  TITLE     Crystal structure of dodecameric vanadium-dependent bromoperoxidase from the red  algae Corallina officinalis.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 299 (2000) 1035-49.
  ORGANISM  Corallina officinalis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8LLW7]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15548002]
  AUTHORS   Carter-Franklin JN, Butler A
  TITLE     Vanadium bromoperoxidase-catalyzed biosynthesis of halogenated marine natural products.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 126 (2004) 15060-6.
  ORGANISM  Corallina officinalis, Laurencia pacifica, Plocamium cartilagineum
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15133166]
  AUTHORS   Ohshiro T, Littlechild J, Garcia-Rodriguez E, Isupov MN, Iida Y, Kobayashi T, Izumi Y
  TITLE     Modification of halogen specificity of a vanadium-dependent bromoperoxidase.
  JOURNAL   Protein. Sci. 13 (2004) 1566-71.
  ORGANISM  Corallina pilulifera
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.11.1.18
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.11.1.18
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.11.1.18
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.11.1.18
///
