ENTRY       EC 1.13.12.18               Enzyme
NAME        dinoflagellate luciferase;
            (dinoflagellate luciferin) luciferase;
            Gonyaulax luciferase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on single donors with incorporation of molecular oxygen (oxygenases);
            With incorporation of one atom of oxygen (internal monooxygenases or internal mixed-function oxidases)
SYSNAME     dinoflagellate-luciferin:oxygen 132-oxidoreductase
REACTION    dinoflagellate luciferin + O2 = oxidized dinoflagellate luciferin + H2O + hnu [RN:R09571]
ALL_REAC    R09571
SUBSTRATE   dinoflagellate luciferin [CPD:C19704];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     oxidized dinoflagellate luciferin [CPD:C19705];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            hnu [CPD:C00205]
COMMENT     A luciferase from dinoflagelates such as Gonyaulax polyedra, Lingulodinium polyedrum, Noctiluca scintillans, and Pyrocystis lunula. It is a single protein with three luciferase domains. The luciferin is strongly bound by a luciferin binding protein above a pH of 7.
HISTORY     EC 1.13.12.18 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:7197271]
  AUTHORS   Dunlap JC, Hastings JW
  TITLE     The biological clock in Gonyaulax controls luciferase activity by regulating turnover.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 256 (1981) 10509-18.
  ORGANISM  Gonyaulax polyedra
  SEQUENCE  [up:O77206]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:2745419]
  AUTHORS   Morse D, Pappenheimer AM Jr, Hastings JW
  TITLE     Role of a luciferin-binding protein in the circadian bioluminescent reaction of Gonyaulax polyedra.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 264 (1989) 11822-6.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:7918642]
  AUTHORS   Bae YM, Hastings JW
  TITLE     Cloning, sequencing and expression of dinoflagellate luciferase DNA from a marine alga, Gonyaulax polyedra.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1219 (1994) 449-56.
  ORGANISM  Gonyaulax polyedra
  SEQUENCE  [up:O77206]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:10812605]
  AUTHORS   Li L
  TITLE     Gonyaulax luciferase: gene structure, protein expression, and purification from recombinant sources.
  JOURNAL   Methods. Enzymol. 305 (2000) 249-58.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:10812606]
  AUTHORS   Morse D, Mittag M
  TITLE     Dinoflagellate luciferin-binding protein.
  JOURNAL   Methods. Enzymol. 305 (2000) 258-76.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:15665092]
  AUTHORS   Schultz LW, Liu L, Cegielski M, Hastings JW
  TITLE     Crystal structure of a pH-regulated luciferase catalyzing the bioluminescent oxidation of an open tetrapyrrole.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 102 (2005) 1378-83.
  ORGANISM  Gonyaulax polyedra
  SEQUENCE  [up:O77206]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.13.12.18
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.13.12.18
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.13.12.18
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.13.12.18
            CAS: 303183-71-3
///
