ENTRY       EC 1.13.11.55               Enzyme
NAME        sulfur oxygenase/reductase;
            SOR;
            sulfur oxygenase;
            sulfur oxygenase reductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on single donors with incorporation of molecular oxygen (oxygenases);
            With incorporation of two atoms of oxygen
SYSNAME     sulfur:oxygen oxidoreductase (hydrogen-sulfide- and sulfite-forming)
REACTION    4 sulfur + 4 H2O + O2 = 2 hydrogen sulfide + 2 bisulfite + 2 H+ [RN:R07365]
ALL_REAC    R07365
SUBSTRATE   sulfur [CPD:C00087];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     hydrogen sulfide [CPD:C00283];
            bisulfite [CPD:C11481];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     This enzyme, which is found in thermophilic microorganisms, contains one mononuclear none-heme iron centre per subunit. Elemental sulfur is both the electron donor and one of the two known acceptors, the other being oxygen. Another reaction product is thiosulfate, but this is probably formed non-enzymically at elevated temperature from sulfite and sulfur [1]. This enzyme differs from EC 1.13.11.18, sulfur dioxygenase and EC 1.12.98.4, sulfhydrogenase, in that both activities occur simultaneously.
HISTORY     EC 1.13.11.55 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:2493451]
  AUTHORS   Kletzin A.
  TITLE     Coupled enzymatic production of sulfite, thiosulfate, and hydrogen sulfide from sulfur: purification and properties of a sulfur oxygenase reductase from the facultatively anaerobic archaebacterium Desulfurolobus ambivalens.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 171 (1989) 1638-43.
  ORGANISM  Desulfurolobus ambivalens
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:1522063]
  AUTHORS   Kletzin A.
  TITLE     Molecular characterization of the sor gene, which encodes the sulfur oxygenase/reductase of the thermoacidophilic Archaeum Desulfurolobus ambivalens.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 174 (1992) 5854-9.
  ORGANISM  Desulfurolobus ambivalens
  SEQUENCE  [up:P29082]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:12664265]
  AUTHORS   Sun CW, Chen ZW, He ZG, Zhou PJ, Liu SJ.
  TITLE     Purification and properties of the sulfur oxygenase/reductase from the acidothermophilic archaeon, Acidianus strain S5.
  JOURNAL   Extremophiles. 7 (2003) 131-4.
  ORGANISM  Acidianus sp.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15030315]
  AUTHORS   Urich T, Bandeiras TM, Leal SS, Rachel R, Albrecht T, Zimmermann P, Scholz C, Teixeira M, Gomes CM, Kletzin A.
  TITLE     The sulphur oxygenase reductase from Acidianus ambivalens is a multimeric protein containing a low-potential mononuclear non-haem iron centre.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 381 (2004) 137-46.
  ORGANISM  Acidianus sp.
  SEQUENCE  [up:P29082]
PATHWAY     ec00920  Sulfur metabolism
            ec01120  Microbial metabolism in diverse environments
ORTHOLOGY   K16952  sulfur oxygenase/reductase
GENES       TNI: TVNIR_2721
            HNA: Hneap_1222
            AFI: Acife_2601
            DBA: Dbac_1171
            SAY: TPY_0405
            SAP: Sulac_0370
            AAE: aq_455(sor)
            PTO: PTO0801
            STO: ST1127
            AHO: Ahos_0131
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.13.11.55
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.13.11.55
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.13.11.55
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.13.11.55
            CAS: 120598-92-7
///
