ENTRY       EC 1.13.12.5                Enzyme
NAME        Renilla-luciferin 2-monooxygenase;
            Renilla-type luciferase;
            aequorin;
            luciferase (Renilla luciferin)
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on single donors with incorporation of molecular oxygen (oxygenases);
            With incorporation of one atom of oxygen (internal monooxygenases or internal mixed-function oxidases)
SYSNAME     Renilla-luciferin:oxygen 2-oxidoreductase (decarboxylating)
REACTION    Renilla luciferin + O2 = oxidized Renilla luciferin + CO2 + hnu [RN:R03137]
ALL_REAC    R03137
SUBSTRATE   Renilla luciferin [CPD:C00982];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     oxidized Renilla luciferin [CPD:C03717];
            CO2 [CPD:C00011];
            hnu [CPD:C00205]
COMMENT     From the soft coral coelenterate Renilla reniformis. The luciferin is bound to a luciferin-binding protein (BP-LH2). The bioluminescent reaction between the luciferin complex, luciferase and oxygen is triggered by calcium ions. In vivo, the excited state luciferin---luciferase complex undergoes the process of nonradiative energy transfer to an accessory protein, Renilla green fluorescent protein, which results in green bioluminescence. In vitro, Renilla luciferase emits blue light in the absence of any green fluorescent protein.
HISTORY     EC 1.13.12.5 created 1976, modified 1981, modified 1982, modified 2004
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:4154104]
  AUTHORS   Cormier MJ, Hori K, Anderson JM.
  TITLE     Bioluminescence in coelenterates.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 346 (1974) 137-64.
  ORGANISM  Renilla reniformis
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:237531]
  AUTHORS   Hori K, Anderson JM, Ward WW, Cormier MJ.
  TITLE     Renilla luciferin as the substrate for calcium induced photoprotein bioluminescence. Assignment of luciferin tautomers in aequorin and mnemiopsin.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 14 (1975) 2371-6.
  ORGANISM  Renilla reniformis
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:236561]
  AUTHORS   Shimomura O, Johnson FH.
  TITLE     Chemical nature of bioluminescence systems in coelenterates.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 72 (1975) 1546-9.
  ORGANISM  Renilla reniformis
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:33174]
  AUTHORS   Charbonneau H, Cormier MJ.
  TITLE     Ca2+-induced bioluminescence in Renilla reniformis. Purification and characterization of a calcium-triggered luciferin-binding protein.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 254 (1979) 769-80.
  ORGANISM  Renilla reniformis
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:4149963]
  AUTHORS   Anderson JM, Charbonneau H, Cormier MJ.
  TITLE     Mechanism of calcium induction of Renilla bioluminescence. Involvement of a calcium-triggered luciferin binding protein.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 13 (1974) 1195-200.
  ORGANISM  Renilla reniformis, Renilla muelleri
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:1674607]
  AUTHORS   Lorenz WW, McCann RO, Longiaru M, Cormier MJ.
  TITLE     Isolation and expression of a cDNA encoding Renilla reniformis luciferase.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 88 (1991) 4438-42.
  ORGANISM  Renilla reniformis
  SEQUENCE  [up:P27652]
ORTHOLOGY   K18053  renilla-luciferin 2-monooxygenase
GENES       BFO: BRAFLDRAFT_117184
            CIN: 100178046
            SPU: 583965 587333 589439 589487 593476 763261
            TAD: TRIADDRAFT_60698
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.13.12.5
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.13.12.5
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.13.12.5
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.13.12.5
            CAS: 61869-41-8
///
