ENTRY       EC 1.13.12.17               Enzyme
NAME        dichloroarcyriaflavin A synthase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on single donors with incorporation of molecular oxygen (oxygenases);
            With incorporation of one atom of oxygen (internal monooxygenases or internal mixed-function oxidases)
SYSNAME     dichlorochromopyrrolate,NADH:oxygen 2,5-oxidoreductase (dichloroarcyriaflavin A-forming)
REACTION    dichlorochromopyrrolate + 4 O2 + 4 NADH + 4 H+ = dichloroarcyriaflavin A + 2 CO2 + 6 H2O + 4 NAD+ [RN:R09567]
ALL_REAC    R09567
SUBSTRATE   dichlorochromopyrrolate [CPD:C19698];
            O2 [CPD:C00007];
            NADH [CPD:C00004];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
PRODUCT     dichloroarcyriaflavin A [CPD:C19699];
            CO2 [CPD:C00011];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            NAD+ [CPD:C00003]
COMMENT     The conversion of dichlorochromopyrrolate to dichloroarcyriaflavin A is a complex process that involves two enzyme components. RebP is an NAD-dependent cytochrome P450 oxygenase that performs an aryl-aryl bond formation yielding the six-ring indolocarbazole scaffold [1]. Along with RebC, a flavin-dependent hydroxylase, it also catalyses the oxidative decarboxylation of both carboxyl groups. The presence of RebC ensures that the only product is the rebeccamycin aglycone dichloroarcyriaflavin A [2]. The enzymes are similar, but not identical, to StaP and StaC, which are involved in the synthesis of staurosporine [3].
HISTORY     EC 1.13.12.17 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:17606921]
  AUTHORS   Makino M, Sugimoto H, Shiro Y, Asamizu S, Onaka H, Nagano S
  TITLE     Crystal structures and catalytic mechanism of cytochrome P450 StaP that produces  the indolocarbazole skeleton.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 104 (2007) 11591-6.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces sp.
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q83WG3]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16967980]
  AUTHORS   Howard-Jones AR, Walsh CT
  TITLE     Staurosporine and rebeccamycin aglycones are assembled by the oxidative action of StaP, StaC, and RebC on chromopyrrolic acid.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 128 (2006) 12289-98.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces longisporoflavus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q06IS1 Q06IS2]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:15625109]
  AUTHORS   Sanchez C, Zhu L, Brana AF, Salas AP, Rohr J, Mendez C, Salas JA
  TITLE     Combinatorial biosynthesis of antitumor indolocarbazole compounds.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 102 (2005) 461-6.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces albus
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.13.12.17
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.13.12.17
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.13.12.17
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.13.12.17
///
