ENTRY       EC 1.14.20.1                Enzyme
NAME        deacetoxycephalosporin-C synthase;
            DAOCS;
            penicillin N expandase;
            DAOC synthase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With 2-oxoglutarate as one donor, and the other dehydrogenated
SYSNAME     penicillin-N,2-oxoglutarate:oxygen oxidoreductase (ring-expanding)
REACTION    penicillin N + 2-oxoglutarate + O2 = deacetoxycephalosporin C + succinate + CO2 + H2O [RN:R05301]
ALL_REAC    R05301
SUBSTRATE   penicillin N [CPD:C06564];
            2-oxoglutarate [CPD:C00026];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     deacetoxycephalosporin C [CPD:C06565];
            succinate [CPD:C00042];
            CO2 [CPD:C00011];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     Forms part of the penicillin biosynthesis pathway (for pathway, click here).
HISTORY     EC 1.14.20.1 created 2002
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1354366]
  AUTHORS   Cantwell C, Beckmann R, Whiteman P, Queener SW, Abraham EP.
  TITLE     Isolation of deacetoxycephalosporin C from fermentation broths of Penicillium chrysogenum transformants: construction of a new fungal biosynthetic pathway.
  JOURNAL   Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B. Biol. Sci. 248 (1992) 283-9.
  ORGANISM  Penicillium chrysogenum
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:11352583]
  AUTHORS   Lee HJ, Lloyd MD, Harlos K, Clifton IJ, Baldwin JE, Schofield CJ.
  TITLE     Kinetic and crystallographic studies on deacetoxycephalosporin C synthase (DAOCS).
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 308 (2001) 937-48.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces clavuligerus
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   Yeh, W.K., Ghag, S.K. and Queener, S.W.
  TITLE     Enzymes for epimerization of isopenicillin N, ring expansion of penicillin N, and 3'-hydroxylation of deacetoxycephalosporin C. Function, evolution, refolding, and enzyme engineering.
  JOURNAL   Ann. N.Y. Acad. Sci. 672 (1992) 396-408.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9723623]
  AUTHORS   Valegard K, van Scheltinga AC, Lloyd MD, Hara T, Ramaswamy S, Perrakis A, Thompson A, Lee HJ, Baldwin JE, Schofield CJ, Hajdu J, Andersson I.
  TITLE     Structure of a cephalosporin synthase.
  JOURNAL   Nature. 394 (1998) 805-9.
  ORGANISM  Cephalosporium acremonium
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:2656705]
  AUTHORS   Dotzlaf JE, Yeh WK.
  TITLE     Purification and properties of deacetoxycephalosporin C synthase from recombinant Escherichia coli and its comparison with the native enzyme purified from Streptomyces clavuligerus.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 264 (1989) 10219-27.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces clavuligerus
PATHWAY     ec00311  Penicillin and cephalosporin biosynthesis
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K12744  deacetoxycephalosporin-C synthase
GENES       SCT: SCAT_5687(cefE)
            SCY: SCATT_56870
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.20.1
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.20.1
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.20.1
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.20.1
            CAS: 85746-10-7
///
