ENTRY       EC 1.14.12.22               Enzyme
NAME        carbazole 1,9a-dioxygenase;
            CARDO
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of two atoms of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     9H-carbazole,NAD(P)H:oxygen oxidoreductase (2,3-hydroxylating)
REACTION    9H-carbazole + NAD(P)H + H+ + O2 = 2'-aminobiphenyl-2,3-diol + NAD(P)+ [RN:R05414 R09512]
ALL_REAC    R05414 R09512
SUBSTRATE   9H-carbazole [CPD:C08060];
            NADH [CPD:C00004];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     2'-aminobiphenyl-2,3-diol [CPD:C08061];
            NAD+ [CPD:C00003];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006]
COMMENT     This enzyme catalyses the first reaction in the pathway of carbazole degradation. The enzyme attacks at the 1 and 9a positions of carbazole, resulting in the formation of a highly unstable hemiaminal intermediate that undergoes a spontaneous cleavage and rearomatization, resulting in 2'-aminobiphenyl-2,3-diol. In most bacteria the enzyme is a complex composed of a terminal oxygenase, a ferredoxin, and a ferredoxin reductase. The terminal oxygenase component contains a nonheme iron centre and a Rieske [2Fe-2S] iron-sulfur cluster.
HISTORY     EC 1.14.12.22 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:12450807]
  AUTHORS   Nam JW, Nojiri H, Noguchi H, Uchimura H, Yoshida T, Habe H, Yamane H, Omori T
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of carbazole 1,9a-dioxygenase, a three-component dioxygenase system of Pseudomonas resinovorans strain CA10.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 68 (2002) 5882-90.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas resinovorans
  SEQUENCE  [pre:PCA10_p0280]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:20368802]
  AUTHORS   Gai Z, Wang X, Liu X, Tai C, Tang H, He X, Wu G, Deng Z, Xu P
  TITLE     The genes coding for the conversion of carbazole to catechol are flanked by IS6100 elements in Sphingomonas sp. strain XLDN2-5.
  JOURNAL   PLoS. One. 5 (2010) e10018.
  ORGANISM  Sphingomonas sp.
  SEQUENCE  [up:D5IGG0]
PATHWAY     ec00621  Dioxin degradation
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01120  Microbial metabolism in diverse environments
ORTHOLOGY   K15751  carbazole 1,9a-dioxygenase, terminal dioxygenase component
GENES       PSD: DSC_14580
            PRE: PCA10_p0280(carAa)
            TTU: TERTU_1259
            CYQ: Q91_0967
            CZA: CYCME_1637
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.12.22
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.12.22
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.12.22
            UM-BBD (Biocatalysis/Biodegradation Database): 1.14.12.22
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.12.22
///
