ENTRY       EC 1.14.13.97               Enzyme
NAME        taurochenodeoxycholate 6alpha-hydroxylase;
            CYP3A4;
            CYP4A21;
            taurochenodeoxycholate 6alpha-monooxygenase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     taurochenodeoxycholate,NADPH:oxygen oxidoreductase (6alpha-hydroxylating)
REACTION    (1) taurochenodeoxycholate + NADPH + H+ + O2 = taurohyocholate + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R07205];
            (2) lithocholate + NADPH + H+ + O2 = hyodeoxycholate + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R07206]
ALL_REAC    R07205 R07206
SUBSTRATE   taurochenodeoxycholate [CPD:C05465];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007];
            lithocholate [CPD:C03990]
PRODUCT     taurohyocholate [CPD:C15516];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            hyodeoxycholate [CPD:C15517]
COMMENT     A heme-thiolate protein (P-450). Requires cytochrome b5 for maximal activity. Acts on taurochenodeoxycholate, taurodeoxycholate and less readily on lithocholate and chenodeoxycholate. In adult pig (Sus scrofa), hyocholic acid replaces cholic acid as a primary bile acid [5].
HISTORY     EC 1.14.13.97 created 2005
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10216279]
  AUTHORS   Araya Z, Wikvall K.
  TITLE     6alpha-hydroxylation of taurochenodeoxycholic acid and lithocholic acid by CYP3A4 in human liver microsomes.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1438 (1999) 47-54.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:1576]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7649186]
  AUTHORS   Araya Z, Hellman U, Hansson R.
  TITLE     Characterisation of taurochenodeoxycholic acid 6 alpha-hydroxylase from pig liver microsomes.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 231 (1995) 855-61.
  ORGANISM  Sus scofa
  SEQUENCE  [ssc:403327]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11069906]
  AUTHORS   Kramer W, Sauber K, Baringhaus KH, Kurz M, Stengelin S, Lange G, Corsiero D, Girbig F, Konig W, Weyland C.
  TITLE     Identification of the bile acid-binding site of the ileal lipid-binding protein by photoaffinity labeling, matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization-mass spectrometry, and NMR structure.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 276 (2001) 7291-301.
  ORGANISM  Oryctolagus cuniculus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:11113117]
  AUTHORS   Lundell K, Hansson R, Wikvall K.
  TITLE     Cloning and expression of a pig liver taurochenodeoxycholic acid 6alpha-hydroxylase (CYP4A21): a novel member of the CYP4A subfamily.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 276 (2001) 9606-12.
  ORGANISM  Sus scofa
  SEQUENCE  [ssc:403327]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:14643796]
  AUTHORS   Lundell K, Wikvall K.
  TITLE     Gene structure of pig sterol 12alpha-hydroxylase (CYP8B1) and expression in fetal liver: comparison with expression of taurochenodeoxycholic acid 6alpha-hydroxylase (CYP4A21).
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1634 (2003) 86-96.
  ORGANISM  Sus scofa
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:12543708]
  AUTHORS   Russell DW.
  TITLE     The enzymes, regulation, and genetics of bile acid synthesis.
  JOURNAL   Annu. Rev. Biochem. 72 (2003) 137-74.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
ORTHOLOGY   K17689  cytochrome P450, family 3, subfamily A, polypeptide 4
            K18228  taurochenodeoxycholate 6alpha-hydroxylase
GENES       HSA: 1576(CYP3A4)
            PTR: 463582(CYP3A4)
            PPS: 100976899
            GGO: 101149513
            PON: 100436782
            MCC: 678670(CYP3A4)
            MCF: 102144258(CYP3A8)
            SSC: 403327(CYP4A21)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.97
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.13.97
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.13.97
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.97
            CAS: 105669-85-0
///
