ENTRY       EC 1.14.11.21               Enzyme
NAME        clavaminate synthase;
            clavaminate synthase 2;
            clavaminic acid synthase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With 2-oxoglutarate as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into each donor
SYSNAME     deoxyamidinoproclavaminate,2-oxoglutarate:oxygen oxidoreductase (3-hydroxylating)
REACTION    (1) deoxyamidinoproclavaminate + 2-oxoglutarate + O2 = amidinoproclavaminate + succinate + CO2 [RN:R05466];
            (2) proclavaminate + 2-oxoglutarate + O2 = dihydroclavaminate + succinate + CO2 + H2O [RN:R05468];
            (3) dihydroclavaminate + 2-oxoglutarate + O2 = clavaminate + succinate + CO2 + H2O [RN:R05469]
ALL_REAC    R05466 R05468 R05469
SUBSTRATE   deoxyamidinoproclavaminate [CPD:C06656];
            2-oxoglutarate [CPD:C00026];
            O2 [CPD:C00007];
            proclavaminate [CPD:C06658];
            dihydroclavaminate [CPD:C06659]
PRODUCT     amidinoproclavaminate [CPD:C06657];
            succinate [CPD:C00042];
            CO2 [CPD:C00011];
            dihydroclavaminate [CPD:C06659];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            clavaminate [CPD:C06660]
COMMENT     Contains nonheme iron. Catalyses three separate oxidative reactions in the pathway for the biosythesis of the beta-lactamase inhibitor clavulanate in Streptomyces clavuligerus. The first step (hydroxylation) is separated from the latter two (oxidative cyclization and desaturation) by the action of EC 3.5.3.22, proclavaminate amidinohydrolase. The three reactions are all catalysed at the same nonheme iron site.
HISTORY     EC 1.14.11.21 created 2003
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1998687]
  AUTHORS   Salowe SP, Krol WJ, Iwata-Reuyl D, Townsend CA.
  TITLE     Elucidation of the order of oxidations and identification of an intermediate in the multistep clavaminate synthase reaction.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 30 (1991) 2281-92.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces clavuligerus
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Zhou, J., Gunsior, M., Bachmann, B.O., Townsend, C.A. and Solomon, E.I.
  TITLE     Substrate binding to the alpha-ketoglutarate-dependent non-heme iron enzyme clavaminate synthase 2: Coupling mechanism of oxidative decarboxylation and hydroxylation.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 120 (1998) 13539-13540.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10655615]
  AUTHORS   Zhang Z, Ren J, Stammers DK, Baldwin JE, Harlos K, Schofield CJ.
  TITLE     Structural origins of the selectivity of the trifunctional oxygenase clavaminic acid synthase.
  JOURNAL   Nat. Struct. Biol. 7 (2000) 127-33.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces clavuligerus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q05581]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:11472170]
  AUTHORS   Zhou J, Kelly WL, Bachmann BO, Gunsior M, Townsend CA, Solomon EI.
  TITLE     Spectroscopic studies of substrate interactions with clavaminate synthase 2, a multifunctional alpha-KG-dependent non-heme iron enzyme: correlation with mechanisms and reactivities.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 123 (2001) 7388-98.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces clavuligerus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:12413541]
  AUTHORS   Townsend CA.
  TITLE     New reactions in clavulanic acid biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol. 6 (2002) 583-9.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces clavuligerus
PATHWAY     ec00331  Clavulanic acid biosynthesis
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K12675  clavaminate synthase
GENES       SFA: Sfla_0558
            STRP: F750_6321
            SVI: Svir_33410
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.11.21
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.11.21
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.11.21
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.11.21
            CAS: 122799-56-8
///
