ENTRY       EC 1.14.13.109              Enzyme
NAME        abieta-7,13-dien-18-ol hydroxylase;
            CYP720B1;
            PtAO;
            abietadienol hydroxylase (ambiguous)
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     abieta-7,13-dien-18-ol,NADPH:oxygen oxidoreductase (18-hydroxylating)
REACTION    abieta-7,13-dien-18-ol + NADPH + H+ + O2 = abieta-7,13-dien-18-al + NADP+ + 2 H2O (overall reaction) [RN:R06354];
            (1a) abieta-7,13-dien-18-ol + NADPH + H+ + O2 = abieta-7,13-dien-18,18-diol + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R10077];
            (1b) abieta-7,13-dien-18,18-diol = abieta-7,13-dien-18-al + H2O (spontaneous) [RN:R10078]
ALL_REAC    R06354 R10077 R10078
SUBSTRATE   abieta-7,13-dien-18-ol;
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007];
            abieta-7,13-dien-18,18-diol [CPD:C20329]
PRODUCT     abieta-7,13-dien-18-al;
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            abieta-7,13-dien-18,18-diol [CPD:C20329]
COMMENT     A heme-thiolate protein (P-450). This enzyme catalyses a step in the pathway of abietic acid biosynthesis. The activity has been demonstrated in cell-free stem extracts of Abies grandis (grand fir) and Pinus contorta (lodgepole pine) [1], and the gene encoding the enzyme has been identified in Pinus taeda (loblolly pine) [3]. The recombinant enzyme catalyses the oxidation of multiple diterpene alcohol and aldehydes, including levopimaradienol, isopimara-7,15-dienol, isopimara-7,15-dienal, dehydroabietadienol and dehydroabietadienal. It is not able to oxidize abietadiene.
HISTORY     EC 1.14.13.109 created 2009, modified 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8311462]
  AUTHORS   Funk C, Croteau R
  TITLE     Diterpenoid resin acid biosynthesis in conifers: characterization of two cytochrome P450-dependent monooxygenases and an aldehyde dehydrogenase involved in abietic acid biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 308 (1994) 258-66.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis, Pinus contorta
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12232380]
  AUTHORS   Funk C, Lewinsohn E, Vogel BS, Steele CL, Croteau R
  TITLE     Regulation of Oleoresinosis in Grand Fir (Abies grandis) (Coordinate Induction of Monoterpene and Diterpene Cyclases and Two Cytochrome P450-Dependent Diterpenoid Hydroxylases by Stem Wounding).
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 106 (1994) 999-1005.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:15911762]
  AUTHORS   Ro DK, Arimura G, Lau SY, Piers E, Bohlmann J
  TITLE     Loblolly pine abietadienol/abietadienal oxidase PtAO (CYP720B1) is a multifunctional, multisubstrate cytochrome P450 monooxygenase.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 102 (2005) 8060-5.
  ORGANISM  Pinus taeda
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q50EK6]
PATHWAY     ec00904  Diterpenoid biosynthesis
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K14040  abietadienol/abietadienal oxidase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.109
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.13.109
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.13.109
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.109
///
