ENTRY       EC 1.14.12.20               Enzyme
NAME        pheophorbide a oxygenase;
            pheide a monooxygenase;
            pheide a oxygenase;
            PaO;
            PAO
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of two atoms of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     pheophorbide-a,NADPH:oxygen oxidoreductase (biladiene-forming)
REACTION    pheophorbide a + NADPH + H+ + O2 = red chlorophyll catabolite + NADP+ [RN:R08921]
ALL_REAC    R08921
SUBSTRATE   pheophorbide a [CPD:C18021];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     red chlorophyll catabolite [CPD:C18022];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006]
COMMENT     This enzyme catalyses a key reaction in chlorophyll degradation, which occurs during leaf senescence and fruit ripening in higher plants. The enzyme from Arabidopsis contains a Rieske-type iron-sulfur cluster [2] and requires reduced ferredoxin, which is generated either by NADPH through the pentose-phosphate pathway or by the action of photosystem I [4]. While still attached to this enzyme, the product is rapidly converted into primary fluorescent chlorophyll catabolite by the action of EC 1.3.1.80, red chlorophyll catabolite reductase [2,6]. Pheophorbide b acts as an inhibitor. In 18O2 labelling experiments, only the aldehyde oxygen is labelled, suggesting that the other oxygen atom may originate from H2O [1].
HISTORY     EC 1.14.12.20 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9624113]
  AUTHORS   Hortensteiner S, Wuthrich KL, Matile P, Ongania KH, Krautler B.
  TITLE     The key step in chlorophyll breakdown in higher plants. Cleavage of pheophorbide a macrocycle by a monooxygenase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 273 (1998) 15335-9.
  ORGANISM  Brassica napus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:14657372]
  AUTHORS   Pruzinska A, Tanner G, Anders I, Roca M, Hortensteiner S.
  TITLE     Chlorophyll breakdown: pheophorbide a oxygenase is a Rieske-type iron-sulfur protein, encoded by the accelerated cell death 1 gene.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 100 (2003) 15259-64.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana
  SEQUENCE  [ath:AT3G44880]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16844830]
  AUTHORS   Chung DW, Pruzinska A, Hortensteiner S, Ort DR.
  TITLE     The role of pheophorbide a oxygenase expression and activity in the canola green seed problem.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 142 (2006) 88-97.
  ORGANISM  Brassica napus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12223835]
  AUTHORS   Rodoni S, Muhlecker W, Anderl M, Krautler B, Moser D, Thomas H, Matile P, Hortensteiner S.
  TITLE     Chlorophyll Breakdown in Senescent Chloroplasts (Cleavage of Pheophorbide a in Two Enzymic Steps).
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 115 (1997) 669-676.
  ORGANISM  Brassica napus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:16669755]
  AUTHORS   Hortensteiner S.
  TITLE     Chlorophyll degradation during senescence.
  JOURNAL   Annu. Rev. Plant. Biol. 57 (2006) 55-77.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:17237353]
  AUTHORS   Pruzinska A, Anders I, Aubry S, Schenk N, Tapernoux-Luthi E, Muller T, Krautler B, Hortensteiner S.
  TITLE     In vivo participation of red chlorophyll catabolite reductase in chlorophyll breakdown.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Cell. 19 (2007) 369-87.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana
PATHWAY     ec00860  Porphyrin and chlorophyll metabolism
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K13071  pheophorbide a oxygenase
GENES       ATH: AT3G44880(ACD1)
            ALY: ARALYDRAFT_905628
            CRB: CARUB_v10016980mg
            EUS: EUTSA_v10002475mg
            CIT: 102625487
            CIC: CICLE_v10028147mg
            TCC: TCM_041583
            GMX: 100812162 778121
            MTR: MTR_4g057200
            CAM: 101513298
            FVE: 101295785
            CSV: 101217499(CSPAO)
            RCU: RCOM_0475420
            POP: POPTR_0004s22680g POPTR_0009s00950g
            VVI: 100256831
            SLY: 543677
            SOT: 102579316
            OSA: 4331611
            DOSA: Os03t0146400-01(Os03g0146400)
            OBR: 102703661
            BDI: 100840185
            SBI: SORBI_01g047120(SORBIDRAFT_01g047120)
            SITA: 101766370
            ATR: s00140p00073520(AMTR_s00140p00073520) s00140p00074640(AMTR_s00140p00074640)
            SMO: SELMODRAFT_174928 SELMODRAFT_177205
            PPP: PHYPADRAFT_134389 PHYPADRAFT_150204
            CRE: CHLREDRAFT_150538(PAO2) CHLREDRAFT_150540(PAO1)
            VCN: VOLCADRAFT_89014
            CSL: COCSUDRAFT_39968 COCSUDRAFT_46572 COCSUDRAFT_47272 COCSUDRAFT_62940 COCSUDRAFT_67210 COCSUDRAFT_67947
            CVR: CHLNCDRAFT_137589 CHLNCDRAFT_51738
            CCP: CHC_T00003882001 CHC_T00004024001 CHC_T00006958001
            EHX: EMIHUDRAFT_115527 EMIHUDRAFT_95263
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.12.20
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.12.20
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.12.20
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.12.20
///
