ENTRY       EC 1.14.13.185              Enzyme
NAME        pikromycin synthase;
            PikC;
            CYP107L1
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     narbomycin,NADH:oxygen oxidoreductase (pikromycin-forming)
REACTION    (1) narbomycin + NADPH + H+ + O2 = pikromycin + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R06464];
            (2) narbomycin + NADPH + H+ + O2 = neopikromycin + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R10626];
            (3) narbomycin + 2 NADPH + 2 H+ + 2 O2 = novapikromyin + 2 NADP+ + 2 H2O [RN:R10627];
            (4) 10-deoxymethymycin + NADPH + H+ + O2 = methymycin + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R06463];
            (5) 10-deoxymethymycin + NADPH + H+ + O2 = neomethymycin + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R06462];
            (6) 10-deoxymethymycin + 2 NADPH + 2 H+ + 2 O2 = novamethymycin + 2 NADP+ + 2 H2O [RN:R10628]
ALL_REAC    R06462 R06463 R06464 R10626 R10627 R10628
SUBSTRATE   narbomycin [CPD:C11998];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007];
            10-deoxymethymycin [CPD:C11994]
PRODUCT     pikromycin [CPD:C11999];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            neopikromycin [CPD:C20739];
            novapikromyin [CPD:C20740];
            methymycin [CPD:C11996];
            neomethymycin [CPD:C11995];
            novamethymycin [CPD:C20741]
COMMENT     A heme-thiolate protein (cytochrome P-450). Involved in the biosynthesis of a number of bacterial macrolide antibiotics containing a desosamine glycoside unit. With narbomycin it hydroxylates at either C-12 to give pikromycin or C-14 to give neopikromycin or both positions to give narvopikromycin. With 10-deoxymethymycin it hydroxylates at either C-10 to give methymycin or C-12 to give neomethymycin or both positions to give novamethymycin.
HISTORY     EC 1.14.13.185 created 2014
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9831532]
  AUTHORS   Xue Y, Wilson D, Zhao L, Liu Hw, Sherman DH
  TITLE     Hydroxylation of macrolactones YC-17 and narbomycin is mediated by the pikC-encoded cytochrome P450 in Streptomyces venezuelae.
  JOURNAL   Chem. Biol. 5 (1998) 661-7.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16825192]
  AUTHORS   Sherman DH, Li S, Yermalitskaya LV, Kim Y, Smith JA, Waterman MR, Podust LM
  TITLE     The structural basis for substrate anchoring, active site selectivity, and product formation by P450 PikC from Streptomyces venezuelae.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 281 (2006) 26289-97.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:19124459]
  AUTHORS   Li S, Ouellet H, Sherman DH, Podust LM
  TITLE     Analysis of transient and catalytic desosamine-binding pockets in cytochrome P-450 PikC from Streptomyces venezuelae.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 284 (2009) 5723-30.
PATHWAY     ec00522  Biosynthesis of 12-, 14- and 16-membered macrolides
            ec01052  Type I polyketide structures
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K16006  pikromycin synthase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.185
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.13.185
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.13.185
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.185
///
