ENTRY       EC 1.14.13.108              Enzyme
NAME        abieta-7,13-diene hydroxylase;
            abietadiene hydroxylase (ambiguous)
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     abieta-7,13-diene,NADPH:oxygen oxidoreductase (18-hydroxylating)
REACTION    abieta-7,13-diene + NADPH + H+ + O2 = abieta-7,13-dien-18-ol + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R06351]
ALL_REAC    R06351
SUBSTRATE   abieta-7,13-diene;
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     abieta-7,13-dien-18-ol;
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     A heme-thiolate protein (P-450). This enzyme catalyses a step in the pathway of abietic acid biosynthesis. The activity has been demonstrated in cell-free stem extracts of Abies grandis (grand fir) and Pinus contorta (lodgepole pine). The enzyme is localized in the microsomal fraction and requires both oxygen and NADPH. Inhibition by carbon monoxide and several substituted N-heterocyclic inhibitors suggests that the enzyme is a cytochrome P-450-dependent monooxygenase [1]. Activity is induced by wounding of the plant tissue [2].
HISTORY     EC 1.14.13.108 created 2009, modified 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8311462]
  AUTHORS   Funk C, Croteau R
  TITLE     Diterpenoid resin acid biosynthesis in conifers: characterization of two cytochrome P450-dependent monooxygenases and an aldehyde dehydrogenase involved in abietic acid biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 308 (1994) 258-66.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis, Pinus contorta
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12232380]
  AUTHORS   Funk C, Lewinsohn E, Vogel BS, Steele CL, Croteau R
  TITLE     Regulation of Oleoresinosis in Grand Fir (Abies grandis) (Coordinate Induction of Monoterpene and Diterpene Cyclases and Two Cytochrome P450-Dependent Diterpenoid Hydroxylases by Stem Wounding).
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 106 (1994) 999-1005.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
PATHWAY     ec00904  Diterpenoid biosynthesis
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.108
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.13.108
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.13.108
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.108
///
