ENTRY       EC 1.14.12.12               Enzyme
NAME        naphthalene 1,2-dioxygenase;
            naphthalene dioxygenase;
            naphthalene oxygenase;
            NDO
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of two atoms of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     naphthalene,NADH:oxygen oxidoreductase (1,2-hydroxylating)
REACTION    naphthalene + NADH + H+ + O2 = (1R,2S)-1,2-dihydronaphthalene-1,2-diol + NAD+ [RN:R02968]
ALL_REAC    R02968;
            (other) R05422 R05423 R05424 R05425 R05426 R05427 R06909 R06930 R06937 R07704 R09159
SUBSTRATE   naphthalene [CPD:C00829];
            NADH [CPD:C00004];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     (1R,2S)-1,2-dihydronaphthalene-1,2-diol [CPD:C04314];
            NAD+ [CPD:C00003]
COMMENT     This enzyme is a member of the ring-hydroxylating dioxygenase (RHD) family of bacterial enzymes that play a critical role in the degradation of aromatic compounds, such as polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons [5]. This enzyme comprises a multicomponent system, containing a reductase that is an iron-sulfur flavoprotein (FAD; EC 1.18.1.3, ferredoxin---NAD+ reductase), an iron-sulfur oxygenase, and ferredoxin. Requires Fe2+.
HISTORY     EC 1.14.12.12 created 1992
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:6874638]
  AUTHORS   Ensley BD, Gibson DT.
  TITLE     Naphthalene dioxygenase: purification and properties of a terminal oxygenase component.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 155 (1983) 505-11.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas sp.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:234247]
  AUTHORS   Jeffrey AM, Yeh HJ, Jerina DM, Patel TR, Davey JF, Gibson DT.
  TITLE     Initial reactions in the oxidation of naphthalene by Pseudomonas putida.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 14 (1975) 575-84.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas putida
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9634695]
  AUTHORS   Kauppi B, Lee K, Carredano E, Parales RE, Gibson DT, Eklund H, Ramaswamy S
  TITLE     Structure of an aromatic-ring-hydroxylating dioxygenase-naphthalene 1,2-dioxygenase.
  JOURNAL   Structure. 6 (1998) 571-86.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas sp.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:10692370]
  AUTHORS   Parales RE, Lee K, Resnick SM, Jiang H, Lessner DJ, Gibson DT
  TITLE     Substrate specificity of naphthalene dioxygenase: effect of specific amino acids at the active site of the enzyme.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 182 (2000) 1641-9.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas sp.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:17014090]
  AUTHORS   Jouanneau Y, Meyer C, Jakoncic J, Stojanoff V, Gaillard J
  TITLE     Characterization of a naphthalene dioxygenase endowed with an exceptionally broad substrate specificity toward polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 45 (2006) 12380-91.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas putida
PATHWAY     ec00624  Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon degradation
            ec00626  Naphthalene degradation
            ec00642  Ethylbenzene degradation
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01120  Microbial metabolism in diverse environments
ORTHOLOGY   K14579  naphthalene 1,2-dioxygenase subunit alpha
            K14580  naphthalene 1,2-dioxygenase subunit beta
GENES       PPI: ND055(nahAc) ND056(nahAd)
            PSC: A458_06720 A458_06725
            ALT: ambt_17890 ambt_17895
            PNA: Pnap_2484 Pnap_2485
            AJS: Ajs_3092 Ajs_3093
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.12.12
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.12.12
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.12.12
            UM-BBD (Biocatalysis/Biodegradation Database): 1.14.12.12
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.12.12
            CAS: 9074-04-8
///
