ENTRY       EC 1.14.13.188              Enzyme
NAME        6-deoxyerythronolide B hydroxylase;
            DEB hydroxylase;
            eryF (gene name);
            P450(eryF);
            CYP107A1
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     6-deoxyerythronolide-B,NADPH:oxygen oxidoreductase
REACTION    6-deoxyerythronolide B + NADPH + H+ + O2 = erythronolide B + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R05270]
ALL_REAC    R05270
SUBSTRATE   6-deoxyerythronolide B [CPD:C03240];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     erythronolide B [CPD:C06635];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     A heme-thiolate protein (P-450). Isolated from the bacterium Saccharopolyspora erythraea. The enzyme is involved in the biosynthesis of the antibiotic erythromycin.
HISTORY     EC 1.14.13.188 created 2014
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:2011746]
  AUTHORS   Weber JM, Leung JO, Swanson SJ, Idler KB, McAlpine JB
  TITLE     An erythromycin derivative produced by targeted gene disruption in Saccharopolyspora erythraea.
  JOURNAL   Science. 252 (1991) 114-7.
  ORGANISM  Saccharopolyspora erythraea
  SEQUENCE  [sen:SACE_0730]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:2446657]
  AUTHORS   Shafiee A, Hutchinson CR
  TITLE     Macrolide antibiotic biosynthesis: isolation and properties of two forms of 6-deoxyerythronolide B hydroxylase from Saccharopolyspora erythraea (Streptomyces erythreus).
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 26 (1987) 6204-10.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:7846029]
  AUTHORS   Cupp-Vickery JR, Li H, Poulos TL
  TITLE     Preliminary crystallographic analysis of an enzyme involved in erythromycin biosynthesis: cytochrome P450eryF.
  JOURNAL   Proteins. 20 (1994) 197-201.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15824115]
  AUTHORS   Nagano S, Cupp-Vickery JR, Poulos TL
  TITLE     Crystal structures of the ferrous dioxygen complex of wild-type cytochrome P450eryF and its mutants, A245S and A245T: investigation of the proton transfer system in P450eryF.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 280 (2005) 22102-7.
PATHWAY     ec00522  Biosynthesis of 12-, 14- and 16-membered macrolides
            ec01052  Type I polyketide structures
ORTHOLOGY   K14366  6-deoxyerythronolide B hydroxylase
GENES       SEN: SACE_0730(eryF)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.188
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.13.188
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.13.188
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.188
///
