ENTRY       EC 1.14.21.7                Enzyme
NAME        biflaviolin synthase;
            CYP158A2;
            CYP 158A2;
            cytochrome P450 158A2
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and the other dehydrogenated
SYSNAME     flaviolin,NADPH:oxygen oxidoreductase
REACTION    (1) 2 flaviolin + NADPH + H+ + O2 = 3,3'-biflaviolin + NADP+ + 2 H2O [RN:R08912];
            (2) 2 flaviolin + NADPH + H+ + O2 = 3,8'-biflaviolin + NADP+ + 2 H2O [RN:R08913]
ALL_REAC    R08912 R08913
SUBSTRATE   flaviolin [CPD:C18012];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     3,3'-biflaviolin [CPD:C18013];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            3,8'-biflaviolin [CPD:C18014]
COMMENT     This cytochrome-P450 enzyme, from the soil-dwelling bacterium Streptomyces coelicolor A3(2), catalyses a phenol oxidation C-C coupling reaction, which results in the polymerization of flaviolin to form biflaviolin or triflaviolin without the incorporation of oxygen into the product [1,3]. The products are highly conjugated pigments that protect the bacterium from the deleterious effects of UV irradiation [1].
HISTORY     EC 1.14.21.7 created 2008
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:15659395]
  AUTHORS   Zhao B, Guengerich FP, Bellamine A, Lamb DC, Izumikawa M, Lei L, Podust LM, Sundaramoorthy M, Kalaitzis JA, Reddy LM, Kelly SL, Moore BS, Stec D, Voehler M, Falck JR, Shimada T, Waterman MR
  TITLE     Binding of two flaviolin substrate molecules, oxidative coupling, and crystal structure of Streptomyces coelicolor A3(2) cytochrome P450 158A2.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 280 (2005) 11599-607.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces coelicolor
  SEQUENCE  [sco:SCO1207]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16239228]
  AUTHORS   Zhao B, Guengerich FP, Voehler M, Waterman MR
  TITLE     Role of active site water molecules and substrate hydroxyl groups in oxygen activation by cytochrome P450 158A2: a new mechanism of proton transfer.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 280 (2005) 42188-97.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces coelicolor
  SEQUENCE  [sco:SCO1207]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:17614370]
  AUTHORS   Zhao B, Lamb DC, Lei L, Kelly SL, Yuan H, Hachey DL, Waterman MR
  TITLE     Different binding modes of two flaviolin substrate molecules in cytochrome P450 158A1 (CYP158A1) compared to CYP158A2.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 46 (2007) 8725-33.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces coelicolor
  SEQUENCE  [sco:SCO1207]
ORTHOLOGY   K13074  biflaviolin synthase
GENES       SCO: SCO1207(2SCG58.07)
            SMA: SAV_7130(cyp25)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.21.7
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.21.7
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.21.7
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.21.7
///
