ENTRY       EC 1.14.19.5                Enzyme
NAME        Delta11-fatty-acid desaturase;
            Delta11 desaturase;
            fatty acid Delta11-desaturase;
            TpDESN;
            Cro-PG;
            Delta11 fatty acid desaturase;
            Z/E11-desaturase;
            Delta11-palmitoyl-CoA desaturase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With oxidation of a pair of donors resulting in the reduction of O2 to two molecules of water
SYSNAME     acyl-CoA,hydrogen donor:oxygen Delta11-oxidoreductase
REACTION    acyl-CoA + reduced acceptor + O2 = Delta11-acyl-CoA + acceptor + 2 H2O
SUBSTRATE   acyl-CoA [CPD:C00040];
            reduced acceptor [CPD:C00030];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     Delta11-acyl-CoA;
            acceptor [CPD:C00028];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     In common with front-end desaturases involved in the synthesis of polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs), this membrane-bound enzyme has a cytochrome b5-like domain at the N-terminus and contains three histidine boxes that are critical for desaturase activity [1]. The enzyme from the marine microalga Thalassiosira pseudonana specifically desaturates palmitic acid 16:0 to 16:1Delta11 [1] whereas that from the leafroller moth Choristoneura rosaceana desaturates myristic acid 14:0 to 14:1Delta11 [2]. 16:1Delta11 represents an important precursor for pheromone synthesis in insect cells, although its function in microalgae is currently unknown [1]. The enzyme from the Egyptian cotton leafworm Spodoptera littoralis has a preference for palmitoyl-CoA as substrate and for NADH rather than NADPH as reduced acceptor [3].
HISTORY     EC 1.14.19.5 created 2008
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:15063718]
  AUTHORS   Tonon T, Harvey D, Qing R, Li Y, Larson TR, Graham IA.
  TITLE     Identification of a fatty acid Delta11-desaturase from the microalga Thalassiosira pseudonana.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 563 (2004) 28-34.
  ORGANISM  Thalassiosira pseudonana
  SEQUENCE  [tps:THAPS_23391]
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Hao, G., O'Connor, M., Liu, W. and Roelofs, W.L.
  TITLE     Characterization of Z/E11- and Z9-desaturases from the obliquebanded leafroller moth, Choristoneura rosaceana.
  JOURNAL   J. Insect Sci. 2:26 (2002) 1-7.
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   Rodriguez, F., Hallahan, D.L., Pickett, J.A. and Camps, F.
  TITLE     Characterization of the Delta11-palmitoyl-CoA-desaturase from Spodoptera littoralis (Lepidoptera:Noctuidae).
  JOURNAL   Insect Biochem. Mol. Biol. 22 (1992) 143-148.
ORTHOLOGY   K18247  delta11-fatty-acid desaturase
GENES       TPS: THAPS_23391(DES11)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.19.5
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.19.5
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.19.5
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.19.5
///
