ENTRY       EC 1.14.13.69               Enzyme
NAME        alkene monooxygenase;
            alkene epoxygenase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     alkene,NADH:oxygen oxidoreductase
REACTION    propene + NADH + H+ + O2 = 1,2-epoxypropane + NAD+ + H2O [RN:R07194]
ALL_REAC    R07194 > R05729 R05730;
            (other) R05444
SUBSTRATE   propene [CPD:C11505];
            NADH [CPD:C00004];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     1,2-epoxypropane [CPD:C15508];
            NAD+ [CPD:C00003];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     The enzyme from Xanthobacter sp. strain Py2 is a multicomponent enzyme comprising (1) an NADH reductase, which provides the reductant for O2 activation; (2) a Rieske-type ferredoxin, which is an electron-transfer protein; (3) an oxygenase, which contains the catalytic centre for alkene epoxidation and (4) a small protein of unknown function that is essential for activity. Requires Fe(II). The enzyme oxygenates C2 to C6 aliphatic alkenes. With 1,2-epoxypropane as substrate, the stereospecifity of the epoxypropane formed is 95% (R) and 5% (S).
HISTORY     EC 1.14.13.69 created 2001
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9312093]
  AUTHORS   Small FJ, Ensign SA.
  TITLE     Alkene monooxygenase from Xanthobacter strain Py2. Purification and characterization of a four-component system central to the bacterial metabolism of aliphatic alkenes.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 272 (1997) 24913-20.
  ORGANISM  Xanthobacter sp.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:10103255]
  AUTHORS   Zhou NY, Jenkins A, Chan Kwo Chion CK, Leak DJ.
  TITLE     The alkene monooxygenase from Xanthobacter strain Py2 is closely related to aromatic monooxygenases and catalyzes aromatic monohydroxylation of benzene, toluene, and phenol.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 65 (1999) 1589-95.
  ORGANISM  Xanthobacter sp.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9266707]
  AUTHORS   Gallagher SC, Cammack R, Dalton H.
  TITLE     Alkene monooxygenase from Nocardia corallina B-276 is a member of the class of dinuclear iron proteins capable of stereospecific epoxygenation reactions.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 247 (1997) 635-41.
  ORGANISM  Nocardia corallina
PATHWAY     ec00625  Chloroalkane and chloroalkene degradation
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01120  Microbial metabolism in diverse environments
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.69
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.13.69
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.13.69
            UM-BBD (Biocatalysis/Biodegradation Database): 1.14.13.69
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.69
            CAS: 63439-50-9
///
