ENTRY       EC 1.14.13.111              Enzyme
NAME        methanesulfonate monooxygenase;
            mesylate monooxygenase;
            mesylate,reduced-FMN:oxygen oxidoreductase;
            MsmABC;
            methanesulfonic acid monooxygenase;
            MSA monooxygenase;
            MSAMO
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     methanesulfonate,NADH:oxygen oxidoreductase
REACTION    methanesulfonate + NADH + H+ + O2 = formaldehyde + NAD+ + sulfite + H2O [RN:R09513]
ALL_REAC    R09513
SUBSTRATE   methanesulfonate [CPD:C11145];
            NADH [CPD:C00004];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     formaldehyde [CPD:C00067];
            NAD+ [CPD:C00003];
            sulfite [CPD:C00094];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     A flavoprotein. Methanesulfonate is the simplest of the sulfonates and is a substrate for the growth of certain methylotrophic microorganisms. Compared with EC 1.14.14.5, alkanesulfonate monooxygenase, this enzyme has a restricted substrate range that includes only the short-chain aliphatic sulfonates (methanesulfonate to butanesulfonate) and excludes all larger molecules, such as arylsulfonates [1]. The enzyme from the bacterium Methylosulfonomonas methylovora is a multicomponent system comprising a hydroxylase, a reductase (MsmD) and a ferredoxin (MsmC). The hydroxylase has both large (MsmA) and small (MsmB) subunits, with each large subunit containing a Rieske-type [2Fe-2S] cluster.
HISTORY     EC 1.14.13.111 created 2009 as EC 1.14.14.6, transferred 2010 to EC 1.14.13.111
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10094704]
  AUTHORS   de Marco P, Moradas-Ferreira P, Higgins TP, McDonald I, Kenna EM, Murrell JC
  TITLE     Molecular analysis of a novel methanesulfonic acid monooxygenase from the methylotroph Methylosulfonomonas methylovora.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 181 (1999) 2244-51.
  ORGANISM  Methylosulfonomonas methylovora
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9X404 Q9X405]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8932698]
  AUTHORS   Higgins TP, Davey M, Trickett J, Kelly DP, Murrell JC
  TITLE     Metabolism of methanesulfonic acid involves a multicomponent monooxygenase enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Microbiology. 142 ( Pt 2) (1996) 251-60.
PATHWAY     ec00920  Sulfur metabolism
ORTHOLOGY   K16968  methanesulfonate monooxygenase large subunit
            K16969  methanesulfonate monooxygenase small subunit
GENES       BCT: GEM_5811 GEM_5812
            PPK: U875_05270 U875_05275
            PRB: X636_04320 X636_04325
            BPA: BPP0512 BPP0513
            BBR: BB0517 BB0518
            BBM: BN115_0496 BN115_0497
            BBH: BN112_2903 BN112_2904
            PUT: PT7_2465 PT7_2466
            MPT: Mpe_A0919(msmS2) Mpe_A0920(msmB)
            MNO: Mnod_2708 Mnod_8364 Mnod_8365
            APB: SAR116_2102 SAR116_2103 SAR116_2109
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.111
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.13.111
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.13.111
            UM-BBD (Biocatalysis/Biodegradation Database): 1.14.13.111
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.111
///
