ENTRY       EC 1.14.15.8                Enzyme
NAME        steroid 15beta-monooxygenase;
            cytochrome P-450meg;
            cytochrome P450meg;
            steroid 15beta-hydroxylase;
            CYP106A2;
            BmCYP106A2
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With reduced iron-sulfur protein as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     progesterone,reduced-ferredoxin:oxygen oxidoreductase (15beta-hydroxylating)
REACTION    progesterone + reduced ferredoxin + O2 = 15beta-hydroxyprogesterone + oxidized ferredoxin + H2O [RN:R09587]
ALL_REAC    R09587
SUBSTRATE   progesterone [CPD:C00410];
            reduced ferredoxin [CPD:C00138];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     15beta-hydroxyprogesterone [CPD:C19726];
            oxidized ferredoxin [CPD:C00139];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     The enzyme from Bacillus megaterium hydroxylates a variety of 3-oxo-Delta4-steroids in position 15beta. Ring A-reduced, aromatic, and 3beta-hydroxy-Delta4-steroids do not serve as substrates [2].
HISTORY     EC 1.14.15.8 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:109432]
  AUTHORS   Berg A, Ingelman-Sundberg M, Gustafsson JA
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of cytochrome P-450meg.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 254 (1979) 5264-71.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus megaterium
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q06069]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:177422]
  AUTHORS   Berg A, Gustafsson JA, Ingelman-Sundberg M
  TITLE     Characterization of a cytochrome P-450-dependent steroid hydroxylase system present in Bacillus megaterium.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 251 (1976) 2831-8.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus megaterium
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:15178459]
  AUTHORS   Lisurek M, Kang MJ, Hartmann RW, Bernhardt R
  TITLE     Identification of monohydroxy progesterones produced by CYP106A2 using comparative HPLC and electrospray ionisation collision-induced dissociation mass  spectrometry.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 319 (2004) 677-82.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus megaterium
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q06069]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:19635596]
  AUTHORS   Goni G, Zollner A, Lisurek M, Velazquez-Campoy A, Pinto S, Gomez-Moreno C, Hannemann F, Bernhardt R, Medina M
  TITLE     Cyanobacterial electron carrier proteins as electron donors to CYP106A2 from Bacillus megaterium ATCC 13368.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1794 (2009) 1635-42.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus megaterium
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:18481342]
  AUTHORS   Lisurek M, Simgen B, Antes I, Bernhardt R
  TITLE     Theoretical and experimental evaluation of a CYP106A2 low homology model and production of mutants with changed activity and selectivity of hydroxylation.
  JOURNAL   Chembiochem. 9 (2008) 1439-49.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus megaterium
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q06069]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.15.8
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.15.8
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.15.8
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.15.8
///
