ENTRY       EC 1.14.13.156              Enzyme
NAME        1,8-cineole 2-endo-monooxygenase;
            P450cin;
            CYP176A;
            CYP176A1
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     1,8-cineole,NADPH:oxygen oxidoreductase (2-endo-hydroxylating)
REACTION    1,8-cineole + NADPH + H+ + O2 = 2-endo-hydroxy-1,8-cineole + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R08784]
ALL_REAC    R08784
SUBSTRATE   1,8-cineole [CPD:C09844];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     2-endo-hydroxy-1,8-cineole [CPD:C03092];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     A heme-thiolate protein (P-450) which uses a flavodoxin-like redox partner to reduce the heme iron. Isolated from the bacterium Citrobacter braakii, which can use 1,8-cineole as the sole source of carbon.
HISTORY     EC 1.14.13.156 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:12016226]
  AUTHORS   Hawkes DB, Adams GW, Burlingame AL, Ortiz de Montellano PR, De Voss JJ
  TITLE     Cytochrome P450(cin) (CYP176A), isolation, expression, and characterization.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 277 (2002) 27725-32.
  ORGANISM  Citrobacter braakii
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8VQF6]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:15260491]
  AUTHORS   Meharenna YT, Li H, Hawkes DB, Pearson AG, De Voss J, Poulos TL
  TITLE     Crystal structure of P450cin in a complex with its substrate, 1,8-cineole, a close structural homologue to D-camphor, the substrate for P450cam.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 43 (2004) 9487-94.
  ORGANISM  Citrobacter braakii
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8VQF6]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:17606612]
  AUTHORS   Kimmich N, Das A, Sevrioukova I, Meharenna Y, Sligar SG, Poulos TL
  TITLE     Electron transfer between cytochrome P450cin and its FMN-containing redox partner, cindoxin.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 282 (2007) 27006-11.
  ORGANISM  Citrobacter braakii
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8VQF6]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:18270198]
  AUTHORS   Meharenna YT, Slessor KE, Cavaignac SM, Poulos TL, De Voss JJ
  TITLE     The critical role of substrate-protein hydrogen bonding in the control of regioselective hydroxylation in p450cin.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 283 (2008) 10804-12.
  ORGANISM  Citrobacter braakii
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8VQF6]
PATHWAY     ec00902  Monoterpenoid biosynthesis
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.156
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.13.156
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.13.156
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.156
///
