ENTRY       EC 1.14.13.101              Enzyme
NAME        senecionine N-oxygenase;
            senecionine monooxygenase (N-oxide-forming);
            SNO
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     senecionine,NADPH:oxygen oxidoreductase (N-oxide-forming)
REACTION    senecionine + NADPH + H+ + O2 = senecionine N-oxide + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R07373]
ALL_REAC    R07373
SUBSTRATE   senecionine [CPD:C06176];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     senecionine N-oxide [CPD:C15612];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     A flavoprotein. NADH cannot replace NADPH. While pyrrolizidine alkaloids of the senecionine and monocrotaline types are generally good substrates (e.g. senecionine, retrorsine and monocrotaline), the enzyme does not use ester alkaloids lacking an hydroxy group at C-7 (e.g. supinine and phalaenopsine), 1,2-dihydro-alkaloids (e.g. sarracine) or unesterified necine bases (e.g. senkirkine) as substrates [1]. Senecionine N-oxide is used by insects as a chemical defense: senecionine N-oxide is non-toxic, but it is bioactivated to a toxic form by the action of cytochrome P-450 oxidase when absorbed by insectivores.
HISTORY     EC 1.14.13.101 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9182998]
  AUTHORS   Lindigkeit R, Biller A, Buch M, Schiebel HM, Boppre M, Hartmann T.
  TITLE     The two facies of pyrrolizidine alkaloids: the role of the tertiary amine and its N-oxide in chemical defense of insects with acquired plant alkaloids.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 245 (1997) 626-36.
  ORGANISM  Arctia caja, Creatonotos transiens, Tyria jacobaeae, Zonocerus variegatus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8MP06]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:11972041]
  AUTHORS   Naumann C, Hartmann T, Ober D.
  TITLE     Evolutionary recruitment of a flavin-dependent monooxygenase for the detoxification of host plant-acquired pyrrolizidine alkaloids in the alkaloid-defended arctiid moth Tyria jacobaeae.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 99 (2002) 6085-90.
  ORGANISM  Tyria jacobaeae
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8MP06]
PATHWAY     ec00960  Tropane, piperidine and pyridine alkaloid biosynthesis
ORTHOLOGY   K13608  senecionine N-oxygenase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.101
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.13.101
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.13.101
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.101
            CAS: 220581-68-0
///
