ENTRY       EC 1.14.13.41               Enzyme
NAME        tyrosine N-monooxygenase;
            tyrosine N-hydroxylase;
            CYP79A1
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen;
            With NADH or NADPH as one donor, and incorporation of one atom of oxygen into the other donor
SYSNAME     L-tyrosine,NADPH:oxygen oxidoreductase (N-hydroxylating)
REACTION    L-tyrosine + 2 O2 + 2 NADPH + 2 H+ = (Z)-[4-hydroxyphenylacetaldehyde oxime] + 2 NADP+ + CO2 + 3 H2O (overall reaction) [RN:R08656];
            (1a) L-tyrosine + O2 + NADPH + H+ = N-hydroxy-L-tyrosine + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R00730];
            (1b) N-hydroxy-L-tyrosine + O2 + NADPH + H+ = N,N-dihydroxy-L-tyrosine + NADP+ + H2O [RN:R04460];
            (1c) N,N-dihydroxy-L-tyrosine = (Z)-[4-hydroxyphenylacetaldehyde oxime] + CO2 + H2O [RN:R07190]
ALL_REAC    R00730 R04460 R07190 R08656;
            (other) R06585 R10671
SUBSTRATE   L-tyrosine [CPD:C00082];
            O2 [CPD:C00007];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            N-hydroxy-L-tyrosine [CPD:C03004];
            N,N-dihydroxy-L-tyrosine [CPD:C15503]
PRODUCT     (Z)-[4-hydroxyphenylacetaldehyde oxime] [CPD:C04353];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006];
            CO2 [CPD:C00011];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            N-hydroxy-L-tyrosine [CPD:C03004];
            N,N-dihydroxy-L-tyrosine [CPD:C15503]
COMMENT     A heme-thiolate protein (P-450). This enzyme is involved in the biosynthesis of the cyanogenic glucoside dhurrin in sorghum, along with EC 1.14.13.68, 4-hydroxyphenylacetaldehyde oxime monooxygenase and EC 2.4.1.85, cyanohydrin beta-glucosyltransferase. Some 2-(4-hydroxyphenyl)-1-nitroethane is formed as a side product.
HISTORY     EC 1.14.13.41 created 1992, modified 2001, modified 2005
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:2250015]
  AUTHORS   Halkier BA, Moller BL.
  TITLE     The biosynthesis of cyanogenic glucosides in higher plants. Identification of three hydroxylation steps in the biosynthesis of dhurrin in Sorghum bicolor (L.) Moench and the involvement of 1-ACI-nitro-2-(p-hydroxyphenyl)ethane as an intermediate.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 265 (1990) 21114-21.
  ORGANISM  Sorghum bicolor
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7876084]
  AUTHORS   Sibbesen O, Koch B, Halkier BA, Moller BL.
  TITLE     Cytochrome P-450TYR is a multifunctional heme-thiolate enzyme catalyzing the conversion of L-tyrosine to p-hydroxyphenylacetaldehyde oxime in the biosynthesis of the cyanogenic glucoside dhurrin in Sorghum bicolor (L.) Moench.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 270 (1995) 3506-11.
  ORGANISM  Sorghum bicolor
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10938360]
  AUTHORS   Bak S, Olsen CE, Halkier BA, Moller BL.
  TITLE     Transgenic tobacco and Arabidopsis plants expressing the two multifunctional sorghum cytochrome P450 enzymes, CYP79A1 and CYP71E1, are cyanogenic and accumulate metabolites derived from intermediates in Dhurrin biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 123 (2000) 1437-48.
  ORGANISM  Sorghum bicolor
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:10759528]
  AUTHORS   Nielsen JS, Moller BL.
  TITLE     Cloning and expression of cytochrome P450 enzymes catalyzing the conversion of tyrosine to p-hydroxyphenylacetaldoxime in the biosynthesis of cyanogenic glucosides in Triglochin maritima.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 122 (2000) 1311-21.
  ORGANISM  Triglochin maritima
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:12114576]
  AUTHORS   Busk PK, Moller BL.
  TITLE     Dhurrin synthesis in sorghum is regulated at the transcriptional level and induced by nitrogen fertilization in older plants.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 129 (2002) 1222-31.
  ORGANISM  Sorghum bicolor
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:15665094]
  AUTHORS   Kristensen C, Morant M, Olsen CE, Ekstrom CT, Galbraith DW, Moller BL, Bak S.
  TITLE     Metabolic engineering of dhurrin in transgenic Arabidopsis plants with marginal inadvertent effects on the metabolome and transcriptome.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 102 (2005) 1779-84.
  ORGANISM  Sorghum bicolor
PATHWAY     ec00460  Cyanoamino acid metabolism
            ec00966  Glucosinolate biosynthesis
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K13027  tyrosine N-monooxygenase
GENES       BDI: 100844710
            SBI: SORBI_01g001200(SORBIDRAFT_01g001200)
            SITA: 101771875 101781613
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.41
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.14.13.41
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.14.13.41
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.14.13.41
            CAS: 159447-19-5
///
