ENTRY       EC 1.16.9.1                 Enzyme
NAME        iron:rusticyanin reductase;
            Cyc2
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Oxidizing metal ions;
            With a copper protein as acceptor
SYSNAME     Fe(II):rusticyanin oxidoreductase
REACTION    Fe(II) + rusticyanin = Fe(III) + reduced rusticyanin
SUBSTRATE   Fe(II) [CPD:C14818];
            rusticyanin
PRODUCT     Fe(III) [CPD:C14819];
            reduced rusticyanin
COMMENT     Contains c-type heme. The enzyme in Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans is a component of an electron transfer chain from Fe(II), comprising this enzyme, the copper protein rusticyanin, cytochrome c4, and cytochrome c oxidase (EC 1.9.3.1).
HISTORY     EC 1.16.9.1 created 2011 as EC 1.16.98.1, transferred 2011 to EC 1.16.9.1
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8049223]
  AUTHORS   Blake RC 2nd, Shute EA
  TITLE     Respiratory enzymes of Thiobacillus ferrooxidans. Kinetic properties of an acid-stable iron:rusticyanin oxidoreductase.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 33 (1994) 9220-8.
  ORGANISM  Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9809418]
  AUTHORS   Appia-Ayme C, Bengrine A, Cavazza C, Giudici-Orticoni MT, Bruschi M, Chippaux M, Bonnefoy V
  TITLE     Characterization and expression of the co-transcribed cyc1 and cyc2 genes encoding the cytochrome c4 (c552) and a high-molecular-mass cytochrome c from Thiobacillus ferrooxidans ATCC 33020.
  JOURNAL   FEMS. Microbiol. Lett. 167 (1998) 171-7.
  ORGANISM  Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11741873]
  AUTHORS   Yarzabal A, Brasseur G, Ratouchniak J, Lund K, Lemesle-Meunier D, DeMoss JA, Bonnefoy V
  TITLE     The high-molecular-weight cytochrome c Cyc2 of Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans is  an outer membrane protein.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 184 (2002) 313-7.
  ORGANISM  Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15256554]
  AUTHORS   Yarzabal A, Appia-Ayme C, Ratouchniak J, Bonnefoy V
  TITLE     Regulation of the expression of the Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans rus operon encoding two cytochromes c, a cytochrome oxidase and rusticyanin.
  JOURNAL   Microbiology. 150 (2004) 2113-23.
  ORGANISM  Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:18791023]
  AUTHORS   Taha TM, Kanao T, Takeuchi F, Sugio T
  TITLE     Reconstitution of iron oxidase from sulfur-grown Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 74 (2008) 6808-10.
  ORGANISM  Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:18632666]
  AUTHORS   Castelle C, Guiral M, Malarte G, Ledgham F, Leroy G, Brugna M, Giudici-Orticoni MT
  TITLE     A new iron-oxidizing/O2-reducing supercomplex spanning both inner and outer membranes, isolated from the extreme acidophile Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 283 (2008) 25803-11.
  ORGANISM  Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:19703284]
  AUTHORS   Quatrini R, Appia-Ayme C, Denis Y, Jedlicki E, Holmes DS, Bonnefoy V
  TITLE     Extending the models for iron and sulfur oxidation in the extreme acidophile Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans.
  JOURNAL   BMC. Genomics. 10 (2009) 394.
  ORGANISM  Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.16.9.1
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.16.9.1
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.16.9.1
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.16.9.1
///
