ENTRY       EC 1.17.99.5                Enzyme
NAME        bile-acid 7alpha-dehydroxylase;
            cholate 7alpha-dehydroxylase;
            7alpha-dehydroxylase;
            bile acid 7-dehydroxylase;
            deoxycholate:NAD+ oxidoreductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on CH or CH2 groups;
            With other acceptors
SYSNAME     deoxycholate:FAD oxidoreductase (7alpha-dehydroxylating)
REACTION    (1) deoxycholate + FAD + H2O = cholate + FADH2 [RN:R07220];
            (2) lithocholate + FAD + H2O = chenodeoxycholate + FADH2 [RN:R03978]
ALL_REAC    R03978 R07220
SUBSTRATE   deoxycholate [CPD:C04483];
            FAD [CPD:C00016];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            lithocholate [CPD:C03990]
PRODUCT     cholate [CPD:C00695];
            FADH2 [CPD:C01352];
            chenodeoxycholate [CPD:C02528]
COMMENT     Under physiological conditions, the reactions occur in the reverse direction to that shown above. This enzyme is highly specific for bile-acid substrates and requires a free C-24 carboxy group and an unhindered 7alpha-hydroxy group on the B-ring of the steroid nucleus for activity, as found in cholate and chenodeoxycholate. The reaction is stimulated by the presence of NAD+ but is inhibited by excess NADH. This unusual regulation by the NAD+/NADH ratio is most likely the result of the intermediates being linked at C-24 by an anhydride bond to the 5'-diphosphate of 3'-phospho-ADP [2,5,6]. Allo-deoxycholate is also formed as a side-product of the 7alpha-dehydroxylation of cholate [6]. The enzyme is present in intestinal anaerobic bacteria [6], even though its products are important in mammalian physiology.
HISTORY     EC 1.17.99.5 created 2005 as EC 1.17.1.6, transferred 2006 to EC 1.17.99.5
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:7276750]
  AUTHORS   White BA, Cacciapuoti AF, Fricke RJ, Whitehead TR, Mosbach EH, Hylemon PB.
  TITLE     Cofactor requiremets for 7 alpha-dehydroxylation of cholic and chenodeoxycholic acid in cell extracts of the intestinal anaerobic bacterium, Eubacterium species V.P.I. 13708.
  JOURNAL   J. Lipid. Res. 22 (1981) 891-8.
  ORGANISM  Eubacterium sp.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:6833878]
  AUTHORS   White BA, Paone DA, Cacciapuoti AF, Fricke RJ, Mosbach EH, Hylemon PB.
  TITLE     Regulation of bile acid 7-dehydroxylase activity by NAD+ and NADH in cell extracts of Eubacterium species V.P.I. 12708.
  JOURNAL   J. Lipid. Res. 24 (1983) 20-7.
  ORGANISM  Eubacterium sp.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:3549693]
  AUTHORS   Coleman JP, White WB, Hylemon PB.
  TITLE     Molecular cloning of bile acid 7-dehydroxylase from Eubacterium sp. strain VPI 12708.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 169 (1987) 1516-21.
  ORGANISM  Eubacterium sp.
  SEQUENCE  [up:P07914]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12543708]
  AUTHORS   Russell DW.
  TITLE     The enzymes, regulation, and genetics of bile acid synthesis.
  JOURNAL   Annu. Rev. Biochem. 72 (2003) 137-74.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:3558364]
  AUTHORS   Coleman JP, White WB, Egestad B, Sjovall J, Hylemon PB.
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of a novel bile acid nucleotide and mechanism of 7 alpha-dehydroxylation by an intestinal Eubacterium species.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 262 (1987) 4701-7.
  ORGANISM  Eubacterium sp.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:2010697]
  AUTHORS   Hylemon PB, Melone PD, Franklund CV, Lund E, Bjorkhem I.
  TITLE     Mechanism of intestinal 7 alpha-dehydroxylation of cholic acid: evidence that allo-deoxycholic acid is an inducible side-product.
  JOURNAL   J. Lipid. Res. 32 (1991) 89-96.
  ORGANISM  Eubacterium sp.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.17.99.5
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.17.99.5
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.17.99.5
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.17.99.5
            CAS: 85130-33-2
///
