ENTRY       EC 1.17.5.1                 Enzyme
NAME        phenylacetyl-CoA dehydrogenase;
            phenylacetyl-CoA:acceptor oxidoreductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on CH or CH2 groups;
            With a quinone or similar compound as acceptor
SYSNAME     phenylacetyl-CoA:quinone oxidoreductase
REACTION    phenylacetyl-CoA + H2O + 2 quinone = phenylglyoxylyl-CoA + 2 quinol [RN:R07222]
ALL_REAC    R07222
SUBSTRATE   phenylacetyl-CoA [CPD:C00582];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            quinone [CPD:C00472]
PRODUCT     phenylglyoxylyl-CoA [CPD:C15524];
            quinol [CPD:C00530]
COMMENT     The enzyme from Thauera aromatica is a membrane-bound molybdenum---iron---sulfur protein. The enzyme is specific for phenylacetyl-CoA as substrate. Phenylacetate, acetyl-CoA, benzoyl-CoA, propanoyl-CoA, crotonyl-CoA, succinyl-CoA and 3-hydroxybenzoyl-CoA cannot act as substrates. The oxygen atom introduced into the product, phenylglyoxylyl-CoA, is derived from water and not molecular oxygen. Duroquinone, menaquinone and 2,6-dichlorophenolindophenol (DCPIP) can act as acceptor, but the likely physiological acceptor is ubiquinone [1]. A second enzyme, EC 3.1.2.25, phenylacetyl-CoA hydrolase, converts the phenylglyoxylyl-CoA formed into phenylglyoxylate.
HISTORY     EC 1.17.5.1 created 2004
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10336636]
  AUTHORS   Rhee SK, Fuchs G.
  TITLE     Phenylacetyl-CoA:acceptor oxidoreductase, a membrane-bound molybdenum-iron-sulfur enzyme involved in anaerobic metabolism of phenylalanine in the denitrifying bacterium Thauera aromatica.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 262 (1999) 507-15.
  ORGANISM  Thauera aromatica
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9575237]
  AUTHORS   Schneider S, Fuchs G.
  TITLE     Phenylacetyl-CoA:acceptor oxidoreductase, a new alpha-oxidizing enzyme that produces phenylglyoxylate. Assay, membrane localization, and differential production in Thauera aromatica.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Microbiol. 169 (1998) 509-16.
  ORGANISM  Thauera aromatica
PATHWAY     ec00360  Phenylalanine metabolism
ORTHOLOGY   K18361  phenylacetyl-CoA:acceptor oxidoreductase
GENES       EBA: ebA5393(padB)
            AZO: azo1946(padB)
            AZA: AZKH_2904(padB)
            TMZ: Tmz1t_0199 Tmz1t_2959
            RPD: RPD_1507
            MAG: amb1241 amb2015
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.17.5.1
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.17.5.1
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.17.5.1
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.17.5.1
            CAS: 210756-43-7
///
