ENTRY       EC 1.17.1.5                 Enzyme
NAME        nicotinate dehydrogenase;
            nicotinic acid hydroxylase;
            nicotinate hydroxylase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on CH or CH2 groups;
            With NAD+ or NADP+ as acceptor
SYSNAME     nicotinate:NADP+ 6-oxidoreductase (hydroxylating)
REACTION    nicotinate + H2O + NADP+ = 6-hydroxynicotinate + NADPH + H+ [RN:R01720]
ALL_REAC    R01720
SUBSTRATE   nicotinate [CPD:C00253];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006]
PRODUCT     6-hydroxynicotinate [CPD:C01020];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     A flavoprotein containing non-heme iron. The enzyme is capable of acting on a variety of nicotinate analogues to varying degrees, including pyrazine-2-carboxylate, pyrazine 2,3-dicarboxylate, trigonelline and 6-methylnicotinate. The enzyme from Clostridium barkeri also possesses a catalytically essential, labile selenium that can be removed by reaction with cyanide.
HISTORY     EC 1.17.1.5 created 1972 as EC 1.5.1.13, transferred 2004 to EC 1.17.1.5
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:4388026]
  AUTHORS   Holcenberg JS, Stadtman ER.
  TITLE     Nicotinic acid metabolism. 3. Purification and properties of a nicotinic acid hydroxylase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 244 (1969) 1194-203.
  ORGANISM  Clostridium sp.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8555176]
  AUTHORS   Gladyshev VN, Khangulov SV, Stadtman TC.
  TITLE     Properties of the selenium- and molybdenum-containing nicotinic acid hydroxylase from Clostridium barkeri.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 35 (1996) 212-23.
  ORGANISM  Clostridium barkeri
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8278371]
  AUTHORS   Gladyshev VN, Khangulov SV, Stadtman TC.
  TITLE     Nicotinic acid hydroxylase from Clostridium barkeri: electron paramagnetic resonance studies show that selenium is coordinated with molybdenum in the catalytically active selenium-dependent enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 91 (1994) 232-6.
  ORGANISM  Clostridium barkeri
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:6838209]
  AUTHORS   Dilworth GL.
  TITLE     Occurrence of molybdenum in the nicotinic acid hydroxylase from Clostridium barkeri.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 221 (1983) 565-9.
  ORGANISM  Clostridium barkeri
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:7181513]
  AUTHORS   Dilworth GL.
  TITLE     Properties of the selenium-containing moiety of nicotinic acid hydroxylase from Clostridium barkeri.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 219 (1982) 30-8.
  ORGANISM  Clostridium barkeri
REFERENCE   6
  AUTHORS   Nagel, M. and Andreesen, J.R.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of the molybdoenzymes nicotinate dehydrogenase and 6-hydroxynicotinate dehydrogenase from Bacillus niacini.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Microbiol. 154 (1990) 605-613.
PATHWAY     ec00760  Nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolism
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.17.1.5
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.17.1.5
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.17.1.5
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.17.1.5
            CAS: 9059-03-4
///
