ENTRY       EC 1.18.1.6                 Enzyme
NAME        adrenodoxin-NADP+ reductase;
            adrenodoxin reductase;
            nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate-adrenodoxin reductase;
            AdR;
            NADPH:adrenal ferredoxin oxidoreductase;
            NADPH-adrenodoxin reductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on iron-sulfur proteins as donors;
            With NAD+ or NADP+ as acceptor
SYSNAME     adrenodoxin:NADP+ oxidoreductase
REACTION    2 reduced adrenodoxin + NADP+ = 2 oxidized adrenodoxin + NADPH + H+ [RN:R10159]
ALL_REAC    R10159
SUBSTRATE   reduced adrenodoxin [CPD:C00662];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006]
PRODUCT     oxidized adrenodoxin [CPD:C00667];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     A flavoprotein (FAD). The enzyme is the first component in the mitochondrial cytochrome P-450 electron transfer systems, and is involved in the biosynthesis of all steroid hormones.
HISTORY     EC 1.18.1.6 created 1965 as EC 1.6.99.4, transferred 1972 as EC 1.6.7.1, transferred 1978 to EC 1.18.1.2, part transferred 2012 to 1.18.1.6
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Omura, T., Sanders, E., Estabrook, R.W., Cooper, D.Y. and Rosenthal, O.
  TITLE     Isolation from adrenal cortex of a nonheme iron protein and a flavoprotein functional as a reduced triphosphopyridine nucleotide-cytochrome P-450 reductase.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 117 (1966) 660-673.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:4144106]
  AUTHORS   Chu JW, Kimura T
  TITLE     Studies on adrenal steroid hydroxylases. Molecular and catalytic properties of adrenodoxin reductase (a flavoprotein).
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 248 (1973) 2089-94.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:235468]
  AUTHORS   Sugiyama T, Yamano T
  TITLE     Purification and crystallization of NADPH-adrenodoxin reductase from bovine adrenocortical mitochondria.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 52 (1975) 145-8.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:6766943]
  AUTHORS   Hanukoglu I, Jefcoate CR.
  TITLE     Mitochondrial cytochrome P-450sec. Mechanism of electron transport by adrenodoxin.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 255 (1980) 3057-61.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:3011431]
  AUTHORS   Hanukoglu I, Hanukoglu Z
  TITLE     Stoichiometry of mitochondrial cytochromes P-450, adrenodoxin and adrenodoxin reductase in adrenal cortex and corpus luteum. Implications for membrane organization and gene regulation.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 157 (1986) 27-31.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:2924777]
  AUTHORS   Hanukoglu I, Gutfinger T
  TITLE     cDNA sequence of adrenodoxin reductase. Identification of NADP-binding sites in oxidoreductases.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 180 (1989) 479-84.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
  SEQUENCE  [bta:282604]
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:10369776]
  AUTHORS   Ziegler GA, Vonrhein C, Hanukoglu I, Schulz GE
  TITLE     The structure of adrenodoxin reductase of mitochondrial P450 systems: electron transfer for steroid biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 289 (1999) 981-90.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
  SEQUENCE  [bta:282604]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.18.1.6
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.18.1.6
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.18.1.6
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.18.1.6
///
