ENTRY       EC 1.21.3.6                 Enzyme
NAME        aureusidin synthase;
            AmAS1
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on X-H and Y-H to form an X-Y bond;
            With oxygen as acceptor
SYSNAME     2',4,4',6'-tetrahydroxychalcone 4'-O-beta-D-glucoside:oxygen oxidoreductase
REACTION    (1) 2',4,4',6'-tetrahydroxychalcone 4'-O-beta-D-glucoside + O2 = aureusidin 6-O-beta-D-glucoside + H2O [RN:R08008];
            (2) 2',3,4,4',6'-pentahydroxychalcone 4'-O-beta-D-glucoside + 1/2 O2 = aureusidin 6-O-beta-D-glucoside + H2O [RN:R08010];
            (3) 2',3,4,4',6'-pentahydroxychalcone 4'-O-beta-D-glucoside + O2 = bracteatin 6-O-beta-D-glucoside + H2O [RN:R08009]
ALL_REAC    R08008 R08009 R08010;
            (other) R07224 R07225 R08005
SUBSTRATE   2',4,4',6'-tetrahydroxychalcone 4'-O-beta-D-glucoside [CPD:C16407];
            O2 [CPD:C00007];
            2',3,4,4',6'-pentahydroxychalcone 4'-O-beta-D-glucoside [CPD:C16408]
PRODUCT     aureusidin 6-O-beta-D-glucoside [CPD:C16409];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            bracteatin 6-O-beta-D-glucoside [CPD:C16410]
COMMENT     A copper-containing glycoprotein that plays a key role in the yellow coloration of flowers such as Antirrhinum majus (snapdragon). The enzyme is a homologue of plant polyphenol oxidase [1] and catalyses two separate chemical transformations, i.e. 3-hydroxylation and oxidative cyclization (2',-dehydrogenation). H2O2 activates reaction (1) but inhibits reaction (2). Originally considered to act on the phenol but now thought to act mainly on the 4'-O-beta-D-glucoside in vivo [4].
HISTORY     EC 1.21.3.6 created 2003, modified 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:11073455]
  AUTHORS   Nakayama T, Yonekura-Sakakibara K, Sato T, Kikuchi S, Fukui Y, Fukuchi-Mizutani M, Ueda T, Nakao M, Tanaka Y, Kusumi T, Nishino T.
  TITLE     Aureusidin synthase: a polyphenol oxidase homolog responsible for flower coloration.
  JOURNAL   Science. 290 (2000) 1163-6.
  ORGANISM  Antirrhinum majus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9FRX6]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:11418122]
  AUTHORS   Nakayama T, Sato T, Fukui Y, Yonekura-Sakakibara K, Hayashi H, Tanaka Y, Kusumi T, Nishino T.
  TITLE     Specificity analysis and mechanism of aurone synthesis catalyzed by aureusidin synthase, a polyphenol oxidase homolog responsible for flower coloration.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 499 (2001) 107-11.
  ORGANISM  Antirrhinum majus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9FRX6]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11164594]
  AUTHORS   Sato T, Nakayama T, Kikuchi S, Fukui Y, Yonekura-Sakakibara K, Ueda T, Nishino T, Tanaka Y, Kusumi T.
  TITLE     Enzymatic formation of aurones in the extracts of yellow snapdragon flowers.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Sci. 160 (2001) 229-236.
  ORGANISM  Antirrhinum majus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16832053]
  AUTHORS   Ono E, Fukuchi-Mizutani M, Nakamura N, Fukui Y, Yonekura-Sakakibara K, Yamaguchi M, Nakayama T, Tanaka T, Kusumi T, Tanaka Y.
  TITLE     Yellow flowers generated by expression of the aurone biosynthetic pathway.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 103 (2006) 11075-80.
  ORGANISM  Antirrhinum majus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9FRX6]
PATHWAY     ec00941  Flavonoid biosynthesis
ORTHOLOGY   K13079  aureusidin synthase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.21.3.6
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.21.3.6
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.21.3.6
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.21.3.6
            CAS: 320784-48-3
///
