ENTRY       EC 1.21.3.7                 Enzyme
NAME        tetrahydrocannabinolic acid synthase;
            THCA synthase;
            Delta1-tetrahydrocannabinolic acid synthase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on X-H and Y-H to form an X-Y bond;
            With oxygen as acceptor
SYSNAME     cannabigerolate:oxygen oxidoreductase (cyclizing, Delta9-tetrahydrocannabinolate-forming)
REACTION    cannabigerolate + O2 = Delta9-tetrahydrocannabinolate + H2O2
SUBSTRATE   cannabigerolate [CPD:C20406];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     Delta9-tetrahydrocannabinolate;
            H2O2 [CPD:C00027]
COMMENT     A flavoprotein (FAD). The cofactor is covalently bound. Part of the cannabinoids biosynthetic pathway in the plant Cannabis sativa. The enzyme can also convert cannabinerolate (the (Z)-isomer of cannabigerolate) to Delta9-THCA with lower efficiency. Whereas the product was originally called Delta1-tetrahydrocannabinolate, the recommended name according to systematic peripheral numbering is Delta9-tetrahydrocannabinolate.
HISTORY     EC 1.21.3.7 created 2012
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Taura, F., Morimoto, S. Shoyama, Y. and Mechoulam, R.
  TITLE     First direct evidence for the mechanism of Delta1-tetrahydrocannabinolic acid biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 117 (1995) 9766-9767.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:15190053]
  AUTHORS   Sirikantaramas S, Morimoto S, Shoyama Y, Ishikawa Y, Wada Y, Shoyama Y, Taura F
  TITLE     The gene controlling marijuana psychoactivity: molecular cloning and heterologous expression of Delta1-tetrahydrocannabinolic acid synthase from Cannabis sativa L.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 279 (2004) 39767-74.
  ORGANISM  Cannabis sativa
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8GTB6]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16511162]
  AUTHORS   Shoyama Y, Takeuchi A, Taura F, Tamada T, Adachi M, Kuroki R, Shoyama Y, Morimoto S
  TITLE     Crystallization of Delta1-tetrahydrocannabinolic acid (THCA) synthase from Cannabis sativa.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. Sect. F. Struct. Biol. Cryst. Commun. 61 (2005) 799-801.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:22766313]
  AUTHORS   Shoyama Y, Tamada T, Kurihara K, Takeuchi A, Taura F, Arai S, Blaber M, Shoyama Y, Morimoto S, Kuroki R
  TITLE     Structure and function of 1-tetrahydrocannabinolic acid (THCA) synthase, the enzyme controlling the psychoactivity of Cannabis sativa.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 423 (2012) 96-105.
  ORGANISM  Cannabis sativa
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8GTB6]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.21.3.7
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.21.3.7
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.21.3.7
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.21.3.7
///
