ENTRY       EC 1.3.1.100                Enzyme
NAME        chanoclavine-I aldehyde reductase;
            FgaOx3;
            easA (gene name)
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-CH group of donors;
            With NAD+ or NADP+ as acceptor
SYSNAME     chanoclavine-I aldehyde:NAD+ oxidoreductase
REACTION    dihydrochanoclavine-I aldehyde + NADP+ = chanoclavine-I aldehyde + NADPH + H+
SUBSTRATE   dihydrochanoclavine-I aldehyde;
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006]
PRODUCT     chanoclavine-I aldehyde [CPD:C20379];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     Contains FMN. The enzyme participates in the biosynthesis of fumigaclavine C, an ergot alkaloid produced by some fungi of the Trichocomaceae family. The enzyme catalyses the reduction of chanoclavine-I aldehyde to dihydrochanoclavine-I aldehyde. This hydrolyses spontaneously to form 6,8-dimethyl-6,7-didehydroergoline, which is converted to festuclavine by EC 1.5.1.44, festuclavine dehydrogenase.
HISTORY     EC 1.3.1.100 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:20435769]
  AUTHORS   Coyle CM, Cheng JZ, O'Connor SE, Panaccione DG
  TITLE     An old yellow enzyme gene controls the branch point between Aspergillus fumigatus and Claviceps purpurea ergot alkaloid pathways.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 76 (2010) 3898-903.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:20102147]
  AUTHORS   Cheng JZ, Coyle CM, Panaccione DG, O'Connor SE
  TITLE     A role for Old Yellow Enzyme in ergot alkaloid biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 132 (2010) 1776-7.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:20526482]
  AUTHORS   Wallwey C, Matuschek M, Xie XL, Li SM
  TITLE     Ergot alkaloid biosynthesis in Aspergillus fumigatus: Conversion of chanoclavine-I aldehyde to festuclavine by the festuclavine synthase FgaFS in the presence of the old yellow enzyme FgaOx3.
  JOURNAL   Org. Biomol. Chem. 8 (2010) 3500-8.
  ORGANISM  Neosartorya fumigata
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q4WZ70]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:21898587]
  AUTHORS   Xie X, Wallwey C, Matuschek M, Steinbach K, Li SM
  TITLE     Formyl migration product of chanoclavine-I aldehyde in the presence of the old yellow enzyme FgaOx3 from Aspergillus fumigatus: a NMR structure elucidation.
  JOURNAL   Magn. Reson. Chem. 49 (2011) 678-81.
  ORGANISM  Neosartorya fumigata
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q4WZ70]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.3.1.100
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.3.1.100
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.3.1.100
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.3.1.100
///
