ENTRY       EC 1.3.1.80                 Enzyme
NAME        red chlorophyll catabolite reductase;
            RCCR;
            RCC reductase;
            red Chl catabolite reductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on the CH-CH group of donors;
            With NAD+ or NADP+ as acceptor
SYSNAME     primary fluorescent chlorophyll catabolite:NADP+ oxidoreductase
REACTION    primary fluorescent chlorophyll catabolite + NADP+ = red chlorophyll catabolite + NADPH + H+ [RN:R09032]
ALL_REAC    R09032
SUBSTRATE   primary fluorescent chlorophyll catabolite [CPD:C18098];
            NADP+ [CPD:C00006]
PRODUCT     red chlorophyll catabolite [CPD:C18022];
            NADPH [CPD:C00005];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     Chlorophyll degradation is a characteristic symptom of leaf senescence and fruit ripening. The reaction catalysed by this enzyme requires reduced ferredoxin, which is generated either by NADPH through the pentose-phosphate pathway or by the action of photosystem I [1,2]. This reaction takes place without release of the substrate from EC 1.14.12.20, pheophorbide a oxygenase [3]. Depending on the plant species used as the source of enzyme, one of two possible C-1 epimers of primary fluorescent chlorophyll catabolite (pFCC), pFCC-1 or pFCC-2, is normally formed, with all genera or species within a family producing the same isomer [3,4]. After modification and export, pFCCs are eventually imported into the vacuole, where the acidic environment causes their non-enzymic conversion into colourless breakdown products called non-fluorescent chlorophyll catabolites (NCCs) [2].
HISTORY     EC 1.3.1.80 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:12223835]
  AUTHORS   Rodoni S, Muhlecker W, Anderl M, Krautler B, Moser D, Thomas H, Matile P, Hortensteiner S.
  TITLE     Chlorophyll Breakdown in Senescent Chloroplasts (Cleavage of Pheophorbide a in Two Enzymic Steps).
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 115 (1997) 669-676.
  ORGANISM  Brassica napus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:10743659]
  AUTHORS   Wuthrich KL, Bovet L, Hunziker PE, Donnison IS, Hortensteiner S.
  TITLE     Molecular cloning, functional expression and characterisation of RCC reductase involved in chlorophyll catabolism.
  JOURNAL   Plant. J. 21 (2000) 189-98.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana, Hordeum vulgare
  SEQUENCE  [ath:AT4G37000]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:17237353]
  AUTHORS   Pruzinska A, Anders I, Aubry S, Schenk N, Tapernoux-Luthi E, Muller T, Krautler B, Hortensteiner S.
  TITLE     In vivo participation of red chlorophyll catabolite reductase in chlorophyll breakdown.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Cell. 19 (2007) 369-87.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana
  SEQUENCE  [ath:AT4G37000]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16669755]
  AUTHORS   Hortensteiner S.
  TITLE     Chlorophyll degradation during senescence.
  JOURNAL   Annu. Rev. Plant. Biol. 57 (2006) 55-77.
  ORGANISM  Hordeum vulgare, Solanum lycopersicum, Spinacia oleracea, Arabidopsis sp.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:12223836]
  AUTHORS   Rodoni S, Vicentini F, Schellenberg M, Matile P, Hortensteiner S.
  TITLE     Partial Purification and Characterization of Red Chlorophyll Catabolite Reductase, a Stroma Protein Involved in Chlorophyll Breakdown.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 115 (1997) 677-682.
  ORGANISM  Hordeum vulgare
PATHWAY     ec00860  Porphyrin and chlorophyll metabolism
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K13545  red chlorophyll catabolite reductase
GENES       ATH: AT4G37000(ACD2)
            ALY: ARALYDRAFT_353127
            CRB: CARUB_v10005253mg
            EUS: EUTSA_v10025731mg EUTSA_v10027845mg EUTSA_v10027846mg
            CIT: 102622999 102623285
            CIC: CICLE_v10026041mg CICLE_v10026248mg
            TCC: TCM_000609
            GMX: 100777640 100780934
            MTR: MTR_5g096150
            CAM: 101488374
            FVE: 101301239
            CSV: 101202861 101223133
            RCU: RCOM_1407700
            POP: POPTR_0007s11040g(POPTRDRAFT_819935) POPTR_0007s11060g(POPTRDRAFT_764544) POPTR_0007s11070g(POPTRDRAFT_764546)
            VVI: 100252439
            SLY: 778267(rccr)
            SOT: 102591737
            OSA: 4348519
            DOSA: Os10t0389100-00(Os10g0389100) Os10t0389200-01(Os10g0389200) Os10t0389300-01(Os10g0389300)
            OBR: 102703616
            BDI: 100841732 100843855
            SBI: SORBI_01g029900(SORBIDRAFT_01g029900) SORBI_03g012660(SORBIDRAFT_03g012660) SORBI_05g017270(SORBIDRAFT_05g017270)
            ZMA: 100272914
            SITA: 101780665
            ATR: s00132p00112670(AMTR_s00132p00112670)
            SMO: SELMODRAFT_186296 SELMODRAFT_269565
            PPP: PHYPADRAFT_130472
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.3.1.80
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.3.1.80
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.3.1.80
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.3.1.80
///
