ENTRY       EC 1.6.3.4                  Enzyme
NAME        NADH oxidase (H2O-forming);
            H2O-forming NADH oxidase;
            Nox-2
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on NADH or NADPH;
            With oxygen as acceptor
SYSNAME     NADH:oxygen oxidoreductase (H2O-forming)
REACTION    2 NADH + 2 H+ + O2 = 2 NAD+ + 2 H2O [RN:R10517]
ALL_REAC    R10517
SUBSTRATE   NADH [CPD:C00004];
            H+ [CPD:C00080];
            O2 [CPD:C00007]
PRODUCT     NAD+ [CPD:C00003];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     A flavoprotein (FAD). The bacterium Streptococcus mutans contains two distinct NADH oxidases, a H2O-forming enzyme and a H2O2-forming enzyme (cf. EC 1.6.3.3, NADH oxidase (H2O2-forming)) [1].
HISTORY     EC 1.6.3.4 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3082630]
  AUTHORS   Schmidt HL, Stocklein W, Danzer J, Kirch P, Limbach B
  TITLE     Isolation and properties of an H2O-forming NADH oxidase from Streptococcus faecalis.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 156 (1986) 149-55.
  ORGANISM  Enterococcus faecalis
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8254304]
  AUTHORS   Higuchi M, Shimada M, Yamamoto Y, Hayashi T, Koga T, Kamio Y
  TITLE     Identification of two distinct NADH oxidases corresponding to H2O2-forming oxidase and H2O-forming oxidase induced in Streptococcus mutans.
  JOURNAL   J. Gen. Microbiol. 139 (1993) 2343-51.
  ORGANISM  Streptococcus mutans
  SEQUENCE  [smu:SMU_1117]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8824824]
  AUTHORS   Matsumoto J, Higuchi M, Shimada M, Yamamoto Y, Kamio Y
  TITLE     Molecular cloning and sequence analysis of the gene encoding the H2O-forming NADH oxidase from Streptococcus mutans.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 60 (1996) 39-43.
  ORGANISM  Streptococcus mutans
  SEQUENCE  [smu:SMU_1117]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15014929]
  AUTHORS   Kawasaki S, Ishikura J, Chiba D, Nishino T, Niimura Y
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of an H2O-forming NADH oxidase from Clostridium aminovalericum: existence of an oxygen-detoxifying enzyme in an obligate anaerobic bacteria.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Microbiol. 181 (2004) 324-30.
  ORGANISM  Clostridium aminovalericum
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:22418266]
  AUTHORS   Zhang YW, Tiwari MK, Gao H, Dhiman SS, Jeya M, Lee JK
  TITLE     Cloning and characterization of a thermostable H2O-forming NADH oxidase from Lactobacillus rhamnosus.
  JOURNAL   Enzyme. Microb. Technol. 50 (2012) 255-62.
  ORGANISM  Lactobacillus rhamnosus
  SEQUENCE  [lrg:LRHM_0312]
ORTHOLOGY   K17869  NADH oxidase (H2O-forming)
GENES       LCA: LSEI_0285
            LCB: LCABL_02800(nox)
            LCZ: LCAZH_0305
            LCS: LCBD_0278
            LCE: LC2W_0269
            LCW: BN194_02850(nox_2)
            LCL: LOCK919_0299
            LRH: LGG_00325(nox)
            LRG: LRHM_0312
            LRL: LC705_00311(nox)
            LRA: LRHK_319(nox)
            LRO: LOCK900_0301
            LRC: LOCK908_0315
            LPI: LBPG_02448
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.6.3.4
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.6.3.4
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.6.3.4
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.6.3.4
///
