ENTRY       EC 1.7.5.1                  Enzyme
NAME        nitrate reductase (quinone);
            nitrate reductase A;
            nitrate reductase Z;
            quinol/nitrate oxidoreductase;
            quinol-nitrate oxidoreductase;
            quinol:nitrate oxidoreductase;
            NarA;
            NarZ;
            NarGHI;
            dissimilatory nitrate reductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on other nitrogenous compounds as donors;
            With a quinone or similar compound as acceptor
SYSNAME     nitrite:quinone oxidoreductase
REACTION    nitrate + a quinol = nitrite + a quinone + H2O [RN:R09497]
ALL_REAC    R09497
SUBSTRATE   nitrate [CPD:C00244];
            quinol [CPD:C15603]
PRODUCT     nitrite [CPD:C00088];
            quinone [CPD:C15602];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     A membrane-bound enzyme which supports anaerobic respiration on nitrate under anaerobic conditions and in the presence of nitrate. Contains the bicyclic form of the molybdo-bis(molybdopterin guanine dinucleotide) cofactor, iron-sulfur clusters and heme b. Escherichia coli expresses two forms NarA and NarZ, both being comprised of three subunits.
HISTORY     EC 1.7.5.1 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:4616697]
  AUTHORS   Enoch HG, Lester RL
  TITLE     The role of a novel cytochrome b-containing nitrate reductase and quinone in the  in vitro reconstruction of formate-nitrate reductase activity of E. coli.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 61 (1974) 1234-41.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12910261]
  AUTHORS   Bertero MG, Rothery RA, Palak M, Hou C, Lim D, Blasco F, Weiner JH, Strynadka NC
  TITLE     Insights into the respiratory electron transfer pathway from the structure of nitrate reductase A.
  JOURNAL   Nat. Struct. Biol. 10 (2003) 681-7.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:17439244]
  AUTHORS   Lanciano P, Magalon A, Bertrand P, Guigliarelli B, Grimaldi S
  TITLE     High-stability semiquinone intermediate in nitrate reductase A (NarGHI) from Escherichia coli is located in a quinol oxidation site close to heme bD.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 46 (2007) 5323-9.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15615728]
  AUTHORS   Bertero MG, Rothery RA, Boroumand N, Palak M, Blasco F, Ginet N, Weiner JH, Strynadka NC
  TITLE     Structural and biochemical characterization of a quinol binding site of Escherichia coli nitrate reductase A.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 280 (2005) 14836-43.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:7747940]
  AUTHORS   Bonnefoy V, Demoss JA
  TITLE     Nitrate reductases in Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   Antonie. Van. Leeuwenhoek. 66 (1994) 47-56.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:1321049]
  AUTHORS   Guigliarelli B, Asso M, More C, Augier V, Blasco F, Pommier J, Giordano G, Bertrand P
  TITLE     EPR and redox characterization of iron-sulfur centers in nitrate reductases A and Z from Escherichia coli. Evidence for a high-potential and a low-potential class  and their relevance in the electron-transfer mechanism.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 207 (1992) 61-8.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:2139607]
  AUTHORS   Iobbi-Nivol C, Santini CL, Blasco F, Giordano G
  TITLE     Purification and further characterization of the second nitrate reductase of Escherichia coli K12.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 188 (1990) 679-87.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.7.5.1
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.7.5.1
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.7.5.1
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.7.5.1
///
