ENTRY       EC 1.7.3.6                  Enzyme
NAME        hydroxylamine oxidase (cytochrome);
            HAO (ambiguous);
            hydroxylamine oxidoreductase (ambiguous);
            hydroxylamine oxidase (misleading)
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on other nitrogenous compounds as donors;
            With oxygen as acceptor
SYSNAME     hydroxylamine:oxygen oxidoreductase
REACTION    hydroxylamine + O2 + ferricytochrome c = nitrite + H2O + ferrocytochrome c + H+ [RN:R10230]
ALL_REAC    R10230
SUBSTRATE   hydroxylamine [CPD:C00192];
            O2 [CPD:C00007];
            ferricytochrome c [CPD:C00125]
PRODUCT     nitrite [CPD:C00088];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            ferrocytochrome c [CPD:C00126];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     The enzyme from the heterotrophic nitrifying bacterium Paracoccus denitrificans contains three to five non-heme, non-iron-sulfur iron atoms and interacts with cytochrome c556 and pseudoazurin [2,3].
HISTORY     EC 1.7.3.6 created 1972 as EC 1.7.3.4, part transferred 2013 to EC 1.7.3.6
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Kurokawa, M, Fukumori, Y and Yamanaka, T
  TITLE     A hydroxylamine - cytochrome c reductase occurs in the heterotrophic nitrifier Arthrobacter globiformis.
  JOURNAL   Plant Cell Physiol 26 (1985) 1439-1442.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8253206]
  AUTHORS   Wehrfritz JM, Reilly A, Spiro S, Richardson DJ
  TITLE     Purification of hydroxylamine oxidase from Thiosphaera pantotropha. Identification of electron acceptors that couple heterotrophic nitrification to aerobic denitrification.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 335 (1993) 246-50.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8920986]
  AUTHORS   Moir JW, Wehrfritz JM, Spiro S, Richardson DJ
  TITLE     The biochemical characterization of a novel non-haem-iron hydroxylamine oxidase from Paracoccus denitrificans GB17.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 319 ( Pt 3) (1996) 823-7.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9082922]
  AUTHORS   Wehrfritz J, Carter JP, Spiro S, Richardson DJ
  TITLE     Hydroxylamine oxidation in heterotrophic nitrate-reducing soil bacteria and purification of a hydroxylamine-cytochrome c oxidoreductase from a Pseudomonas species.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Microbiol. 166 (1996) 421-4.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.7.3.6
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.7.3.6
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.7.3.6
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.7.3.6
            CAS: 9075-43-8
///
