ENTRY       EC 1.8.5.4                  Enzyme
NAME        sulfide:quinone reductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Acting on a sulfur group of donors;
            With a quinone or similar compound as acceptor
SYSNAME     sulfide:quinone oxidoreductase
REACTION    n HS- + n quinone = polysulfide + n quinol
SUBSTRATE   HS-;
            quinone [CPD:C00472]
PRODUCT     polysulfide [CPD:C19692];
            quinol [CPD:C00530]
COMMENT     Contains FAD. Ubiquinone, plastoquinone or menaquinone can act as acceptor in different species. This enzyme catalyses the formation of sulfur globules. It is also an important step in anoxygenic bacterial photosynthesis.
HISTORY     EC 1.8.5.4 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8119908]
  AUTHORS   Arieli B, Shahak Y, Taglicht D, Hauska G, Padan E
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of sulfide-quinone reductase, a novel enzyme driving anoxygenic photosynthesis in Oscillatoria limnetica.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 269 (1994) 5705-11.
  ORGANISM  Oscillatoria limnetica
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9639604]
  AUTHORS   Reinartz M, Tschape J, Bruser T, Truper HG, Dahl C
  TITLE     Sulfide oxidation in the phototrophic sulfur bacterium Chromatium vinosum.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Microbiol. 170 (1998) 59-68.
  ORGANISM  Oscillatoria limnetica
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10816041]
  AUTHORS   Nubel T, Klughammer C, Huber R, Hauska G, Schutz M
  TITLE     Sulfide:quinone oxidoreductase in membranes of the hyperthermophilic bacterium Aquifex aeolicus (VF5).
  JOURNAL   Arch. Microbiol. 173 (2000) 233-44.
  ORGANISM  Aquifex aeolicus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:19438211]
  AUTHORS   Brito JA, Sousa FL, Stelter M, Bandeiras TM, Vonrhein C, Teixeira M, Pereira MM, Archer M
  TITLE     Structural and functional insights into sulfide:quinone oxidoreductase.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 48 (2009) 5613-22.
  ORGANISM  Acidianus ambivalens
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:20303979]
  AUTHORS   Cherney MM, Zhang Y, Solomonson M, Weiner JH, James MN
  TITLE     Crystal structure of sulfide:quinone oxidoreductase from Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans: insights into sulfidotrophic respiration and detoxification.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 398 (2010) 292-305.
  ORGANISM  Acidithiobacillus ferrooxidans
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:20691146]
  AUTHORS   Marcia M, Langer JD, Parcej D, Vogel V, Peng G, Michel H
  TITLE     Characterizing a monotopic membrane enzyme. Biochemical, enzymatic and crystallization studies on Aquifex aeolicus sulfide:quinone oxidoreductase.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1798 (2010) 2114-23.
  ORGANISM  Aquifex aeolicus
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.8.5.4
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.8.5.4
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.8.5.4
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.8.5.4
///
