ENTRY       EC 1.97.1.8                 Enzyme
NAME        tetrachloroethene reductive dehalogenase;
            tetrachloroethene reductase
CLASS       Oxidoreductases;
            Other oxidoreductases;
            Sole sub-subclass for oxidoreductases that do not belong in the other subclasses
SYSNAME     acceptor:trichloroethene oxidoreductase (chlorinating)
REACTION    trichloroethene + chloride + acceptor = tetrachloroethene + reduced acceptor [RN:R05753]
ALL_REAC    R05753;
            (other) R05499 R05500 R05501
SUBSTRATE   trichloroethene [CPD:C06790];
            chloride [CPD:C00698];
            acceptor [CPD:C00028]
PRODUCT     tetrachloroethene [CPD:C06789];
            reduced acceptor [CPD:C00030]
COMMENT     This enzyme allows the common pollutant tetrachloroethene to support bacterial growth and is responsible for disposal of a number of chlorinated hydrocarbons by this organism. The reaction occurs in the reverse direction. The enzyme also reduces trichloroethene to dichloroethene. Although the physiological reductant is unknown, the supply of reductant in some organisms is via reduced menaquinone, itself formed from molecular hydrogen, via EC 1.12.5.1 (hydrogen:quinone oxidoreductase). The enzyme contains a corrinoid and two iron-sulfur clusters. Methyl viologen can act as electron donor.
HISTORY     EC 1.97.1.8 created 2001
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Holliger, C, Wohlfarth, G. and Diekert, G.
  TITLE     Reductive dechlorination in the energy metabolism of anaerobic bacteria.
  JOURNAL   FEMS Microbiol. Rev. 22 (1998) 383-398.
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Glod, G., Angst, W., Holliger, C. and Schwarzenbach, R.P.
  TITLE     Corrinoid-mediated reduction of tetrachloroethene, trichloroethene, and trichlorofluoroethene in homogeneous aqueous solution: Reaction kinetics and reaction mechanisms.
  JOURNAL   Environ. Sci. Technol. 31 (1997) 253-260.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8663199]
  AUTHORS   Neumann A, Wohlfarth G, Diekert G.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of tetrachloroethene reductive dehalogenase from Dehalospirillum multivorans.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 271 (1996) 16515-9.
  ORGANISM  Dehalospirillum multivorans
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9224702]
  AUTHORS   Schumacher W, Holliger C, Zehnder AJ, Hagen WR.
  TITLE     Redox chemistry of cobalamin and iron-sulfur cofactors in the tetrachloroethene reductase of Dehalobacter restrictus.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 409 (1997) 421-5.
  ORGANISM  Dehalobacter restrictus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:8636034]
  AUTHORS   Schumacher W, Holliger C.
  TITLE     The proton/electron ration of the menaquinone-dependent electron transport from dihydrogen to tetrachloroethene in &quot;Dehalobacter restrictus&quot;.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 178 (1996) 2328-33.
  ORGANISM  Dehalobacter restrictus
PATHWAY     ec00625  Chloroalkane and chloroalkene degradation
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01120  Microbial metabolism in diverse environments
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 1.97.1.8
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 1.97.1.8
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 1.97.1.8
            UM-BBD (Biocatalysis/Biodegradation Database): 1.97.1.8
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 1.97.1.8
            CAS: 163913-51-7
///
