ENTRY       EC 2.1.1.179                Enzyme
NAME        16S rRNA (guanine1405-N7)-methyltransferase;
            methyltransferase Sgm;
            m7G1405 Mtase;
            Sgm Mtase;
            Sgm;
            sisomicin-gentamicin methyltransferase;
            sisomicin-gentamicin methylase;
            GrmA;
            RmtB;
            RmtC;
            ArmA
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring one-carbon groups;
            Methyltransferases
SYSNAME     S-adenosyl-L-methionine:16S rRNA (guanine1405-N7)-methyltransferase
REACTION    S-adenosyl-L-methionine + guanine1405 in 16S rRNA = S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine + 7-methylguanine1405 in 16S rRNA
SUBSTRATE   S-adenosyl-L-methionine [CPD:C00019];
            guanine1405 in 16S rRNA
PRODUCT     S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine [CPD:C00021];
            7-methylguanine1405 in 16S rRNA
COMMENT     The enzyme specifically methylates guanine1405 at N7 in 16S rRNA. The enzyme from the antibiotic-producing bacterium Micromonospora zionensis methylates guanine1405 in 16S rRNA to 7-methylguanine, thereby rendering the ribosome resistant to 4,6-disubstituted deoxystreptamine aminoglycosides, which include gentamicins and kanamycins [2].
HISTORY     EC 2.1.1.179 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:20194115]
  AUTHORS   Husain N, Tkaczuk KL, Tulsidas SR, Kaminska KH, Cubrilo S, Maravic-Vlahovicek G, Bujnicki JM, Sivaraman J
  TITLE     Structural basis for the methylation of G1405 in 16S rRNA by aminoglycoside resistance methyltransferase Sgm from an antibiotic producer: a diversity of active sites in m7G methyltransferases.
  JOURNAL   Nucleic. Acids. Res. 38 (2010) 4120-32.
  ORGANISM  Micromonospora zionensis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q7M0R2]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:19589804]
  AUTHORS   Savic M, Lovric J, Tomic TI, Vasiljevic B, Conn GL
  TITLE     Determination of the target nucleosides for members of two families of 16S rRNA methyltransferases that confer resistance to partially overlapping groups of aminoglycoside antibiotics.
  JOURNAL   Nucleic. Acids. Res. 37 (2009) 5420-31.
  ORGANISM  Micromonospora zionensis, Micromonospora echinospora
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q7M0R2 P24618]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:18930134]
  AUTHORS   Tomic TI, Moric I, Conn GL, Vasiljevic B
  TITLE     Aminoglycoside resistance genes sgm and kgmB protect bacterial but not yeast small ribosomal subunits in vitro despite high conservation of the rRNA A-site.
  JOURNAL   Res. Microbiol. 159 (2008) 658-62.
  ORGANISM  Micromonospora zionensis
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:18586937]
  AUTHORS   Savic M, Ilic-Tomic T, Macmaster R, Vasiljevic B, Conn GL
  TITLE     Critical residues for cofactor binding and catalytic activity in the aminoglycoside resistance methyltransferase Sgm.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 190 (2008) 5855-61.
  ORGANISM  Micromonospora zionensis
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:18343347]
  AUTHORS   Maravic Vlahovicek G, Cubrilo S, Tkaczuk KL, Bujnicki JM
  TITLE     Modeling and experimental analyses reveal a two-domain structure and amino acids  important for the activity of aminoglycoside resistance methyltransferase Sgm.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1784 (2008) 582-90.
  ORGANISM  Micromonospora zionensis
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:1447159]
  AUTHORS   Kojic M, Topisirovic L, Vasiljevic B
  TITLE     Cloning and characterization of an aminoglycoside resistance determinant from Micromonospora zionensis.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 174 (1992) 7868-72.
  ORGANISM  Micromonospora zionensis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q7M0R2]
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:19303884]
  AUTHORS   Schmitt E, Galimand M, Panvert M, Courvalin P, Mechulam Y
  TITLE     Structural bases for 16 S rRNA methylation catalyzed by ArmA and RmtB methyltransferases.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 388 (2009) 570-82.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:20722735]
  AUTHORS   Wachino J, Shibayama K, Kimura K, Yamane K, Suzuki S, Arakawa Y
  TITLE     RmtC introduces G1405 methylation in 16S rRNA and confers high-level aminoglycoside resistance on Gram-positive microorganisms.
  JOURNAL   FEMS. Microbiol. Lett. 311 (2010) 56-60.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli, Bacillus subtilis, Staphylococcus aureu
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:16626740]
  AUTHORS   Liou GF, Yoshizawa S, Courvalin P, Galimand M
  TITLE     Aminoglycoside resistance by ArmA-mediated ribosomal 16S methylation in human bacterial pathogens.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 359 (2006) 358-64.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.1.1.179
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.1.1.179
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.1.1.179
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.1.1.179
///
