ENTRY       EC 2.1.1.273                Enzyme
NAME        benzoate O-methyltransferase;
            BAMT;
            S-adenosyl-L-methionine:benzoic acid carboxyl methyltransferase
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring one-carbon groups;
            Methyltransferases
SYSNAME     S-adenosyl-L-methionine:benzoate O-methyltransferase
REACTION    S-adenosyl-L-methionine + benzoate = S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine + methyl benzoate [RN:R10447]
ALL_REAC    R10447
SUBSTRATE   S-adenosyl-L-methionine [CPD:C00019];
            benzoate [CPD:C00180]
PRODUCT     S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine [CPD:C00021];
            methyl benzoate [CPD:C20645]
COMMENT     While the enzyme from the plant Zea mays is specific for benzoate [6], the enzymes from Arabidopsis species and Clarkia breweri also catalyse the reaction of EC 2.1.1.274, salicylate 1-O-methyltransferase [1,5]. In snapdragon (Antirrhinum majus) two isoforms are found, one specific for benzoate [2,3] and one that is also active towards salicylate [4]. The volatile product is an important scent compound in some flowering species [2].
HISTORY     EC 2.1.1.273 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10375393]
  AUTHORS   Ross JR, Nam KH, D'Auria JC, Pichersky E
  TITLE     S-Adenosyl-L-methionine:salicylic acid carboxyl methyltransferase, an enzyme involved in floral scent production and plant defense, represents a new class of  plant methyltransferases.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 367 (1999) 9-16.
  ORGANISM  Clarkia breweri
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9SPV4]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:10852939]
  AUTHORS   Dudareva N, Murfitt LM, Mann CJ, Gorenstein N, Kolosova N, Kish CM, Bonham C, Wood K
  TITLE     Developmental regulation of methyl benzoate biosynthesis and emission in snapdragon flowers.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Cell. 12 (2000) 949-61.
  ORGANISM  Antirrhinum majus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9FYZ9]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11051108]
  AUTHORS   Murfitt LM, Kolosova N, Mann CJ, Dudareva N
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of S-adenosyl-L-methionine:benzoic acid carboxyl methyltransferase, the enzyme responsible for biosynthesis of the volatile ester methyl benzoate in flowers of Antirrhinum majus.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 382 (2000) 145-51.
  ORGANISM  Antirrhinum majus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12361714]
  AUTHORS   Negre F, Kolosova N, Knoll J, Kish CM, Dudareva N
  TITLE     Novel S-adenosyl-L-methionine:salicylic acid carboxyl methyltransferase, an enzyme responsible for biosynthesis of methyl salicylate and methyl benzoate, is  not involved in floral scent production in snapdragon flowers.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 406 (2002) 261-70.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana, Clarkia breweri
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:14617060]
  AUTHORS   Chen F, D'Auria JC, Tholl D, Ross JR, Gershenzon J, Noel JP, Pichersky E
  TITLE     An Arabidopsis thaliana gene for methylsalicylate biosynthesis, identified by a biochemical genomics approach, has a role in defense.
  JOURNAL   Plant. J. 36 (2003) 577-88.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana
  SEQUENCE  [ath:AT3G11480]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:20519632]
  AUTHORS   Kollner TG, Lenk C, Zhao N, Seidl-Adams I, Gershenzon J, Chen F, Degenhardt J
  TITLE     Herbivore-induced SABATH methyltransferases of maize that methylate anthranilic acid using s-adenosyl-L-methionine.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 153 (2010) 1795-807.
  ORGANISM  Zea mays
  SEQUENCE  [zma:100500709]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.1.1.273
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.1.1.273
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.1.1.273
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.1.1.273
///
