ENTRY       EC 2.1.1.224                Enzyme
NAME        23S rRNA (adenine2503-C8)-methyltransferase;
            Cfr (gene name)
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring one-carbon groups;
            Methyltransferases
SYSNAME     S-adenosyl-L-methionine:23S rRNA (adenine2503-C8)-methyltransferase
REACTION    2 S-adenosyl-L-methionine + adenine2503 in 23S rRNA = S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine + L-methionine + 5'-deoxyadenosine + 8-methyladenine2503 in 23S rRNA
SUBSTRATE   S-adenosyl-L-methionine [CPD:C00019];
            adenine2503 in 23S rRNA
PRODUCT     S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine [CPD:C00021];
            L-methionine [CPD:C00073];
            5'-deoxyadenosine [CPD:C05198];
            8-methyladenine2503 in 23S rRNA
COMMENT     This enzyme is a member of the 'AdoMet radical' (radical SAM) family. S-Adenosyl-L-methionine acts as both a radical generator and as the source of the appended methyl group. It contains an [4Fe-S] cluster [1]. Cfr is an plasmid-acquired methyltransferase that protects cells from the action of antibiotics [1]. The enzyme methylates adenosine at position 2503 of 23S rRNA by a radical mechanism, transferring a CH2 group from S-adenosyl-L-methionine while retaining the hydrogen at the C-8 position of the adenine. It will also methylate 2-methyladenine produced by the action of EC 2.1.1.192 [23S rRNA (adenine2503-C2)-methyltransferase].
HISTORY     EC 2.1.1.224 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:19144912]
  AUTHORS   Giessing AM, Jensen SS, Rasmussen A, Hansen LH, Gondela A, Long K, Vester B, Kirpekar F
  TITLE     Identification of 8-methyladenosine as the modification catalyzed by the radical  SAM methyltransferase Cfr that confers antibiotic resistance in bacteria.
  JOURNAL   RNA. 15 (2009) 327-36.
  ORGANISM  Staphylococcus sciuri
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9FBG4]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:20007606]
  AUTHORS   Kaminska KH, Purta E, Hansen LH, Bujnicki JM, Vester B, Long KS
  TITLE     Insights into the structure, function and evolution of the radical-SAM 23S rRNA methyltransferase Cfr that confers antibiotic resistance in bacteria.
  JOURNAL   Nucleic. Acids. Res. 38 (2010) 1652-63.
  ORGANISM  Staphylococcus aureus
  SEQUENCE  [up:A5HBL2]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:20184321]
  AUTHORS   Yan F, LaMarre JM, Rohrich R, Wiesner J, Jomaa H, Mankin AS, Fujimori DG
  TITLE     RlmN and Cfr are radical SAM enzymes involved in methylation of ribosomal RNA.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 132 (2010) 3953-64.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:21368151]
  AUTHORS   Yan F, Fujimori DG
  TITLE     RNA methylation by radical SAM enzymes RlmN and Cfr proceeds via methylene transfer and hydride shift.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 108 (2011) 3930-4.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:21415317]
  AUTHORS   Grove TL, Benner JS, Radle MI, Ahlum JH, Landgraf BJ, Krebs C, Booker SJ
  TITLE     A radically different mechanism for S-adenosylmethionine-dependent methyltransferases.
  JOURNAL   Science. 332 (2011) 604-7.
  ORGANISM  Staphylococcus aureus
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:21527678]
  AUTHORS   Boal AK, Grove TL, McLaughlin MI, Yennawar NH, Booker SJ, Rosenzweig AC
  TITLE     Structural basis for methyl transfer by a radical SAM enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Science. 332 (2011) 1089-92.
ORTHOLOGY   K15632  23S rRNA (adenine2503-C8)-methyltransferase
GENES       PFA: PF14_0066
            PFD: PFDG_02279
            PFH: PFHG_00454
            PYO: PY01072
            PCB: PC301328.00.0
            PBE: PB000978.02.0
            PKN: PKH_134000
            PVX: PVX_086085
            PCY: PCYB_134950
            TAN: TA09930
            TPV: TP04_0797
            BBO: BBOV_III008940(17.m07780)
            BEQ: BEWA_010600
            TGO: TGME49_052460
            BAO: BAMF_0476(RBAM_005660)
            BAY: RBAM_005660
            BCL: ABC1074
            BBE: BBR47_45040
            GYM: GYMC10_3402
            CBO: CBO2857(cfr)
            CBA: CLB_2801
            CBH: CLC_2734
            CBY: CLM_3236
            CBL: CLK_2251
            CBB: CLD_1710
            CBI: CLJ_B3097
            CBF: CLI_2911
            CPY: Cphy_2221
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.1.1.224
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.1.1.224
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.1.1.224
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.1.1.224
///
