ENTRY       EC 2.1.1.297                Enzyme
NAME        peptide chain release factor N5-glutamine methyltransferase;
            N5-glutamine S-adenosyl-L-methionine dependent methyltransferase;
            N5-glutamine MTase;
            HemK;
            PrmC
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring one-carbon groups;
            Methyltransferases
SYSNAME     S-adenosyl-L-methionine:[peptide chain release factor 1 or 2]-L-glutamine (N5-glutamine)-methyltransferase
REACTION    S-adenosyl-L-methionine + [peptide chain release factor 1 or 2]-L-glutamine = S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine + [peptide chain release factor 1 or 2]-N5-methyl-L-glutamine
SUBSTRATE   S-adenosyl-L-methionine [CPD:C00019];
            [peptide chain release factor 1]-L-glutamine;
            [peptide chain release factor 2]-L-glutamine
PRODUCT     S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine [CPD:C00021];
            [peptide chain release factor 1]-N5-methyl-L-glutamine;
            [peptide chain release factor 2]-N5-methyl-L-glutamine
COMMENT     Modifies the glutamine residue in the universally conserved glycylglycylglutamine (GGQ) motif of peptide chain release factor, resulting in almost complete loss of release activity.
HISTORY     EC 2.1.1.297 created 2014
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:11805295]
  AUTHORS   Nakahigashi K, Kubo N, Narita S, Shimaoka T, Goto S, Oshima T, Mori H, Maeda M, Wada C, Inokuchi H
  TITLE     HemK, a class of protein methyl transferase with similarity to DNA methyl transferases, methylates polypeptide chain release factors, and hemK knockout induces defects in translational termination.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 99 (2002) 1473-8.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b1212]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:11847124]
  AUTHORS   Heurgue-Hamard V, Champ S, Engstrom A, Ehrenberg M, Buckingham RH
  TITLE     The hemK gene in Escherichia coli encodes the N(5)-glutamine methyltransferase that modifies peptide release factors.
  JOURNAL   EMBO. J. 21 (2002) 769-78.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b1212]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:12741815]
  AUTHORS   Schubert HL, Phillips JD, Hill CP
  TITLE     Structures along the catalytic pathway of PrmC/HemK, an N5-glutamine AdoMet-dependent methyltransferase.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 42 (2003) 5592-9.
  ORGANISM  Thermotoga maritima
  SEQUENCE  [tma:TM0488]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:14651272]
  AUTHORS   Yoon HJ, Kang KY, Ahn HJ, Shim SM, Ha JY, Lee SK, Mikami B, Suh SW
  TITLE     X-ray crystallographic studies of HemK from Thermotoga maritima, an N5-glutamine  methyltransferase.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Cells. 16 (2003) 266-9.
  ORGANISM  Thermotoga maritima
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15223314]
  AUTHORS   Yang Z, Shipman L, Zhang M, Anton BP, Roberts RJ, Cheng X
  TITLE     Structural characterization and comparative phylogenetic analysis of Escherichia  coli HemK, a protein (N5)-glutamine methyltransferase.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 340 (2004) 695-706.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b1212]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:15629922]
  AUTHORS   Pannekoek Y, Heurgue-Hamard V, Langerak AA, Speijer D, Buckingham RH, van der Ende A
  TITLE     The N5-glutamine S-adenosyl-L-methionine-dependent methyltransferase PrmC/HemK in Chlamydia trachomatis methylates class 1 release factors.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 187 (2005) 507-11.
  ORGANISM  Chlamydia trachomatis
  SEQUENCE  [ctb:CTL0279]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.1.1.297
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.1.1.297
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.1.1.297
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.1.1.297
///
