ENTRY       EC 2.1.1.188                Enzyme
NAME        23S rRNA (guanine748-N1)-methyltransferase;
            Rlma(II);
            Rlma2;
            23S rRNA m1G748 methyltransferase;
            RlmaII;
            Rlma II;
            tylosin-resistance methyltransferase RlmA(II);
            TlrB;
            rRNA large subunit methyltransferase II
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring one-carbon groups;
            Methyltransferases
SYSNAME     S-adenosyl-L-methionine:23S rRNA (guanine748-N1)-methyltransferase
REACTION    S-adenosyl-L-methionine + guanine748 in 23S rRNA = S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine + N1-methylguanine748 in 23S rRNA [RN:R07233]
ALL_REAC    R07233
SUBSTRATE   S-adenosyl-L-methionine [CPD:C00019];
            guanine748 in 23S rRNA
PRODUCT     S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine [CPD:C00021];
            N1-methylguanine748 in 23S rRNA
COMMENT     The enzyme specifically methylates guanine748 at N1 in 23S rRNA. The methyltransferase RlmAII confers resistance to the macrolide antibiotic tylosin in the drug-producing strain Streptomyces fradiae [1].
HISTORY     EC 2.1.1.188 created 1976 as EC 2.1.1.51, part transferred 2010 to EC 2.1.1.188
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:15046978]
  AUTHORS   Douthwaite S, Crain PF, Liu M, Poehlsgaard J
  TITLE     The tylosin-resistance methyltransferase RlmA(II) (TlrB) modifies the N-1 position of 23S rRNA nucleotide G748.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 337 (2004) 1073-7.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces fradiae
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9S1M6]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:10972803]
  AUTHORS   Liu M, Kirpekar F, Van Wezel GP, Douthwaite S
  TITLE     The tylosin resistance gene tlrB of Streptomyces fradiae encodes a methyltransferase that targets G748 in 23S rRNA.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 37 (2000) 811-20.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces fradiae
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9S1M6]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:12514124]
  AUTHORS   Lebars I, Yoshizawa S, Stenholm AR, Guittet E, Douthwaite S, Fourmy D
  TITLE     Structure of 23S rRNA hairpin 35 and its interaction with the tylosin-resistance  methyltransferase RlmAII.
  JOURNAL   EMBO. J. 22 (2003) 183-92.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:17673230]
  AUTHORS   Lebars I, Husson C, Yoshizawa S, Douthwaite S, Fourmy D
  TITLE     Recognition elements in rRNA for the tylosin resistance methyltransferase RlmA(II).
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 372 (2007) 525-34.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:18406425]
  AUTHORS   Douthwaite S, Jakobsen L, Yoshizawa S, Fourmy D
  TITLE     Interaction of the tylosin-resistance methyltransferase RlmA II at its rRNA target differs from the orthologue RlmA I.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 378 (2008) 969-75.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:11967079]
  AUTHORS   Liu M, Douthwaite S
  TITLE     Methylation at nucleotide G745 or G748 in 23S rRNA distinguishes Gram-negative from Gram-positive bacteria.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 44 (2002) 195-204.
ORTHOLOGY   K14336  23S rRNA (guanine748-N1)-methyltransferase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.1.1.188
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.1.1.188
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.1.1.188
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.1.1.188
///
