ENTRY       EC 2.3.1.190                Enzyme
NAME        acetoin dehydrogenase;
            acetoin dehydrogenase complex;
            acetoin dehydrogenase enzyme system;
            AoDH ES
CLASS       Transferases;
            Acyltransferases;
            Transferring groups other than aminoacyl groups
SYSNAME     acetyl-CoA:acetoin O-acetyltransferase
REACTION    acetoin + CoA + NAD+ = acetaldehyde + acetyl-CoA + NADH + H+ [RN:R09524]
ALL_REAC    R09524
SUBSTRATE   acetoin [CPD:C00466];
            CoA [CPD:C00010];
            NAD+ [CPD:C00003]
PRODUCT     acetaldehyde [CPD:C00084];
            acetyl-CoA [CPD:C00024];
            NADH [CPD:C00004];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
COMMENT     Requires thiamine diphosphate. This enzyme, which belongs to the family of 2-oxo acid dehydrogenase complexes, catalyses the oxidative-hydrolytic cleavage of acetoin to acetaldehyde and acetyl-CoA in many bacterial strains, both aerobic and anaerobic. The enzyme is composed of multiple copies of three enzymic components: acetoin oxidoreductase (E1), dihydrolipoamide acetyltransferase (E2) and dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase (E3).
HISTORY     EC 2.3.1.190 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:2061286]
  AUTHORS   Priefert H, Hein S, Kruger N, Zeh K, Schmidt B, Steinbuchel A
  TITLE     Identification and molecular characterization of the Alcaligenes eutrophus H16 aco operon genes involved in acetoin catabolism.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 173 (1991) 4056-71.
  ORGANISM  Alcaligenes eutrophus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8110297]
  AUTHORS   Oppermann FB, Steinbuchel A
  TITLE     Identification and molecular characterization of the aco genes encoding the Pelobacter carbinolicus acetoin dehydrogenase enzyme system.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 176 (1994) 469-85.
  ORGANISM  Pelobacter carbinolicus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8206840]
  AUTHORS   Kruger N, Oppermann FB, Lorenzl H, Steinbuchel A
  TITLE     Biochemical and molecular characterization of the Clostridium magnum acetoin dehydrogenase enzyme system.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 176 (1994) 3614-30.
  ORGANISM  Clostridium magnu
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:7813883]
  AUTHORS   Huang M, Oppermann FB, Steinbuchel A
  TITLE     Molecular characterization of the Pseudomonas putida 2,3-butanediol catabolic pathway.
  JOURNAL   FEMS. Microbiol. Lett. 124 (1994) 141-50.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas putida
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:10368162]
  AUTHORS   Huang M, Oppermann-Sanio FB, Steinbuchel A
  TITLE     Biochemical and molecular characterization of the Bacillus subtilis acetoin catabolic pathway.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 181 (1999) 3837-41.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus subtilis
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.3.1.190
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.3.1.190
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.3.1.190
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.3.1.190
///
