ENTRY       EC 2.3.1.175                Enzyme
NAME        deacetylcephalosporin-C acetyltransferase;
            acetyl-CoA:deacetylcephalosporin-C acetyltransferase;
            DAC acetyltransferase;
            cefG;
            deacetylcephalosporin C acetyltransferase;
            acetyl coenzyme A:DAC acetyltransferase;
            acetyl-CoA:DAC acetyltransferase;
            CPC acetylhydrolase;
            acetyl-CoA:DAC O-acetyltransferase;
            DAC-AT
CLASS       Transferases;
            Acyltransferases;
            Transferring groups other than aminoacyl groups
SYSNAME     acetyl-CoA:deacetylcephalosporin-C O-acetyltransferase
REACTION    acetyl-CoA + deacetylcephalosporin C = CoA + cephalosporin C [RN:R03064]
ALL_REAC    R03064
SUBSTRATE   acetyl-CoA [CPD:C00024];
            deacetylcephalosporin C [CPD:C03112]
PRODUCT     CoA [CPD:C00010];
            cephalosporin C [CPD:C00916]
COMMENT     This enzyme catalyses the final step in the biosynthesis of cephalosporin C.
HISTORY     EC 2.3.1.175 created 2005
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1368946]
  AUTHORS   Matsuyama K, Matsumoto H, Matsuda A, Sugiura H, Komatsu K, Ichikawa S.
  TITLE     Purification of acetyl coenzyme A: deacetylacephalosporin C O-acetyltransferase from Acremonium chrysogenum.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 56 (1992) 1410-2.
  ORGANISM  Acremonium chrysogenum
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:1569032]
  AUTHORS   Gutierrez S, Velasco J, Fernandez FJ, Martin JF.
  TITLE     The cefG gene of Cephalosporium acremonium is linked to the cefEF gene and encodes a deacetylcephalosporin C acetyltransferase closely related to homoserine O-acetyltransferase.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 174 (1992) 3056-64.
  ORGANISM  Cephalosporium acremonium
  SEQUENCE  [up:P39058]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:1632779]
  AUTHORS   Matsuda A, Sugiura H, Matsuyama K, Matsumoto H, Ichikawa S, Komatsu K.
  TITLE     Cloning and disruption of the cefG gene encoding acetyl coenzyme A: deacetylcephalosporin C o-acetyltransferase from Acremonium chrysogenum.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 186 (1992) 40-6.
  ORGANISM  Acremonium chrysogenum
  SEQUENCE  [up:P39058]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9421924]
  AUTHORS   Gutierrez S, Velasco J, Marcos AT, Fernandez FJ, Fierro F, Barredo JL, Diez B, Martin JF.
  TITLE     Expression of the cefG gene is limiting for cephalosporin biosynthesis in Acremonium chrysogenum.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 48 (1997) 606-14.
  ORGANISM  Acremonium chrysogenum
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:9895280]
  AUTHORS   Velasco J, Gutierrez S, Campoy S, Martin JF.
  TITLE     Molecular characterization of the Acremonium chrysogenum cefG gene product: the native deacetylcephalosporin C acetyltransferase is not processed into subunits.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 337 ( Pt 3) (1999) 379-85.
  ORGANISM  Acremonium chrysogenum
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:7847890]
  AUTHORS   Martin JF, Gutierrez S, Fernandez FJ, Velasco J, Fierro F, Marcos AT, Kosalkova K.
  TITLE     Expression of genes and processing of enzymes for the biosynthesis of penicillins and cephalosporins.
  JOURNAL   Antonie. Van. Leeuwenhoek. 65 (1994) 227-43.
  ORGANISM  Acremonium chrysogenum
PATHWAY     ec00311  Penicillin and cephalosporin biosynthesis
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K12747  deacetylcephalosporin-C acetyltransferase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.3.1.175
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.3.1.175
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.3.1.175
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.3.1.175
            CAS: 57827-76-6
///
