ENTRY       EC 2.3.1.226                Enzyme
NAME        carboxymethylproline synthase;
            CarB (ambiguous)
CLASS       Transferases;
            Acyltransferases;
            Transferring groups other than aminoacyl groups
SYSNAME     malonyl-CoA:(S)-1-pyrroline-5-carboxylate malonyltransferase (cyclizing)
REACTION    malonyl-CoA + (S)-1-pyrroline-5-carboxylate + H2O = CoA + (2S,5S)-5-carboxymethylproline + CO2 [RN:R10485]
ALL_REAC    R10485
SUBSTRATE   malonyl-CoA [CPD:C00083];
            (S)-1-pyrroline-5-carboxylate [CPD:C03912];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     CoA [CPD:C00010];
            (2S,5S)-5-carboxymethylproline [CPD:C17366];
            CO2 [CPD:C00011]
COMMENT     The enzyme is involved in the biosynthesis of the carbapenem beta-lactam antibiotic (5R)-carbapen-2-em-3-carboxylate in the bacterium Pectobacterium carotovorum.
HISTORY     EC 2.3.1.226 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:14625287]
  AUTHORS   Sleeman MC, Schofield CJ
  TITLE     Carboxymethylproline synthase (CarB), an unusual carbon-carbon bond-forming enzyme of the crotonase superfamily involved in carbapenem biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 279 (2004) 6730-6.
  ORGANISM  Pectobacterium carotovorum
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:15595850]
  AUTHORS   Gerratana B, Arnett SO, Stapon A, Townsend CA
  TITLE     Carboxymethylproline synthase from Pectobacterium carotorova: a multifaceted member of the crotonase superfamily.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 43 (2004) 15936-45.
  ORGANISM  Pectobacterium carotovorum
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:15726176]
  AUTHORS   Sorensen JL, Sleeman MC, Schofield CJ
  TITLE     Synthesis of deuterium labelled L- and D-glutamate semialdehydes and their evaluation as substrates for carboxymethylproline synthase (CarB)--implications for carbapenem biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Chem. Commun. (Camb).  (2005) 1155-7.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16096274]
  AUTHORS   Sleeman MC, Sorensen JL, Batchelar ET, McDonough MA, Schofield CJ
  TITLE     Structural and mechanistic studies on carboxymethylproline synthase (CarB), a unique member of the crotonase superfamily catalyzing the first step in carbapenem biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 280 (2005) 34956-65.
  ORGANISM  Pectobacterium carotovorum
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:18972478]
  AUTHORS   Batchelar ET, Hamed RB, Ducho C, Claridge TD, Edelmann MJ, Kessler B, Schofield CJ
  TITLE     Thioester hydrolysis and C-C bond formation by carboxymethylproline synthase from the crotonase superfamily.
  JOURNAL   Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl. 47 (2008) 9322-5.
  ORGANISM  Pectobacterium carotovorum
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:21505494]
  AUTHORS   Hamed RB, Gomez-Castellanos JR, Thalhammer A, Harding D, Ducho C, Claridge TD, Schofield CJ
  TITLE     Stereoselective C-C bond formation catalysed by engineered carboxymethylproline synthases.
  JOURNAL   Nat. Chem. 3 (2011) 365-71.
  ORGANISM  Pectobacterium carotovorum
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.3.1.226
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.3.1.226
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.3.1.226
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.3.1.226
///
