ENTRY       EC 2.3.1.185                Enzyme
NAME        tropine acyltransferase;
            tropine:acyl-CoA transferase;
            acetyl-CoA:tropan-3-ol acyltransferase;
            tropine acetyltransferase;
            tropine tigloyltransferase;
            TAT
CLASS       Transferases;
            Acyltransferases;
            Transferring groups other than aminoacyl groups
SYSNAME     acyl-CoA:tropine O-acyltransferase
REACTION    an acyl-CoA + tropine = CoA + an O-acyltropine [RN:R08712]
ALL_REAC    R08712 > R06735
SUBSTRATE   acyl-CoA [CPD:C00040];
            tropine [CPD:C00729]
PRODUCT     CoA [CPD:C00010];
            O-acyltropine [CPD:C02089]
COMMENT     This enzyme exhibits absolute specificity for the endo/3alpha configuration found in tropine as pseudotropine (tropan-3beta-ol; see EC 2.3.1.186, pseudotropine acyltransferase) is not a substrate [3]. Acts on a wide range of aliphatic acyl-CoA derivatives, with tigloyl-CoA and acetyl-CoA being the best substrates. It is probably involved in the formation of the tropane alkaloid littorine, which is a precursor of hyoscyamine [4].
HISTORY     EC 2.3.1.185 created 2008
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1959620]
  AUTHORS   Robins RJ, Bachmann P, Robinson T, Rhodes MJ, Yamada Y.
  TITLE     The formation of 3 alpha- and 3 beta-acetoxytropanes by Datura stramonium transformed root cultures involves two acetyl-CoA-dependent acyltransferases.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 292 (1991) 293-7.
  ORGANISM  Datura stramonium
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Robins, R.J., Bachmann,P., Peerless, A.C.J. and Rabot, S.
  TITLE     Esterification reactions in the biosynthesis of tropane alkaloids in transformed root cultures.
  JOURNAL   Plant Cell, Tissue Organ Cult. 38 (1994) 241-247.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10626376]
  AUTHORS   Boswell HD, Drager B, McLauchlan WR, Portsteffen A, Robins DJ, Robins RJ, Walton NJ.
  TITLE     Specificities of the enzymes of N-alkyltropane biosynthesis in Brugmansia and Datura.
  JOURNAL   Phytochemistry. 52 (1999) 871-8.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16720272]
  AUTHORS   Li R, Reed DW, Liu E, Nowak J, Pelcher LE, Page JE, Covello PS.
  TITLE     Functional genomic analysis of alkaloid biosynthesis in Hyoscyamus niger reveals a cytochrome P450 involved in littorine rearrangement.
  JOURNAL   Chem. Biol. 13 (2006) 513-20.
  ORGANISM  Hyoscyamus niger
PATHWAY     ec00960  Tropane, piperidine and pyridine alkaloid biosynthesis
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.3.1.185
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.3.1.185
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.3.1.185
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.3.1.185
            CAS: 138440-79-6 162535-29-7
///
