ENTRY       EC 2.4.1.161                Enzyme
NAME        oligosaccharide 4-alpha-D-glucosyltransferase;
            amylase III;
            1,4-alpha-glucan:1,4-alpha-glucan 4-alpha-glucosyltransferase;
            1,4-alpha-D-glucan:1,4-alpha-D-glucan 4-alpha-D-glucosyltransferase;
            alpha-1,4-transglucosylase
CLASS       Transferases;
            Glycosyltransferases;
            Hexosyltransferases
SYSNAME     (1->4)-alpha-D-glucan:(1->4)-alpha-D-glucan 4-alpha-D-glucosyltransferase
REACTION    Transfers the non-reducing terminal alpha-D-glucose residue from a (1->4)-alpha-D-glucan to the 4-position of a free glucose or of a glucosyl residue at the non-reducing terminus of a (1->4)-alpha-D-glucan, thus bringing about the rearrangement of oligosaccharides
COMMENT     The enzyme acts on amylose, amylopectin, glycogen and maltooligosaccharides. No detectable free glucose is formed, indicating the enzyme does not act as a hydrolase. The enzyme from the bacterium Cellvibrio japonicus has the highest activity with maltotriose as a donor, and also accepts maltose [3], while the enzyme from amoeba does not accept maltose [1,2]. Oligosaccharides with 1->6 linkages cannot function as donors, but can act as acceptors [3]. Unlike EC 2.4.1.25, 4-alpha-glucanotransferase, this enzyme can transfer only a single glucosyl residue.
HISTORY     EC 2.4.1.161 created 1989, modified 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:2423097]
  AUTHORS   Nebinger P.
  TITLE     Separation and characterization of four different amylases of Entamoeba histolytica. I. Purification and properties.
  JOURNAL   Biol. Chem. Hoppe. Seyler. 367 (1986) 161-7.
  ORGANISM  Entamoeba histolytica
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:2423098]
  AUTHORS   Nebinger P.
  TITLE     Separation and characterization of four different amylases of Entamoeba histolytica. II. Characterization of amylases.
  JOURNAL   Biol. Chem. Hoppe. Seyler. 367 (1986) 169-76.
  ORGANISM  Entamoeba histolytica
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:23132856]
  AUTHORS   Larsbrink J, Izumi A, Hemsworth GR, Davies GJ, Brumer H
  TITLE     Structural enzymology of Cellvibrio japonicus Agd31B protein reveals alpha-transglucosylase activity in glycoside hydrolase family 31.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 287 (2012) 43288-99.
  ORGANISM  Cellvibrio japonicus
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.4.1.161
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.4.1.161
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.4.1.161
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.4.1.161
            CAS: 9000-92-4
///
