ENTRY       EC 2.4.1.266                Enzyme
NAME        glucosyl-3-phosphoglycerate synthase;
            GpgS protein;
            GPG synthase;
            glucosylphosphoglycerate synthase
CLASS       Transferases;
            Glycosyltransferases;
            Hexosyltransferases
SYSNAME     NDP-glucose:3-phospho-D-glycerate 2-alpha-D-glucosyltransferase
REACTION    NDP-glucose + 3-phospho-D-glycerate = NDP + 2-O-(alpha-D-glucopyranosyl)-3-phospho-D-glycerate [RN:R09663]
ALL_REAC    R09663
SUBSTRATE   NDP-glucose [CPD:C15541];
            3-phospho-D-glycerate [CPD:C00197]
PRODUCT     NDP [CPD:C00454];
            2-O-(alpha-D-glucopyranosyl)-3-phospho-D-glycerate [CPD:C19791]
COMMENT     The enzyme is involved in biosynthesis of 2-O-(alpha-D-glucopyranosyl)-D-glycerate via the two-step pathway in which glucosyl-3-phosphoglycerate synthase catalyses the conversion of GDP-glucose and 3-phospho-D-glycerate into 2-O-(alpha-D-glucopyranosyl)-3-phospho-D-glycerate, which is then converted to 2-O-(alpha-D-glucopyranosyl)-D-glycerate by EC 3.1.3.85 glucosyl-3-phosphoglycerate phosphatase. The activity is dependent on divalent cations (Mn2+, Co2+, or Mg2+). The enzyme from Persephonella marina shows moderate flexibility on the sugar donor concerning the nucleotide moiety (UDP-glucose, ADP-glucose, GDP-glucose) but is strictly specific for glucose. The enzyme is also strictly specific for 3-phospho-D-glycerate as acceptor [1]. The enzyme from Methanococcoides burtonii is strictly specific for GDP-glucose and 3-phospho-D-glycerate [2]. This enzyme catalyses the first glucosylation step in methylglucose lipopolysaccharide biosynthesis in mycobacteria [4,5].
HISTORY     EC 2.4.1.266 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:17189358]
  AUTHORS   Costa J, Empadinhas N, da Costa MS
  TITLE     Glucosylglycerate biosynthesis in the deepest lineage of the Bacteria: characterization of the thermophilic proteins GpgS and GpgP from Persephonella marina.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 189 (2007) 1648-54.
  ORGANISM  Persephonella marina
  SEQUENCE  [pmx:PERMA_1582]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16428406]
  AUTHORS   Costa J, Empadinhas N, Goncalves L, Lamosa P, Santos H, da Costa MS
  TITLE     Characterization of the biosynthetic pathway of glucosylglycerate in the archaeon Methanococcoides burtonii.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 188 (2006) 1022-30.
  ORGANISM  Methanococcoides burtonii
  SEQUENCE  [mbu:Mbur_0737]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:18221489]
  AUTHORS   Empadinhas N, Albuquerque L, Mendes V, Macedo-Ribeiro S, da Costa MS
  TITLE     Identification of the mycobacterial glucosyl-3-phosphoglycerate synthase.
  JOURNAL   FEMS. Microbiol. Lett. 280 (2008) 195-202.
  ORGANISM  Mycobacterium bovis, Mycobacterium smegmatis
  SEQUENCE  [mbo:Mb1240] [msm:MSMEG_5084]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:19015727]
  AUTHORS   Pereira PJ, Empadinhas N, Albuquerque L, Sa-Moura B, da Costa MS, Macedo-Ribeiro S
  TITLE     Mycobacterium tuberculosis glucosyl-3-phosphoglycerate synthase: structure of a key enzyme in methylglucose lipopolysaccharide biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   PLoS. One. 3 (2008) e3748.
  ORGANISM  Mycobacterium tuberculosis
  SEQUENCE  [mtu:Rv1208]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:19052364]
  AUTHORS   Gest P, Kaur D, Pham HT, van der Woerd M, Hansen E, Brennan PJ, Jackson M, Guerin ME
  TITLE     Preliminary crystallographic analysis of GpgS, a key glucosyltransferase involved in methylglucose lipopolysaccharide biosynthesis in Mycobacterium tuberculosis.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. Sect. F. Struct. Biol. Cryst. Commun. 64 (2008) 1121-4.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:19421329]
  AUTHORS   Kaur D, Pham H, Larrouy-Maumus G, Riviere M, Vissa V, Guerin ME, Puzo G, Brennan PJ, Jackson M
  TITLE     Initiation of methylglucose lipopolysaccharide biosynthesis in mycobacteria.
  JOURNAL   PLoS. One. 4 (2009) e5447.
  ORGANISM  Mycobacterium smegmatis
  SEQUENCE  [msm:MSMEG_5084]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.4.1.266
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.4.1.266
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.4.1.266
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.4.1.266
///
