ENTRY       EC 2.4.1.248                Enzyme
NAME        cycloisomaltooligosaccharide glucanotransferase
CLASS       Transferases;
            Glycosyltransferases;
            Hexosyltransferases
SYSNAME     (1->6)-alpha-D-glucan:(1->6)-alpha-D-glucan 6-alpha-D-[1->6alpha-D-glucano]-transferase (cyclizing)
REACTION    cyclizes part of a (1->6)-alpha-D-glucan chain by formation of a (1->6)-alpha-D-glucosidic bond
COMMENT     Specific for (1->6)-alpha-D-glucans (dextrans) and, unlike cyclomaltodextrin glucanotransferase (EC 2.4.1.19), without activity towards (1->4)-alpha-D-glucans, such as amylose. It also has no activity on oligosaccharides, such as amylopectin and pullulan, containing (1->6)-alpha-D-glucosidic linkages at branch points. The enzyme from Bacillus circulans T-3040 has been shown to form cycloisomalto-oligosaccharides of three sizes (7, 8 and 9 glucose units). It will also catalyse the disproportionation of two isomalto-oligosaccharides molecules to yield a series of isomalto-oligosachharides and the addition of D-glucose to cycloisomalto-oligosaccharides with ring opening to form isomalto-oligosaccharides.
HISTORY     EC 2.4.1.248 created 2009
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Oguma T, Horiuchi, T, and Kobayashi M.
  TITLE     Novel Cyclic dextrins, Cycloisomaltooligosaccharides, from Bacillus sp. T-3040 culture.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotech. Biochem. 57 (1993) 1225-1227.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7515357]
  AUTHORS   Oguma T, Tobe K, Kobayashi M
  TITLE     Purification and properties of a novel enzyme from Bacillus spp. T-3040, which catalyzes the conversion of dextran to cyclic isomaltooligosaccharides.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 345 (1994) 135-8.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus circulans
  SEQUENCE  [up:P94286]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16926507]
  AUTHORS   Yamamoto T, Terasawa K, Kim YM, Kimura A, Kitamura Y, Kobayashi M, Funane K
  TITLE     Identification of catalytic amino acids of cyclodextran glucanotransferase from Bacillus circulans T-3040.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 70 (2006) 1947-53.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus circulans
  SEQUENCE  [up:P94286]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.4.1.248
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.4.1.248
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.4.1.248
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.4.1.248
///
