ENTRY       EC 2.5.1.104                Enzyme
NAME        N1-aminopropylagmatine synthase;
            agmatine/cadaverine aminopropyl transferase;
            ACAPT;
            PF0127 (gene name);
            triamine/agmatine aminopropyltransferase;
            SpeE;
            agmatine aminopropyltransferase
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     S-adenosyl 3-(methylthio)propylamine:agmatine 3-aminopropyltransferase
REACTION    S-adenosyl 3-(methylthio)propylamine + agmatine = S-methyl-5'-thioadenosine + N1-(3-aminopropyl)agmatine [RN:R10338]
ALL_REAC    R10338
SUBSTRATE   S-adenosyl 3-(methylthio)propylamine [CPD:C01137];
            agmatine [CPD:C00179]
PRODUCT     S-methyl-5'-thioadenosine [CPD:C00170];
            N1-(3-aminopropyl)agmatine [CPD:C20560]
COMMENT     The enzyme is involved in the biosynthesis of spermidine from agmatine in some archaea and bacteria. The enzyme from the Gram-negative bacterium Thermus thermophilus accepts agmatine, spermidine and norspermidine with similar catalytic efficiency. The enzymes from the archaea Pyrococcus furiosus and Thermococcus kodakarensis prefer agmatine, but can utilize cadaverine, putrescine and propane-1,3-diamine with much lower catalytic efficiency. cf. EC 2.5.1.16, spermidine synthase, and EC 2.5.1.23, sym-norspermidine synthase.
HISTORY     EC 2.5.1.104 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:15983049]
  AUTHORS   Ohnuma M, Terui Y, Tamakoshi M, Mitome H, Niitsu M, Samejima K, Kawashima E, Oshima T
  TITLE     N1-aminopropylagmatine, a new polyamine produced as a key intermediate in polyamine biosynthesis of an extreme thermophile, Thermus thermophilus.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 280 (2005) 30073-82.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:17545282]
  AUTHORS   Cacciapuoti G, Porcelli M, Moretti MA, Sorrentino F, Concilio L, Zappia V, Liu ZJ, Tempel W, Schubot F, Rose JP, Wang BC, Brereton PS, Jenney FE, Adams MW.
  TITLE     The first agmatine/cadaverine aminopropyl transferase: biochemical and structural characterization of an enzyme involved in polyamine biosynthesis in the hyperthermophilic archaeon Pyrococcus furiosus.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 189 (2007) 6057-67.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:20675472]
  AUTHORS   Morimoto N, Fukuda W, Nakajima N, Masuda T, Terui Y, Kanai T, Oshima T, Imanaka T, Fujiwara S
  TITLE     Dual biosynthesis pathway for longer-chain polyamines in the hyperthermophilic archaeon Thermococcus kodakarensis.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 192 (2010) 4991-5001.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:21458463]
  AUTHORS   Ohnuma M, Ganbe T, Terui Y, Niitsu M, Sato T, Tanaka N, Tamakoshi M, Samejima K, Kumasaka T, Oshima T
  TITLE     Crystal structures and enzymatic properties of a triamine/agmatine aminopropyltransferase from Thermus thermophilus.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 408 (2011) 971-86.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.104
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.5.1.104
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.5.1.104
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.104
///
