ENTRY       EC 2.5.1.67                 Enzyme
NAME        chrysanthemyl diphosphate synthase;
            CPPase
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     dimethylallyl-diphosphate:dimethylallyl-diphosphate dimethylallyltransferase (chrysanthemyl-diphosphate-forming)
REACTION    2 dimethylallyl diphosphate = diphosphate + chrysanthemyl diphosphate [RN:R08948]
ALL_REAC    R08948
SUBSTRATE   dimethylallyl diphosphate [CPD:C00235]
PRODUCT     diphosphate [CPD:C00013];
            chrysanthemyl diphosphate [CPD:C18051]
COMMENT     Requires a divalent metal ion for activity, with Mg2+ being better than Mn2+ [1]. Chrysanthemyl diphosphate is a monoterpene with a non-head-to-tail linkage. It is unlike most monoterpenoids, which are derived from geranyl diphosphate and have isoprene units that are linked head-to-tail. The mechanism of its formation is similar to that of the early steps of {terp/squalphyto::squalene and phytoene biosynthesis}. Chrysanthemyl diphosphate is the precursor of chrysanthemic acid, the acid half of the pyrethroid insecticides found in chrysanthemums.
HISTORY     EC 2.5.1.67 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:11287653]
  AUTHORS   Rivera SB, Swedlund BD, King GJ, Bell RN, Hussey CE Jr, Shattuck-Eidens DM, Wrobel WM, Peiser GD, Poulter CD.
  TITLE     Chrysanthemyl diphosphate synthase: isolation of the gene and characterization of the recombinant non-head-to-tail monoterpene synthase from Chrysanthemum cinerariaefolium.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 98 (2001) 4373-8.
  ORGANISM  Chrysanthemum cinerariaefolium
  SEQUENCE  [up:P0C565]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12783539]
  AUTHORS   Erickson HK, Poulter CD.
  TITLE     Chrysanthemyl diphosphate synthase. The relationship among chain elongation, branching, and cyclopropanation reactions in the isoprenoid biosynthetic pathway.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 125 (2003) 6886-8.
  ORGANISM  Artemisia tridentata spiciformis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q7XYS8]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.67
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.5.1.67
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.5.1.67
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.67
///
