ENTRY       EC 2.5.1.111                Enzyme
NAME        4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate 3-dimethylallyltransferase;
            CloQ;
            4HPP dimethylallyltransferase;
            NovQ
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     dimethylallyl diphosphate:4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate 3-dimethylallyltransferase
REACTION    dimethylallyl diphosphate + 4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate = diphosphate + 3-dimethylallyl-4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate [RN:R06757]
ALL_REAC    R06757
SUBSTRATE   dimethylallyl diphosphate [CPD:C00235];
            4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate [CPD:C01179]
PRODUCT     diphosphate [CPD:C00013];
            3-dimethylallyl-4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate [CPD:C12456]
COMMENT     The enzyme is involved in the biosynthesis of the 3-dimethylallyl-4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate moiety of the aminocoumarin antibiotics clorobiocin and novobiocin [1].
HISTORY     EC 2.5.1.111 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:12618544]
  AUTHORS   Pojer F, Wemakor E, Kammerer B, Chen H, Walsh CT, Li SM, Heide L.
  TITLE     CloQ, a prenyltransferase involved in clorobiocin biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 100 (2003) 2316-21.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces roseochromogenes
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8GHB2]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:17077503]
  AUTHORS   Keller S, Pojer F, Heide L, Lawson DM
  TITLE     Crystallization and preliminary X-ray analysis of the aromatic prenyltransferase  CloQ from the clorobiocin biosynthetic cluster of Streptomyces roseochromogenes.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. Sect. F. Struct. Biol. Cryst. Commun. 62 (2006) 1153-5.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces roseochromogenes
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:20946900]
  AUTHORS   Metzger U, Keller S, Stevenson CE, Heide L, Lawson DM
  TITLE     Structure and mechanism of the magnesium-independent aromatic prenyltransferase CloQ from the clorobiocin biosynthetic pathway.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 404 (2010) 611-26.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces roseochromogenes
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8GHB2]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:19557032]
  AUTHORS   Ozaki T, Mishima S, Nishiyama M, Kuzuyama T
  TITLE     NovQ is a prenyltransferase capable of catalyzing the addition of a dimethylallyl group to both phenylpropanoids and flavonoids.
  JOURNAL   J. Antibiot. (Tokyo). 62 (2009) 385-92.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces niveus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9L9F1]
PATHWAY     ec00401  Novobiocin biosynthesis
ORTHOLOGY   K12707  4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate 3-dimethylallyltransferase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.111
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.5.1.111
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.5.1.111
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.111
///
