ENTRY       EC 2.5.1.115                Enzyme
NAME        homogentisate phytyltransferase;
            HPT;
            VTE2 (gene name)
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     phytyl diphosphate:homogentisate phytyltransferase
REACTION    phytyl diphosphate + homogentisate = diphosphate + 2-methyl-6-phytylbenzene-1,4-diol + CO2 [RN:R07500]
ALL_REAC    R07500
SUBSTRATE   phytyl diphosphate [CPD:C05427];
            homogentisate [CPD:C00544]
PRODUCT     diphosphate [CPD:C00013];
            2-methyl-6-phytylbenzene-1,4-diol [CPD:C15882];
            CO2 [CPD:C00011]
COMMENT     Requires Mg2+ for activity [3]. Involved in the biosynthesis of the vitamin E tocopherols. While the enzyme from the cyanobacterium Synechocystis PCC 6803 has an appreciable activity with geranylgeranyl diphosphate (EC 2.5.1.116, homogentisate geranylgeranyltransferase), the enzyme from the plant Arabidopsis thaliana has only a low activity with that substrate [1,3,4].
HISTORY     EC 2.5.1.115 created 2014
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:11706191]
  AUTHORS   Collakova E, DellaPenna D
  TITLE     Isolation and functional analysis of homogentisate phytyltransferase from Synechocystis sp. PCC 6803 and Arabidopsis.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 127 (2001) 1113-24.
  ORGANISM  Synechocystis sp. PCC 6803, Arabidopsis thaliana
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12011362]
  AUTHORS   Savidge B, Weiss JD, Wong YH, Lassner MW, Mitsky TA, Shewmaker CK, Post-Beittenmiller D, Valentin HE
  TITLE     Isolation and characterization of homogentisate phytyltransferase genes from Synechocystis sp. PCC 6803 and Arabidopsis.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 129 (2002) 321-32.
  ORGANISM  Synechocystis sp. PCC 6803
  SEQUENCE  [syn:slr1736] 
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16989822]
  AUTHORS   Sadre R, Gruber J, Frentzen M.
  TITLE     Characterization of homogentisate prenyltransferases involved in plastoquinone-9 and tocochromanol biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 580 (2006) 5357-62.
  ORGANISM  Synechocystis sp. PCC 6803, Arabidopsis thaliana
  SEQUENCE  [syn:slr1736] [ath:AT2G18950]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:21223386]
  AUTHORS   Yang W, Cahoon RE, Hunter SC, Zhang C, Han J, Borgschulte T, Cahoon EB
  TITLE     Vitamin E biosynthesis: functional characterization of the monocot homogentisate  geranylgeranyl transferase.
  JOURNAL   Plant. J. 65 (2011) 206-17.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana, Hordeum vulgare
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.115
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.5.1.115
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.5.1.115
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.115
///
