ENTRY       EC 2.5.1.113                Enzyme
NAME        [CysO sulfur-carrier protein]-thiocarboxylate-dependent cysteine synthase;
            CysM
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     O-phospho-L-serine:thiocarboxylated [CysO sulfur-carrier protein] 2-amino-2-carboxyethyltransferase
REACTION    O-phospho-L-serine + [CysO sulfur-carrier protein]-Gly-NH-CH2-C(O)SH = [CysO sulfur-carrier protein]-Gly-NH-CH2-C(O)-S-L-cysteine + phosphate [RN:R10610]
ALL_REAC    R10610
SUBSTRATE   O-phospho-L-serine [CPD:C01005];
            [CysO sulfur-carrier protein]-Gly-NH-CH2-C(O)SH [CPD:C20728]
PRODUCT     [CysO sulfur-carrier protein]-Gly-NH-CH2-C(O)-S-L-cysteine [CPD:C20729];
            phosphate [CPD:C00009]
COMMENT     A pyridoxal-phosphate protein. The enzyme participates in an alternative pathway for L-cysteine biosynthesis that involves a protein-bound thiocarboxylate as the sulfide donor. The enzyme from the bacterium Mycobacterium tuberculosis also has very low activity with O3-acetyl-L-serine (cf. EC 2.5.1.65, O-phosphoserine sulfhydrylase).
HISTORY     EC 2.5.1.113 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:18842002]
  AUTHORS   O'Leary SE, Jurgenson CT, Ealick SE, Begley TP
  TITLE     O-phospho-L-serine and the thiocarboxylated sulfur carrier protein CysO-COSH are  substrates for CysM, a cysteine synthase from Mycobacterium tuberculosis.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 47 (2008) 11606-15.
  ORGANISM  Mycobacterium tuberculosis
  SEQUENCE  [up:P63873]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:18771296]
  AUTHORS   Jurgenson CT, Burns KE, Begley TP, Ealick SE
  TITLE     Crystal structure of a sulfur carrier protein complex found in the cysteine biosynthetic pathway of Mycobacterium tuberculosis.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 47 (2008) 10354-64.
  ORGANISM  Mycobacterium tuberculosis
  SEQUENCE  [up:P63873]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:18799456]
  AUTHORS   Agren D, Schnell R, Oehlmann W, Singh M, Schneider G
  TITLE     Cysteine synthase (CysM) of Mycobacterium tuberculosis is an O-phosphoserine sulfhydrylase: evidence for an alternative cysteine biosynthesis pathway in mycobacteria.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 283 (2008) 31567-74.
  ORGANISM  Mycobacterium tuberculosis
  SEQUENCE  [up:P63873]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:19101553]
  AUTHORS   Agren D, Schnell R, Schneider G
  TITLE     The C-terminal of CysM from Mycobacterium tuberculosis protects the aminoacrylate intermediate and is involved in sulfur donor selectivity.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 583 (2009) 330-6.
  ORGANISM  Mycobacterium tuberculosis
  SEQUENCE  [up:P63873]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.113
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.5.1.113
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.5.1.113
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.113
///
