ENTRY       EC 2.5.1.81                 Enzyme
NAME        geranylfarnesyl diphosphate synthase;
            FGPP synthase;
            (all-E) geranylfarnesyl diphosphate synthase;
            GFPS;
            Fgs
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     geranylgeranyl-diphosphate:isopentenyl-diphosphate transtransferase (adding 1 isopentenyl unit)
REACTION    geranylgeranyl diphosphate + isopentenyl diphosphate = (2E,6E,10E,14E)-geranylfarnesyl diphosphate + diphosphate [RN:R07475]
ALL_REAC    R07475
SUBSTRATE   geranylgeranyl diphosphate [CPD:C00353];
            isopentenyl diphosphate [CPD:C00129]
PRODUCT     (2E,6E,10E,14E)-geranylfarnesyl diphosphate;
            diphosphate [CPD:C00013]
COMMENT     The enzyme from Methanosarcina mazei is involved in biosynthesis of the polyprenyl side-chain of methanophenazine, an electron carrier utilized for methanogenesis. It prefers geranylgeranyl diphosphate and farnesyl diphosphate as allylic substrate [1]. The enzyme from Aeropyrum pernix prefers farnesyl diphosphate as allylic substrate. The enzyme is involved in the biosynthesis of C25-C25 membrane lipids [2].
HISTORY     EC 2.5.1.81 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:20097171]
  AUTHORS   Ogawa T, Yoshimura T, Hemmi H
  TITLE     Geranylfarnesyl diphosphate synthase from Methanosarcina mazei: Different role, different evolution.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 393 (2010) 16-20.
  ORGANISM  Methanosarcina mazei
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8PYS1]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:10632701]
  AUTHORS   Tachibana A, Yano Y, Otani S, Nomura N, Sako Y, Taniguchi M
  TITLE     Novel prenyltransferase gene encoding farnesylgeranyl diphosphate synthase from a hyperthermophilic archaeon, Aeropyrum pernix. Molecularevolution with alteration  in product specificity.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 267 (2000) 321-8.
  ORGANISM  Aeropyrum pernix
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9UWR6]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8137956]
  AUTHORS   Tachibana A
  TITLE     A novel prenyltransferase, farnesylgeranyl diphosphate synthase, from the haloalkaliphilic archaeon, Natronobacterium pharaonis.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 341 (1994) 291-4.
  ORGANISM  Natronomonas pharaonis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q3IPL1]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15548566]
  AUTHORS   Lee PC, Mijts BN, Petri R, Watts KT, Schmidt-Dannert C
  TITLE     Alteration of product specificity of Aeropyrum pernix farnesylgeranyl diphosphate synthase (Fgs) by directed evolution.
  JOURNAL   Protein. Eng. Des. Sel. 17 (2004) 771-7.
  ORGANISM  Aeropyrum pernix
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9UWR6]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.81
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.5.1.81
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.5.1.81
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.81
///
