ENTRY       EC 2.5.1.69                 Enzyme
NAME        lavandulyl diphosphate synthase;
            FDS-5
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups;
            Transferring alkyl or aryl groups, other than methyl groups (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     dimethylallyl-diphosphate:dimethylallyl-diphosphate dimethylallyltransferase (lavandulyl-diphosphate-forming)
REACTION    2 dimethylallyl diphosphate = diphosphate + lavandulyl diphosphate [RN:R08950]
ALL_REAC    R08950
SUBSTRATE   dimethylallyl diphosphate [CPD:C00235]
PRODUCT     diphosphate [CPD:C00013];
            lavandulyl diphosphate [CPD:C18052]
COMMENT     Lavandulyl diphosphate is a monoterpene with a non-head-to-tail linkage. It is unlike most monoterpenoids, which are derived from geranyl diphosphate and have isoprene units that are linked head-to-tail. When this enzyme is incubated with dimethylallyl diphosphate and isopentenyl diphosphate, it also forms the regular monoterpene geranyl diphosphate [2]. The enzyme from Artemisia tridentata (big sagebrush) forms both lavandulyl diphosphate and chrysanthemyl diphosphate (see EC 2.5.1.67, chrysanthemyl diphosphate synthase) when dimethylally diphosphate is the sole substrate.
HISTORY     EC 2.5.1.69 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:12783539]
  AUTHORS   Erickson HK, Poulter CD.
  TITLE     Chrysanthemyl diphosphate synthase. The relationship among chain elongation, branching, and cyclopropanation reactions in the isoprenoid biosynthetic pathway.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 125 (2003) 6886-8.
  ORGANISM  Artemisia tridentata spiciformis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q7XYS8]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12782626]
  AUTHORS   Hemmerlin A, Rivera SB, Erickson HK, Poulter CD.
  TITLE     Enzymes encoded by the farnesyl diphosphate synthase gene family in the Big Sagebrush Artemisia tridentata ssp. spiciformis.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 278 (2003) 32132-40.
  ORGANISM  Artemisia tridentata spiciformis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q7XYS8]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.69
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.5.1.69
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.5.1.69
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.5.1.69
///
