ENTRY       EC 2.6.1.77                 Enzyme
NAME        taurine---pyruvate aminotransferase;
            Tpa
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring nitrogenous groups;
            Transaminases
SYSNAME     taurine:pyruvate aminotransferase
REACTION    taurine + pyruvate = L-alanine + 2-sulfoacetaldehyde [RN:R05652]
ALL_REAC    R05652
SUBSTRATE   taurine [CPD:C00245];
            pyruvate [CPD:C00022]
PRODUCT     L-alanine [CPD:C00041];
            2-sulfoacetaldehyde [CPD:C00593]
COMMENT     The enzyme from the bacterium Bilophila wadsworthia requires pyridoxal 5'-phosphate as a cofactor, and catalyses a reversible reaction that starts an anaerobic taurine degradation pathway. beta-Alanine is also a significant amino group donor. The enzyme from the bacterium Pseudomonas denitrificans PD1222 can also use hypotaurine, producing 2-sulfinoacetaldehyde, which spontaneously hydrolyses to sulfite and acetaldehyde. Unlike, EC 2.6.1.55, taurine---2-oxoglutarate transaminase, 2-oxoglutarate cannot serve as an acceptor for the amino group.
HISTORY     EC 2.6.1.77 created 2003
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:11082195]
  AUTHORS   Laue H, Cook AM.
  TITLE     Biochemical and molecular characterization of taurine:pyruvate aminotransferase from the anaerobe Bilophila wadsworthia.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 267 (2000) 6841-8.
  ORGANISM  Bilophila wadsworthia
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9APM5]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12471498]
  AUTHORS   Cook AM, Denger K.
  TITLE     Dissimilation of the C2 sulfonates.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Microbiol. 179 (2002) 1-6.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Desulfonispora thiosulfatigenes, Bilophila wadsworthia, Alcaligenes defragrans
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11728723]
  AUTHORS   Masepohl B, Fuhrer F, Klipp W.
  TITLE     Genetic analysis of a Rhodobacter capsulatus gene region involved in utilization of taurine as a sulfur source.
  JOURNAL   FEMS. Microbiol. Lett. 205 (2001) 105-11.
  ORGANISM  Rhodobacter capsulatus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:23603744]
  AUTHORS   Felux AK, Denger K, Weiss M, Cook AM, Schleheck D
  TITLE     Paracoccus denitrificans PD1222 utilizes hypotaurine via transamination followed  by spontaneous desulfination to yield acetaldehyde and, finally, acetate for growth.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 195 (2013) 2921-30.
PATHWAY     ec00430  Taurine and hypotaurine metabolism
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
ORTHOLOGY   K03851  taurine-pyruvate aminotransferase
GENES       PIN: Ping_0051
            BPE: BP0721
            BPA: BPP3675
            BBR: BB4110
            DVM: DvMF_0516
            DDS: Ddes_0218
            DPS: DP0541
            SIL: SPO0673(tpa)
            SIT: TM1040_0159
            RSP: RSP_0943(yhxA)
            RSH: Rsph17029_2602
            RSQ: Rsph17025_2972
            RSK: RSKD131_2333
            RCP: RCAP_rcc02240(tpa)
            RDE: RD1_0981(tpa)
            PDE: Pden_4273
            DSH: Dshi_2042(tpa)
            KVU: EIO_1453
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.6.1.77
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.6.1.77
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.6.1.77
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.6.1.77
            CAS: 51901-18-9
///
