ENTRY       EC 2.6.1.93                 Enzyme
NAME        neamine transaminase;
            glutamate---6'-dehydroparomamine aminotransferase;
            btrB (gene name);
            neoN (gene name);
            kacL (gene name)
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring nitrogenous groups;
            Transaminases
SYSNAME     neamine:2-oxoglutarate aminotransferase
REACTION    neamine + 2-oxoglutarate = 6'-dehydroparomamine + L-glutamate [RN:R08897]
ALL_REAC    R08897
SUBSTRATE   neamine [CPD:C01441];
            2-oxoglutarate [CPD:C00026]
PRODUCT     6'-dehydroparomamine [CPD:C17583];
            L-glutamate [CPD:C00025]
COMMENT     The reaction occurs in vivo in the opposite direction. Involved in the biosynthetic pathways of several clinically important aminocyclitol antibiotics, including kanamycin B, butirosin, neomycin and ribostamycin. Works in combination with EC 1.1.3.43, paromamine 6-oxidase, to replace the 6'-hydroxy group of paromamine with an amino group. The enzyme from the bacterium Streptomyces kanamyceticus can also catalyse EC 2.6.1.94, 2'-deamino-2'-hydroxyneamine transaminase, which leads to production of kanamycin A [3]. The enzyme from the bacterium Streptomyces fradiae can also catalyse EC 2.6.1.95, leading to production of neomycin C [2].
HISTORY     EC 2.6.1.93 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:17206729]
  AUTHORS   Huang F, Spiteller D, Koorbanally NA, Li Y, Llewellyn NM, Spencer JB.
  TITLE     Elaboration of neosamine rings in the biosynthesis of neomycin and butirosin.
  JOURNAL   Chembiochem. 8 (2007) 283-8.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus circulans, Streptomyces fradiae
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q4H4F5]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:21689223]
  AUTHORS   Clausnitzer D, Piepersberg W, Wehmeier UF
  TITLE     The oxidoreductases LivQ and NeoQ are responsible for the different 6'-modifications in the aminoglycosides lividomycin and neomycin.
  JOURNAL   J. Appl. Microbiol. 111 (2011) 642-51.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces fradiae
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q53U08]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:21983602]
  AUTHORS   Park JW, Park SR, Nepal KK, Han AR, Ban YH, Yoo YJ, Kim EJ, Kim EM, Kim D, Sohng JK, Yoon YJ
  TITLE     Discovery of parallel pathways of kanamycin biosynthesis allows antibiotic manipulation.
  JOURNAL   Nat. Chem. Biol. 7 (2011) 843-52.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces kanamyceticus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q6L741]
PATHWAY     ec00524  Butirosin and neomycin biosynthesis
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K13553  neamine transaminase / 2'-deamino-2'-hydroxyneamine transaminase / neomycin C transaminase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.6.1.93
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.6.1.93
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.6.1.93
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.6.1.93
///
