ENTRY       EC 2.6.1.88                 Enzyme
NAME        methionine transaminase;
            methionine-oxo-acid transaminase
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring nitrogenous groups;
            Transaminases
SYSNAME     L-methionine:2-oxo-acid aminotransferase
REACTION    L-methionine + a 2-oxo carboxylate = 2-oxo-4-methylthiobutanoate + an L-amino acid [RN:R08618]
ALL_REAC    R08618
SUBSTRATE   L-methionine [CPD:C00073];
            2-oxo carboxylate [CPD:C00161]
PRODUCT     2-oxo-4-methylthiobutanoate [CPD:C01180];
            L-amino acid [CPD:C00151]
COMMENT     The enzyme is most active with L-methionine. It participates in the L-methionine salvage pathway from S-methyl-5'-thioadenosine, a by-product of polyamine biosynthesis. The enzyme from the bacterium Klebsiella pneumoniae can use several different amino acids as amino donor, with aromatic amino acids being the most effective [1]. The enzyme from the plant Arabidopsis thaliana is also a part of the chain elongation pathway in the biosynthesis of methionine-derived glucosinolates [3].
HISTORY     EC 2.6.1.88 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10074065]
  AUTHORS   Heilbronn J, Wilson J, Berger BJ.
  TITLE     Tyrosine aminotransferase catalyzes the final step of methionine recycling in Klebsiella pneumoniae.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 181 (1999) 1739-47.
  ORGANISM  Klebsiella pneumoniae
  SEQUENCE  [up:O85746]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:15280032]
  AUTHORS   Dolzan M, Johansson K, Roig-Zamboni V, Campanacci V, Tegoni M, Schneider G, Cambillau C
  TITLE     Crystal structure and reactivity of YbdL from Escherichia coli identify a methionine aminotransferase function.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 571 (2004) 141-6.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b0600]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:17056707]
  AUTHORS   Schuster J, Knill T, Reichelt M, Gershenzon J, Binder S
  TITLE     Branched-chain aminotransferase4 is part of the chain elongation pathway in the biosynthesis of methionine-derived glucosinolates in Arabidopsis.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Cell. 18 (2006) 2664-79.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9LE06]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.6.1.88
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.6.1.88
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.6.1.88
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.6.1.88
///
