ENTRY       EC 2.7.7.67                 Enzyme
NAME        CDP-archaeol synthase;
            CDP-2,3-di-O-geranylgeranyl-sn-glycerol synthase;
            CTP:2,3-GG-GP ether cytidylyltransferase;
            CTP:2,3-di-O-geranylgeranyl-sn-glycero-1-phosphate cytidyltransferase
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring phosphorus-containing groups;
            Nucleotidyltransferases
SYSNAME     CTP:2,3-bis-O-(geranylgeranyl)-sn-glycero-1-phosphate cytidylyltransferase
REACTION    CTP + 2,3-bis-O-(geranylgeranyl)-sn-glycero-1-phosphate = diphosphate + CDP-2,3-bis-O-(geranylgeranyl)-sn-glycerol [RN:R08966]
ALL_REAC    R08966
SUBSTRATE   CTP [CPD:C00063];
            2,3-bis-O-(geranylgeranyl)-sn-glycero-1-phosphate
PRODUCT     diphosphate [CPD:C00013];
            CDP-2,3-bis-O-(geranylgeranyl)-sn-glycerol [CPD:C18059]
COMMENT     This enzyme catalyses one of the steps in the biosynthesis of polar lipids in Archaea, which are characterized by having an sn-glycero-1-phosphate backbone rather than an sn-glycero-3-phosphate backbone as is found in bacteria and eukaryotes [1]. The enzyme requires Mg2+ and K+ for maximal activity [1]. The other enzymes involved in the biosynthesis of polar lipids in Archaea are EC 1.1.1.261 (sn-glycerol-1-phosphate dehydrogenase), EC 2.5.1.41 (phosphoglycerol geranylgeranyltransferase) and EC 2.5.1.42 (geranylgeranylglycerol-phosphate geranylgeranyltransferase), which together alkylate the hydroxy groups of glycerol 1-phosphate to give unsaturated archaetidic acid, which is acted upon by this enzyme to form CDP-unsaturated archaeol. The final step in the pathway involves the addition of L-serine, with concomitant removal of CMP, leading to the production of unsaturated archaetidylserine [1].
HISTORY     EC 2.7.7.67 created 2009
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10960477]
  AUTHORS   Morii H, Nishihara M, Koga Y
  TITLE     CTP:2,3-di-O-geranylgeranyl-sn-glycero-1-phosphate cytidyltransferase in the methanogenic archaeon Methanothermobacter thermoautotrophicus.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 275 (2000) 36568-74.
  ORGANISM  Methanothermobacter thermoautotrophicus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12562787]
  AUTHORS   Morii H, Koga Y
  TITLE     CDP-2,3-Di-O-geranylgeranyl-sn-glycerol:L-serine O-archaetidyltransferase (archaetidylserine synthase) in the methanogenic archaeon Methanothermobacter thermautotrophicus.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 185 (2003) 1181-9.
  ORGANISM  Methanothermobacter thermoautotrophicus
PATHWAY     ec00564  Glycerophospholipid metabolism
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.7.7.67
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.7.7.67
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.7.7.67
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.7.7.67
            CAS: 329791-09-5
///
