ENTRY       EC 2.7.11.7                 Enzyme
NAME        myosin-heavy-chain kinase;
            ATP:myosin-heavy-chain O-phosphotransferase;
            calmodulin-dependent myosin heavy chain kinase;
            MHCK;
            MIHC kinase;
            myosin heavy chain kinase;
            myosin I heavy-chain kinase;
            myosin II heavy-chain kinase;
            [myosin-heavy-chain] kinase;
            myosin heavy chain kinase A;
            STK6
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring phosphorus-containing groups;
            Protein-serine/threonine kinases
SYSNAME     ATP:[myosin heavy-chain] O-phosphotransferase
REACTION    ATP + [myosin heavy-chain] = ADP + [myosin heavy-chain] phosphate
ALL_REAC    (other) R04023
SUBSTRATE   ATP [CPD:C00002];
            [myosin heavy-chain]
PRODUCT     ADP [CPD:C00008];
            myosin heavy-chain phosphate [CPD:C03874]
COMMENT     The enzyme from Dictyostelium sp. (slime moulds) brings about phosphorylation of the heavy chains of Dictyostelium myosin, inhibiting the actin-activated ATPase activity of the myosin. One threonine residue in each heavy chain acts as acceptor. While the enzyme from some species is activated by actin, in other cases Ca2+/calmodulin are required for activity.
HISTORY     EC 2.7.11.7 created 1990 as EC 2.7.1.129, transferred 2005 to EC 2.7.11.7
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3027076]
  AUTHORS   Cote GP, Bukiejko U.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of a myosin heavy chain kinase from Dictyostelium discoideum.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 262 (1987) 1065-72.
  ORGANISM  Dictyostelium discoideum
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:6309772]
  AUTHORS   Hammer JA 3rd, Albanesi JP, Korn ED.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of a myosin I heavy chain kinase from Acanthamoeba castellanii.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 258 (1983) 10168-75.
  ORGANISM  Acanthamoeba castellanii
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:2822719]
  AUTHORS   Rieker JP, Swanljung-Collins H, Collins JH.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of a calmodulin-dependent myosin heavy chain kinase from intestinal brush border.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 262 (1987) 15262-8.
  ORGANISM  Gallus gallus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:2549052]
  AUTHORS   Ravid S, Spudich JA.
  TITLE     Myosin heavy chain kinase from developed Dictyostelium cells. Purification and characterization.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 264 (1989) 15144-50.
  ORGANISM  Dictyostelium discoideum
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:2168881]
  AUTHORS   Brzeska H, Lynch TJ, Martin B, Corigliano-Murphy A, Korn ED.
  TITLE     Substrate specificity of Acanthamoeba myosin I heavy chain kinase as determined with synthetic peptides.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 265 (1990) 16138-44.
  ORGANISM  Acanthamoeba castellanii
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:1321427]
  AUTHORS   Ravid S, Spudich JA.
  TITLE     Membrane-bound Dictyostelium myosin heavy chain kinase: a developmentally regulated substrate-specific member of the protein kinase C family.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 89 (1992) 5877-81.
  ORGANISM  Dictyostelium discoideum
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:7822274]
  AUTHORS   Futey LM, Medley QG, Cote GP, Egelhoff TT.
  TITLE     Structural analysis of myosin heavy chain kinase A from Dictyostelium. Evidence for a highly divergent protein kinase domain, an amino-terminal coiled-coil domain, and a domain homologous to the beta-subunit of heterotrimeric G proteins.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 270 (1995) 523-9.
  ORGANISM  Dictyostelium discoideum
  SEQUENCE  [ddi:DDB_G0291231]
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:9539704]
  AUTHORS   Szczepanowska J, Ramachandran U, Herring CJ, Gruschus JM, Qin J, Korn ED, Brzeska H.
  TITLE     Effect of mutating the regulatory phosphoserine and conserved threonine on the activity of the expressed catalytic domain of Acanthamoeba myosin I heavy chain kinase.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 95 (1998) 4146-51.
  ORGANISM  Acanthamoeba castellanii
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:15545285]
  AUTHORS   Egelhoff TT, Croft D, Steimle PA.
  TITLE     Actin activation of myosin heavy chain kinase A in Dictyostelium: a biochemical mechanism for the spatial regulation of myosin II filament disassembly.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 280 (2005) 2879-87.
  ORGANISM  Dictyostelium discoideum
ORTHOLOGY   K08240  myosin-heavy-chain kinase
GENES       TBR: Tb927.4.4970(Tb04.3M17.320) Tb927.8.7450(Tb08.10K10.110)
            TCR: 509011.100 510681.20
            LMA: LMJF_36_4700
            LIF: LINJ_36_4780
            LDO: LDBPK_364780
            LMI: LMXM_36_4551
            LBZ: LBRM_35_4800
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.7.11.7
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.7.11.7
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.7.11.7
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.7.11.7
            CAS: 64763-54-8
///
