ENTRY       EC 2.8.4.4                  Enzyme
NAME        [ribosomal protein S12] (aspartate89-C3)-methylthiotransferase;
            RimO
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring sulfur-containing groups;
            Transferring alkylthio groups
SYSNAME     [ribosomal protein S12]-Asp89:sulfur-(sulfur carrier),S-adenosyl-L-methionine C3-methylthiotransferase
REACTION    Asp89-[ribosomal protein S12] + sulfur-(sulfur carrier) + 2 S-adenosyl-L-methionine = 3-methylthioaspartate89-[ribosomal protein S12] + S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine + (sulfur carrier) + L-methionine + 5'-deoxyadenosine (overall reaction) [RN:R10652];
            (1a) Asp89-[ribosomal protein S12] + sulfur-(sulfur carrier) + S-adenosyl-L-methionine = 3-thioaspartate89-[ribosomal protein S12] + (sulfur carrier) + L-methionine + 5'-deoxyadenosine [RN:R10653];
            (1b) S-adenosyl-L-methionine + 3-thioaspartate89-[ribosomal protein S12] = S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine + 3-methylthioaspartate89-[ribosomal protein S12] [RN:R10654]
ALL_REAC    R10652 R10653 R10654
SUBSTRATE   Asp89-[ribosomal protein S12];
            sulfur-(sulfur carrier);
            S-adenosyl-L-methionine [CPD:C00019];
            3-thioaspartate89-[ribosomal protein S12]
PRODUCT     3-methylthioaspartate89-[ribosomal protein S12];
            S-adenosyl-L-homocysteine [CPD:C00021];
            (sulfur carrier);
            L-methionine [CPD:C00073];
            5'-deoxyadenosine [CPD:C05198];
            3-thioaspartate89-[ribosomal protein S12]
COMMENT     This bacterial enzyme binds two [4Fe-4S] clusters as well as the transferred sulfur [2,3]. The enzyme is a member of the superfamily of S-adenosyl-L-methionine-dependent radical (radical AdoMet) enzymes. The sulfur donor is believed to be one of the [4Fe-4S] clusters, which is sacrificed in the process, so that in vitro the reaction is a single turnover.
HISTORY     EC 2.8.4.4 created 2014
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:18252828]
  AUTHORS   Anton BP, Saleh L, Benner JS, Raleigh EA, Kasif S, Roberts RJ
  TITLE     RimO, a MiaB-like enzyme, methylthiolates the universally conserved Asp88 residue of ribosomal protein S12 in Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 105 (2008) 1826-31.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b0835]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:19736993]
  AUTHORS   Lee KH, Saleh L, Anton BP, Madinger CL, Benner JS, Iwig DF, Roberts RJ, Krebs C, Booker SJ
  TITLE     Characterization of RimO, a new member of the methylthiotransferase subclass of the radical SAM superfamily.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 48 (2009) 10162-74.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b0835]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:20007320]
  AUTHORS   Arragain S, Garcia-Serres R, Blondin G, Douki T, Clemancey M, Latour JM, Forouhar F, Neely H, Montelione GT, Hunt JF, Mulliez E, Fontecave M, Atta M
  TITLE     Post-translational modification of ribosomal proteins: structural and functional  characterization of RimO from Thermotoga maritima, a radical S-adenosylmethionine methylthiotransferase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 285 (2010) 5792-801.
  ORGANISM  Thermotoga maritima
  SEQUENCE  [tma:TM1862]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:21169565]
  AUTHORS   Strader MB, Costantino N, Elkins CA, Chen CY, Patel I, Makusky AJ, Choy JS, Court DL, Markey SP, Kowalak JA
  TITLE     A proteomic and transcriptomic approach reveals new insight into beta-methylthiolation of Escherichia coli ribosomal protein S12.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Cell. Proteomics. 10 (2011) M110.005199.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b0835 b0905]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:23991893]
  AUTHORS   Landgraf BJ, Arcinas AJ, Lee KH, Booker SJ
  TITLE     Identification of an intermediate methyl carrier in the radical S-adenosylmethionine methylthiotransferases RimO and MiaB.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 135 (2013) 15404-16.
  ORGANISM  Thermotoga maritima
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.8.4.4
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.8.4.4
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.8.4.4
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.8.4.4
///
