ENTRY       EC 2.8.1.11                 Enzyme
NAME        molybdopterin synthase sulfurtransferase;
            adenylyltransferase and sulfurtransferase MOCS3;
            Cnx5 (gene name);
            molybdopterin synthase sulfurylase
CLASS       Transferases;
            Transferring sulfur-containing groups;
            Sulfurtransferases
SYSNAME     persulfurated L-cysteine desulfurase:[molybdopterin-synthase sulfur-carrier protein]-Gly-Gly sulfurtransferase
REACTION    [molybdopterin-synthase sulfur-carrier protein]-Gly-Gly-AMP + [cysteine desulfurase]-S-sulfanyl-L-cysteine = AMP + [molybdopterin-synthase sulfur-carrier protein]-Gly-NH-CH2-C(O)SH + cysteine desulfurase
SUBSTRATE   [molybdopterin-synthase sulfur-carrier protein]-Gly-Gly-AMP;
            [cysteine desulfurase]-S-sulfanyl-L-cysteine
PRODUCT     AMP [CPD:C00020];
            [molybdopterin-synthase sulfur-carrier protein]-Gly-NH-CH2-C(O)SH;
            cysteine desulfurase
COMMENT     The enzyme transfers sulfur to form a thiocarboxylate moiety on the C-terminal glycine of the small subunit of EC 2.8.1.12, molybdopterin synthase. In the human, the reaction is catalysed by the rhodanese-like C-terminal domain (cf. EC 2.8.1.1) of the MOCS3 protein, a bifunctional protein that also contains EC 2.7.7.80, molybdopterin-synthase adenylyltransferase, at the N-terminal domain.
HISTORY     EC 2.8.1.11 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:15910006]
  AUTHORS   Matthies A, Nimtz M, Leimkuhler S
  TITLE     Molybdenum cofactor biosynthesis in humans: identification of a persulfide group  in the rhodanese-like domain of MOCS3 by mass spectrometry.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 44 (2005) 7912-20.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:27304]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:11290749]
  AUTHORS   Leimkuhler S, Rajagopalan KV
  TITLE     A sulfurtransferase is required in the transfer of cysteine sulfur in the in vitro synthesis of molybdopterin from precursor Z in Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 276 (2001) 22024-31.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b0826]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:19798741]
  AUTHORS   Hanzelmann P, Dahl JU, Kuper J, Urban A, Muller-Theissen U, Leimkuhler S, Schindelin H
  TITLE     Crystal structure of YnjE from Escherichia coli, a sulfurtransferase with three rhodanese domains.
  JOURNAL   Protein. Sci. 18 (2009) 2480-91.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b1757]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:21856748]
  AUTHORS   Dahl JU, Urban A, Bolte A, Sriyabhaya P, Donahue JL, Nimtz M, Larson TJ, Leimkuhler S
  TITLE     The identification of a novel protein involved in molybdenum cofactor biosynthesis in Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 286 (2011) 35801-12.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 2.8.1.11
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 2.8.1.11
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 2.8.1.11
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 2.8.1.11
///
