ENTRY       EC 3.1.3.81                 Enzyme
NAME        diacylglycerol diphosphate phosphatase;
            DGPP phosphatase;
            DGPP phosphohydrolase;
            DPP1;
            DPPL1;
            DPPL2;
            PAP2;
            pyrophosphate phosphatase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on ester bonds;
            Phosphoric-monoester hydrolases
SYSNAME     1,2-diacyl-sn-glycerol 3-phosphate phosphohydrolase
REACTION    1,2-diacyl-sn-glycerol 3-diphosphate + H2O = 1,2-diacyl-sn-glycerol 3-phosphate + phosphate [RN:R09644]
ALL_REAC    R09644;
            (other) R02239
SUBSTRATE   1,2-diacyl-sn-glycerol 3-diphosphate [CPD:C19776];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     1,2-diacyl-sn-glycerol 3-phosphate [CPD:C00416];
            phosphate [CPD:C00009]
COMMENT     The bifunctional enzyme catalyses the dephosphorylation of diacylglycerol diphosphate to phosphatidate and the subsequent dephosphorylation of phosphatidate to diacylglycerol (cf. phosphatidate phosphatase (EC 3.1.3.4)). It regulates intracellular levels of diacylglycerol diphosphate and phosphatidate, phospholipid molecules believed to play a signalling role in stress response [6]. The phosphatase activity of the bifunctional enzyme is Mg2+-independent and N-ethylmaleimide-insensitive and is distinct from the Mg2+-dependent and N-ethylmaleimide-sensitive enzyme EC 3.1.3.4 (phosphatidate phosphatase) [5].The diacylglycerol pyrophosphate phosphatase activity in Saccharomyces cerevisiae is induced by zinc depletion, by inositol supplementation, and when cells enter the stationary phase [4].
HISTORY     EC 3.1.3.81 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8940025]
  AUTHORS   Dillon DA, Wu WI, Riedel B, Wissing JB, Dowhan W, Carman GM
  TITLE     The Escherichia coli pgpB gene encodes for a diacylglycerol pyrophosphate phosphatase activity.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 271 (1996) 30548-53.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9099673]
  AUTHORS   Dillon DA, Chen X, Zeimetz GM, Wu WI, Waggoner DW, Dewald J, Brindley DN, Carman GM
  TITLE     Mammalian Mg2+-independent phosphatidate phosphatase (PAP2) displays diacylglycerol pyrophosphate phosphatase activity.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 272 (1997) 10361-6.
  ORGANISM  Saccharomyces cerevisiae
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8567632]
  AUTHORS   Wu WI, Liu Y, Riedel B, Wissing JB, Fischl AS, Carman GM
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of diacylglycerol pyrophosphate phosphatase from Saccharomyces cerevisiae.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 271 (1996) 1868-76.
  ORGANISM  Saccharomyces cerevisiae
  SEQUENCE  [sce:YDR284C]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:14642771]
  AUTHORS   Oshiro J, Han GS, Carman GM
  TITLE     Diacylglycerol pyrophosphate phosphatase in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1635 (2003) 1-9.
  ORGANISM  Saccharomyces cerevisiae
  SEQUENCE  [sce:YDR284C]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:9370315]
  AUTHORS   Carman GM
  TITLE     Phosphatidate phosphatases and diacylglycerol pyrophosphate phosphatases in Saccharomyces cerevisiae and Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1348 (1997) 45-55.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:11139591]
  AUTHORS   Han GS, Johnston CN, Chen X, Athenstaedt K, Daum G, Carman GM
  TITLE     Regulation of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae DPP1-encoded diacylglycerol pyrophosphate phosphatase by zinc.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 276 (2001) 10126-33.
  ORGANISM  Saccharomyces cerevisiae
  SEQUENCE  [sce:YDR284C]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.1.3.81
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.1.3.81
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.1.3.81
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.1.3.81
///
