ENTRY       EC 3.1.6.19                 Enzyme
NAME        (R)-specific secondary-alkylsulfatase;
            S3 secondary alkylsulphohydrolase;
            Pisa1;
            secondary alkylsulphohydrolase;
            (R)-specific sec-alkylsulfatase;
            sec-alkylsulfatase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on ester bonds;
            Sulfuric-ester hydrolases
SYSNAME     (R)-secondary-alkyl sulfate sulfohydrolase [(S)-secondary-alcohol forming]
REACTION    an (R)-secondary-alkyl sulfate + H2O = an (S)-secondary-alcohol + sulfate
SUBSTRATE   (R)-secondary-alkyl sulfate;
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     (S)-secondary-alcohol;
            sulfate [CPD:C00059]
COMMENT     The enzyme from Rhodococcus ruber is involved in the biodegradation of alkyl sulfate esters used as detergents and released into the environment. The prefered substrates are linear secondary-alkyl sulfate esters, particularly octan-2-yl, octan-3-yl, and octan-4-yl sulfates [1]. The enzyme from Pseudomonas sp. DSM6611 utilizes a range of secondary-alkyl sulfate esters bearing aromatic, olefinic and acetylenic moieties. Perfect enantioselectivities are obtained for substrates bearing groups of different size adjacent to the sulfate moiety [4]. The enzymic hydrolysis proceeds through inversion of the configuration at the stereogenic carbon atom [1,4]. The enzyme contains a Zn2+ ion [3].
HISTORY     EC 3.1.6.19 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:12732552]
  AUTHORS   Pogorevc M, Faber K
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of an inverting stereo- and enantioselective sec-alkylsulfatase from the gram-positive bacterium Rhodococcus ruber DSM 44541.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 69 (2003) 2810-5.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:15606122]
  AUTHORS   Wallner SR, Nestl BM, Faber K
  TITLE     Highly enantioselective sec-alkyl sulfatase activity of Sulfolobus acidocaldarius DSM 639.
  JOURNAL   Org. Lett. 6 (2004) 5009-10.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:23061549]
  AUTHORS   Knaus T, Schober M, Kepplinger B, Faccinelli M, Pitzer J, Faber K, Macheroux P, Wagner U
  TITLE     Structure and mechanism of an inverting alkylsulfatase from Pseudomonas sp. DSM6611 specific for secondary alkyl sulfates.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. J. 279 (2012) 4374-84.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas sp
REFERENCE   4
  AUTHORS   Schober, M., Knaus, T., Toesch, M., Macheroux, P., Wagner, U. and Faber, K.
  TITLE     The substrate spectrum of the inverting sec-alkylsulfatase Pisa1.
  JOURNAL   Adv. Synth. Catal. 354 (2012) 1737-1742.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.1.6.19
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.1.6.19
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.1.6.19
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.1.6.19
///
