ENTRY       EC 3.1.2.29                 Enzyme
NAME        fluoroacetyl-CoA thioesterase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on ester bonds;
            Thioester hydrolases
SYSNAME     fluoroacetyl-CoA hydrolase
REACTION    fluoroacetyl-CoA + H2O = fluoroacetate + CoA [RN:R09643]
ALL_REAC    R09643
SUBSTRATE   fluoroacetyl-CoA [CPD:C19775];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     fluoroacetate [CPD:C06108];
            CoA [CPD:C00010]
COMMENT     Fluoroacetate is extremely toxic. It reacts with CoA to form fluoroacetyl-CoA, which substitutes for acetyl CoA and reacts with EC 2.3.3.1 (citrate synthase) to produce fluorocitrate, a metabolite of which binds very tightly to EC 4.2.1.3 (aconitase) and halts the TCA cycle. This enzyme hydrolyses fluoroacetyl-CoA before it can react with citrate synthase, and thus confers fluoroacetate resistance on the organisms that produce it. It has been described in the poisonous plant Dichapetalum cymosum and the bacterium Streptomyces cattleya, both of which are fluoroacetate producers.
HISTORY     EC 3.1.2.29 created 2011
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Meyer, J.J.M., Grobbelaar, N., Vleggaar, R. and Louw, A.I.
  TITLE     Fluoroacetyl-coenzyme-A hydrolase-like activity in Dichapetalum cymosum.
  JOURNAL   J. Plant Physiol. 139 (1992) 369-372.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16720268]
  AUTHORS   Huang F, Haydock SF, Spiteller D, Mironenko T, Li TL, O'Hagan D, Leadlay PF, Spencer JB
  TITLE     The gene cluster for fluorometabolite biosynthesis in Streptomyces cattleya: a thioesterase confers resistance to fluoroacetyl-coenzyme A.
  JOURNAL   Chem. Biol. 13 (2006) 475-84.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces cattleya
  SEQUENCE  [sct:SCAT_4159]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:20430898]
  AUTHORS   Dias MV, Huang F, Chirgadze DY, Tosin M, Spiteller D, Dry EF, Leadlay PF, Spencer JB, Blundell TL
  TITLE     Structural basis for the activity and substrate specificity of fluoroacetyl-CoA thioesterase FlK.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 285 (2010) 22495-504.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces cattleya
  SEQUENCE  [sct:SCAT_4159]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.1.2.29
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.1.2.29
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.1.2.29
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.1.2.29
///
