ENTRY       EC 3.1.3.76                 Enzyme
NAME        lipid-phosphate phosphatase;
            hydroxy fatty acid phosphatase;
            dihydroxy fatty acid phosphatase;
            hydroxy lipid phosphatase;
            sEH (ambiguous);
            soluble epoxide hydrolase (ambiguous)
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on ester bonds;
            Phosphoric-monoester hydrolases
SYSNAME     (9S,10S)-10-hydroxy-9-(phosphonooxy)octadecanoate phosphohydrolase
REACTION    (9S,10S)-10-hydroxy-9-(phosphonooxy)octadecanoate + H2O = (9S,10S)-9,10-dihydroxyoctadecanoate + phosphate [RN:R07582]
ALL_REAC    R07582
SUBSTRATE   (9S,10S)-10-hydroxy-9-(phosphonooxy)octadecanoate [CPD:C15989];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     (9S,10S)-9,10-dihydroxyoctadecanoate [CPD:C15988];
            phosphate [CPD:C00009]
COMMENT     Requires Mg2+ for maximal activity. The enzyme from mammals is a bifunctional enzyme: the N-terminal domain exhibits lipid-phosphate-phosphatase activity and the C-terminal domain has the activity of EC 3.3.2.10, soluble epoxide hydrolase (sEH) [1]. The best substrates for this enzyme are 10-hydroxy-9-(phosphonooxy)octadecanoates, with the threo- form being a better substrate than the erythro- form [1]. The phosphatase activity is not found in plant sEH or in EC 3.3.2.9, microsomal epoxide hydrolase, from mammals [1].
HISTORY     EC 3.1.3.76 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:12574510]
  AUTHORS   Newman JW, Morisseau C, Harris TR, Hammock BD.
  TITLE     The soluble epoxide hydrolase encoded by EPXH2 is a bifunctional enzyme with novel lipid phosphate phosphatase activity.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 100 (2003) 1558-63.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:2053]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12574508]
  AUTHORS   Cronin A, Mowbray S, Durk H, Homburg S, Fleming I, Fisslthaler B, Oesch F, Arand M.
  TITLE     The N-terminal domain of mammalian soluble epoxide hydrolase is a phosphatase.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 100 (2003) 1552-7.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Rattus norvegicus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:15822179]
  AUTHORS   Morisseau C, Hammock BD.
  TITLE     Epoxide hydrolases: mechanisms, inhibitor designs, and biological roles.
  JOURNAL   Annu. Rev. Pharmacol. Toxicol. 45 (2005) 311-33.
  ORGANISM  mammalian
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16142916]
  AUTHORS   Tran KL, Aronov PA, Tanaka H, Newman JW, Hammock BD, Morisseau C.
  TITLE     Lipid sulfates and sulfonates are allosteric competitive inhibitors of the N-terminal phosphatase activity of the mammalian soluble epoxide hydrolase.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 44 (2005) 12179-87.
  ORGANISM  mammalian
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15748653]
  AUTHORS   Newman JW, Morisseau C, Hammock BD.
  TITLE     Epoxide hydrolases: their roles and interactions with lipid metabolism.
  JOURNAL   Prog. Lipid. Res. 44 (2005) 1-51.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Macaca mulatta, Mus musculus, Rattus norvegicus, Equus caballus, Sus scofa, Cavia porcellus, Mesocricetus sp., Oncorhynchus mykiss, Oryctolagus cuniculus, Oryzias latipes, Papio sp., Pimphales promelas, Stenotomus chrysops
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:15196990]
  AUTHORS   Srivastava PK, Sharma VK, Kalonia DS, Grant DF.
  TITLE     Polymorphisms in human soluble epoxide hydrolase: effects on enzyme activity, enzyme stability, and quaternary structure.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 427 (2004) 164-9.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:15096040]
  AUTHORS   Gomez GA, Morisseau C, Hammock BD, Christianson DW.
  TITLE     Structure of human epoxide hydrolase reveals mechanistic inferences on bifunctional catalysis in epoxide and phosphate ester hydrolysis.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 43 (2004) 4716-23.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.1.3.76
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.1.3.76
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.1.3.76
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.1.3.76
///
