ENTRY       EC 3.1.1.82                 Enzyme
NAME        pheophorbidase;
            phedase;
            PPD
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on ester bonds;
            Carboxylic-ester hydrolases
SYSNAME     pheophorbide-a hydrolase
REACTION    pheophorbide a + H2O = pyropheophorbide a + methanol + CO2 (overall reaction) [RN:R08974];
            (1a) pheophorbide a + H2O = C-132-carboxypyropheophorbide a + methanol [RN:R08975];
            (1b) C-132-carboxypyropheophorbide a = pyropheophorbide a + CO2 (spontaneous) [RN:R08976]
ALL_REAC    R08974 R08975 R08976
SUBSTRATE   pheophorbide a [CPD:C18021];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            C-132-carboxypyropheophorbide a
PRODUCT     pyropheophorbide a [CPD:C18064];
            methanol [CPD:C00132];
            CO2 [CPD:C00011];
            C-132-carboxypyropheophorbide a
COMMENT     This enzyme forms part of the chlorophyll degradation pathway, and is found in higher plants and in algae. In higher plants it participates in de-greening processes such as fruit ripening, leaf senescence, and flowering. The enzyme exists in two forms: type 1 is induced by senescence whereas type 2 is constitutively expressed [1,2]. The enzyme is highly specific for pheophorbide as substrate (with a preference for pheophorbide a over pheophorbide b) as other chlorophyll derivatives such as protochlorophyllide a, pheophytin a and c, chlorophyll a and b, and chlorophyllide a cannot act as substrates [2]. Another enzyme, called pheophorbide demethoxycarbonylase (PDC), produces pyropheophorbide a from pheophorbide a without forming an intermediate although the precise reaction is not yet known [1].
HISTORY     EC 3.1.1.82 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:16228561]
  AUTHORS   Suzuki Y, Doi M, Shioi Y.
  TITLE     Two enzymatic reaction pathways in the formation of pyropheophorbide a.
  JOURNAL   Photosynth. Res. 74 (2002) 225-33.
  ORGANISM  Raphanus sativus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q2V0W1]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16384908]
  AUTHORS   Suzuki Y, Amano T, Shioi Y.
  TITLE     Characterization and cloning of the chlorophyll-degrading enzyme pheophorbidase from cotyledons of radish.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 140 (2006) 716-25.
  ORGANISM  Raphanus sativus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q2V0W1]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16669755]
  AUTHORS   Hortensteiner S.
  TITLE     Chlorophyll degradation during senescence.
  JOURNAL   Annu. Rev. Plant. Biol. 57 (2006) 55-77.
PATHWAY     ec00860  Porphyrin and chlorophyll metabolism
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K13544  pheophorbidase
GENES       ATH: AT4G16690(MES16)
            ALY: ARALYDRAFT_493208
            CRB: CARUB_v10005512mg
            EUS: EUTSA_v10026004mg
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.1.1.82
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.1.1.82
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.1.1.82
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.1.1.82
///
