ENTRY       EC 3.2.1.171                Enzyme
NAME        rhamnogalacturonan hydrolase;
            rhamnogalacturonase A;
            RGase A;
            RG-hydrolase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Glycosylases;
            Glycosidases, i.e. enzymes that hydrolyse O- and S-glycosyl compounds
SYSNAME     rhamnogalacturonan alpha-D-GalA-(1->2)-alpha-L-Rha hydrolase
REACTION    Endohydrolysis of alpha-D-GalA-(1->2)-alpha-L-Rha glycosidic bond in the rhamnogalacturonan I backbone with initial inversion of anomeric configuration releasing oligosaccharides with beta-D-GalA at the reducing end.
COMMENT     The enzyme is part of the degradation system for rhamnogalacturonan I in Aspergillus aculeatus.
HISTORY     EC 3.2.1.171 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9115442]
  AUTHORS   Petersen TN, Kauppinen S, Larsen S
  TITLE     The crystal structure of rhamnogalacturonase A from Aspergillus aculeatus: a right-handed parallel beta helix.
  JOURNAL   Structure. 5 (1997) 533-44.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus aculeatus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q00001]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7961884]
  AUTHORS   Kofod LV, Kauppinen S, Christgau S, Andersen LN, Heldt-Hansen HP, Dorreich K, Dalboge H
  TITLE     Cloning and characterization of two structurally and functionally divergent rhamnogalacturonases from Aspergillus aculeatus.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 269 (1994) 29182-9.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus aculeatus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q00001]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8720076]
  AUTHORS   Azadi P, O'Neill MA, Bergmann C, Darvill AG, Albersheim P
  TITLE     The backbone of the pectic polysaccharide rhamnogalacturonan I is cleaved by an endohydrolase and an endolyase.
  JOURNAL   Glycobiology. 5 (1995) 783-9.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus aculeatus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q00001]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15299976]
  AUTHORS   Petersen TN, Christgau S, Kofod LV, Kauppinen S, Johnson AH, Larsen S
  TITLE     Crystallization and preliminary X-ray studies of rhamnogalacturonase A from Aspergillus aculeatus.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 53 (1997) 105-7.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:9464254]
  AUTHORS   Pitson SM, Mutter M, van den Broek LA, Voragen AG, Beldman G
  TITLE     Stereochemical course of hydrolysis catalysed by alpha-L-rhamnosyl and alpha-D-galacturonosyl hydrolases from Aspergillus aculeatus.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 242 (1998) 552-9.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus aculeatus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q00001]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.171
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.2.1.171
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.2.1.171
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.171
///
