ENTRY       EC 3.2.1.194                Enzyme
NAME        ginsenosidase type IV
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Glycosylases;
            Glycosidases, i.e. enzymes that hydrolyse O- and S-glycosyl compounds
SYSNAME     protopanaxatriol-type ginsenoside 6-beta-D-glucohydrolase
REACTION    a protopanaxatriol-type ginsenoside with two glycosyl residues at position 6 + 2 H2O = a protopanaxatriol-type ginsenoside with no glycosidic modification at position 6 + D-glucopyranose + a monosaccharide (overall reaction);
            (1a) a protopanaxatriol-type ginsenoside with two glycosyl residues at position 6 + H2O = a protopanaxatriol-type ginsenoside with a single glucosyl at position 6 + a monosaccharide;
            (1b) a protopanaxatriol-type ginsenoside with a single glucosyl at position 6 + H2O = a protopanaxatriol-type ginsenoside with no glycosidic modification at position 6 + D-glucopyranose
SUBSTRATE   protopanaxatriol-type ginsenoside with two glycosyl residues at position 6;
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            protopanaxatriol-type ginsenoside with a single glucosyl at position 6
PRODUCT     protopanaxatriol-type ginsenoside with no glycosidic modification at position 6;
            D-glucopyranose [CPD:C00031];
            monosaccharide;
            protopanaxatriol-type ginsenoside with a single glucosyl at position 6
COMMENT     Ginsenosidase type IV catalyses the sequential hydrolysis of the 6-O-beta-D-(1->2)-glycosidic bond or the 6-O-alpha-D-(1->2)-glycosidic bond in protopanaxatriol-type ginsenosides with a disacchride attached to the C6 position, followed by the hydrolysis of the remaining 6-O-beta-D-glycosidic bond (e.g. ginsenoside Re -> ginsenoside Rg1 -> ginsenoside F1).
HISTORY     EC 3.2.1.194 created 2014
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:22031031]
  AUTHORS   Wang DM, Yu HS, Song JG, Xu YF, Liu CY, Jin FX
  TITLE     A novel ginsenosidase from an Aspergillus strain hydrolyzing 6-O-multi-glycosides of protopanaxatriol-type ginsenosides, named ginsenosidase type IV.
  JOURNAL   J. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 21 (2011) 1057-63.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus sp.
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Wang, D, Yu, H., Song, J., Xu, Y., Jin, F.
  TITLE     Enzyme kinetics of ginsenosidase type IV hydrolyzing 6-O-multi-glycosides of protopanaxatriol type ginsenosides.
  JOURNAL   Process Biochem. 47 (2012) 133-138.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.194
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.2.1.194
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.2.1.194
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.194
///
