ENTRY       EC 3.2.1.146                Enzyme
NAME        beta-galactofuranosidase;
            exo-beta-galactofuranosidase;
            exo-beta-D-galactofuranosidase;
            beta-D-galactofuranosidase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Glycosylases;
            Glycosidases, i.e. enzymes that hydrolyse O- and S-glycosyl compounds
SYSNAME     beta-D-galactofuranoside hydrolase
REACTION    Hydrolysis of terminal non-reducing beta-D-galactofuranosides, releasing galactose
COMMENT     The enzyme from Helminthosporium sacchari detoxifies helminthosporoside, a bis(digalactosyl)terpene produced by this fungus, by releasing its four molecules of bound galactose.
HISTORY     EC 3.2.1.146 created 2001
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:863879]
  AUTHORS   Rietschel-Berst M, Jentoft NH, Rick PD, Pletcher C, Fang F, Gander JE.
  TITLE     Extracellular exo-beta-galactofuranosidase from Penicillium charlesii: isolation, purification, and properties.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 252 (1977) 3219-26.
  ORGANISM  Penicillium charlesii
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Daley, L.S. and Strobel, G.A.
  TITLE     beta-Galactofuranosidase activity in Helminthosporium sacchari and its relationship to the production of helminthosporoside.
  JOURNAL   Plant Sci. Lett. 30 (1983) 145-154.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:2502527]
  AUTHORS   Cousin MA, Notermans S, Hoogerhout P, Van Boom JH.
  TITLE     Detection of beta-galactofuranosidase production by Penicillium and Aspergillus species using 4-nitrophenyl beta-D-galactofuranoside.
  JOURNAL   J. Appl. Bacteriol. 66 (1989) 311-7.
  ORGANISM  Penicillium funiculosum, Penicillium islandicum, Penicillium rubrum, Penicillium tardum, Aspergillus spp.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:10573856]
  AUTHORS   Miletti LC, Marino C, Marino K, de Lederkremer RM, Colli W, Alves MJ.
  TITLE     Immobilized 4-aminophenyl 1-thio-beta-D-galactofuranoside as a matrix for affinity purification of an exo-beta-D-galactofuranosidase.
  JOURNAL   Carbohydr. Res. 320 (1999) 176-82.
  ORGANISM  Penicillium fellutanum
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.146
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.2.1.146
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.2.1.146
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.146
            CAS: 52357-57-0
///
