ENTRY       EC 3.2.1.83                 Enzyme
NAME        kappa-carrageenase;
            kappa-carrageenan 4-beta-D-glycanohydrolase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Glycosylases;
            Glycosidases, i.e. enzymes that hydrolyse O- and S-glycosyl compounds
SYSNAME     kappa-carrageenan 4-beta-D-glycanohydrolase (configuration-retaining)
REACTION    Endohydrolysis of (1->4)-beta-D-linkages between D-galactose 4-sulfate and 3,6-anhydro-D-galactose in kappa-carrageenans
COMMENT     The main products of hydrolysis are neocarrabiose-sulfate and neocarratetraose-sulfate [5]. Unlike EC 3.2.1.157 (iota-carrageenase), but similar to EC 3.2.1.81 (beta-agarase), this enzyme proceeds with retention of the anomeric configuration.
HISTORY     EC 3.2.1.83 created 1972, modified 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:5972647]
  AUTHORS   Weigl J, Yaphe W.
  TITLE     The enzymic hydrolysis of carrageenan by Pseudomonas carrageenovora: purification of a kappa-carrageenase.
  JOURNAL   Can. J. Microbiol. 12 (1966) 939-47.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas carrageenovora
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:1915370]
  AUTHORS   Potin P, Sanseau A, Le Gall Y, Rochas C, Kloareg B.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of a new kappa-carrageenase from a marine Cytophaga-like bacterium.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 201 (1991) 241-7.
  ORGANISM  Delesseria sanguinea
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:7737202]
  AUTHORS   Potin P, Richard C, Barbeyron T, Henrissat B, Gey C, Petillot Y, Forest E, Dideberg O, Rochas C, Kloareg B.
  TITLE     Processing and hydrolytic mechanism of the cgkA-encoded kappa-carrageenase of Alteromonas carrageenovora.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 228 (1995) 971-5.
  ORGANISM  Alteromonas carrageenovora
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:10089334]
  AUTHORS   Michel G, Barbeyron T, Flament D, Vernet T, Kloareg B, Dideberg O.
  TITLE     Expression, purification, crystallization and preliminary x-ray analysis of the kappa-carrageenase from Pseudoalteromonas carrageenovora.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 55 (1999) 918-20.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas carrageenovora
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:11435116]
  AUTHORS   Michel G, Chantalat L, Duee E, Barbeyron T, Henrissat B, Kloareg B, Dideberg O.
  TITLE     The kappa-carrageenase of P. carrageenovora features a tunnel-shaped active site: a novel insight in the evolution of Clan-B glycoside hydrolases.
  JOURNAL   Structure. 9 (2001) 513-25.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas carrageenovora
  SEQUENCE  [up:P43478]
ORTHOLOGY   K05990  kappa-carrageenase
GENES       RBA: RB2702
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.83
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.2.1.83
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.2.1.83
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.83
            CAS: 37288-59-8
///
