ENTRY       EC 3.2.1.81                 Enzyme
NAME        beta-agarase;
            agarase (ambiguous);
            AgaA;
            AgaB;
            endo-beta-agarase;
            agarose 3-glycanohydrolase (incorrect)
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Glycosylases;
            Glycosidases, i.e. enzymes that hydrolyse O- and S-glycosyl compounds
SYSNAME     agarose 4-glycanohydrolase
REACTION    Hydrolysis of (1->4)-beta-D-galactosidic linkages in agarose, giving the tetramer as the predominant product
COMMENT     Also acts on porphyran, but more slowly [1]. This enzyme cleaves the beta-(1->4) linkages of agarose in a random manner with retention of the anomeric-bond configuration, producing beta-anomers that give rise progressively to alpha-anomers when mutarotation takes place [6]. The end products of hydrolysis are neoagarotetraose and neoagarohexaose in the case of AgaA from the marine bacterium Zobellia galactanivorans, and neoagarotetraose and neoagarobiose in the case of AgaB [6].
HISTORY     EC 3.2.1.81 created 1972, modified 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:5386190]
  AUTHORS   Duckworth M, Turvey JR.
  TITLE     The action of a bacterial agarase on agarose, porphyran and alkali-treated porphyran.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 113 (1969) 687-92.
  ORGANISM  Cytophaga sp.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12970344]
  AUTHORS   Allouch J, Jam M, Helbert W, Barbeyron T, Kloareg B, Henrissat B, Czjzek M.
  TITLE     The three-dimensional structures of two beta-agarases.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 278 (2003) 47171-80.
  ORGANISM  Zobellia galactanivorans
  SEQUENCE  [zga:zobellia_4203 zobellia_3573]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:15170112]
  AUTHORS   Ohta Y, Nogi Y, Miyazaki M, Li Z, Hatada Y, Ito S, Horikoshi K.
  TITLE     Enzymatic properties and nucleotide and amino acid sequences of a thermostable beta-agarase from the novel marine isolate, JAMB-A94.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 68 (2004) 1073-81.
  ORGANISM  Microbulbifer salipaludis
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15088129]
  AUTHORS   Ohta Y, Hatada Y, Nogi Y, Miyazaki M, Li Z, Akita M, Hidaka Y, Goda S, Ito S, Horikoshi K.
  TITLE     Enzymatic properties and nucleotide and amino acid sequences of a thermostable beta-agarase from a novel species of deep-sea Microbulbifer.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 64 (2004) 505-14.
  ORGANISM  Microbulbifer elongataus, Microbulbifer salipaludis, Microbulbifer elongataus, Microbulbifer hydrolyticus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:8517750]
  AUTHORS   Sugano Y, Terada I, Arita M, Noma M, Matsumoto T.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of a new agarase from a marine bacterium, Vibrio sp. strain JT0107.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 59 (1993) 1549-54.
  ORGANISM  Undaria pinnatiJida, Laminaria sp., Vibrio sp.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:15456406]
  AUTHORS   Jam M, Flament D, Allouch J, Potin P, Thion L, Kloareg B, Czjzek M, Helbert W, Michel G, Barbeyron T.
  TITLE     The endo-beta-agarases AgaA and AgaB from the marine bacterium Zobellia galactanivorans: two paralogue enzymes with different molecular organizations and catalytic behaviours.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 385 (2005) 703-13.
  ORGANISM  Zobellia galactanivorans
  SEQUENCE  [zga:zobellia_4203 zobellia_3573]
ORTHOLOGY   K01219  agarase
GENES       PAT: Patl_1904 Patl_1971 Patl_2341 Patl_2640 Patl_2642
            SDE: Sde_1175(aga16B) Sde_1176(aga50A) Sde_2644(aga50B) Sde_2650(aga86C) Sde_2655(aga86E)
            GAG: Glaag_2339
            RPB: RPB_3029
            RPD: RPD_2419
            RPE: RPE_4620
            SCO: SCO3471(dagA)
            CAA: Caka_0493
            RBA: RB3421(agrA)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.81
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.2.1.81
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.2.1.81
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.81
            CAS: 37288-57-6
///
