ENTRY       EC 3.2.1.129                Enzyme
NAME        endo-alpha-sialidase;
            endo-N-acylneuraminidase;
            endoneuraminidase;
            endo-N-acetylneuraminidase;
            poly(alpha-2,8-sialosyl) endo-N-acetylneuraminidase;
            poly(alpha-2,8-sialoside) alpha-2,8-sialosylhydrolase;
            endosialidase;
            endo-N
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Glycosylases;
            Glycosidases, i.e. enzymes that hydrolyse O- and S-glycosyl compounds
SYSNAME     polysialoside (2->8)-alpha-sialosylhydrolase
REACTION    Endohydrolysis of (2->8)-alpha-sialosyl linkages in oligo- or poly(sialic) acids
COMMENT     Although the name endo-N-acetylneuraminidase has also been used for this enzyme, this is misleading since its activity is not restricted to acetylated substrates. An exo-alpha-sialidase activity is listed as EC 3.2.1.18 exo-alpha-sialidase. See also EC 4.2.2.15 anhydrosialidase.
HISTORY     EC 3.2.1.129 created 1990, modified 1999
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3968060]
  AUTHORS   Finne J, Makela PH.
  TITLE     Cleavage of the polysialosyl units of brain glycoproteins by a bacteriophage endosialidase. Involvement of a long oligosaccharide segment in molecular interactions of polysialic acid.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 260 (1985) 1265-70.
  ORGANISM  bacteriophage PK1A
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:3546309]
  AUTHORS   Hallenbeck PC, Vimr ER, Yu F, Bassler B, Troy FA.
  TITLE     Purification and properties of a bacteriophage-induced endo-N-acetylneuraminidase specific for poly-alpha-2,8-sialosyl carbohydrate units.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 262 (1987) 3553-61.
  ORGANISM  bacteriophage K1F
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:3142874]
  AUTHORS   Kitajima K, Inoue S, Inoue Y, Troy FA.
  TITLE     Use of a bacteriophage-derived endo-N-acetylneuraminidase and an equine antipolysialyl antibody to characterize the polysialyl residues in salmonid fish egg polysialoglycoproteins. Substrate and immunospecificity studies.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 263 (1988) 18269-76.
  ORGANISM  bacteriophage PK1A
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:7109038]
  AUTHORS   Kwiatkowski B, Boschek B, Thiele H, Stirm S.
  TITLE     Endo-N-acetylneuraminidase associated with bacteriophage particles.
  JOURNAL   J. Virol. 43 (1982) 697-704.
  ORGANISM  bacteriophage PHI1.2
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:2778882]
  AUTHORS   Pelkonen S, Pelkonen J, Finne J.
  TITLE     Common cleavage pattern of polysialic acid by bacteriophage endosialidases of different properties and origins.
  JOURNAL   J. Virol. 63 (1989) 4409-16.
  ORGANISM  bacteriophage PK1A, bacteriophage PK1E
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:3894684]
  AUTHORS   Tomlinson S, Taylor PW.
  TITLE     Neuraminidase associated with coliphage E that specifically depolymerizes the Escherichia coli K1 capsular polysaccharide.
  JOURNAL   J. Virol. 55 (1985) 374-8.
  ORGANISM  bacteriophage E
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:1883340]
  AUTHORS   Cabezas JA.
  TITLE     Some questions and suggestions on the type references of the official nomenclature (IUB) for sialidase(s) and endosialidase.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 278 ( Pt 1) (1991) 311-2.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.129
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.2.1.129
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.2.1.129
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.129
            CAS: 91195-87-8
///
