ENTRY       EC 3.2.1.193                Enzyme
NAME        ginsenosidase type I
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Glycosylases;
            Glycosidases, i.e. enzymes that hydrolyse O- and S-glycosyl compounds
SYSNAME     ginsenoside glucohydrolase
REACTION    (1) a protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with two glucosyl residues at position 3 + H2O = a protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with one glucosyl residue at position 3 + D-glucopyranose;
            (2) a protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with one glucosyl residue at position 3 + H2O = a protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with no glycosidic modifications at position 3 + D-glucopyranose;
            (3) a protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with two glycosyl residues at position 20 + H2O = a protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with a single glucosyl residue at position 20 + a monosaccharide
SUBSTRATE   protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with two glucosyl residues at position 3;
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with one glucosyl residue at position 3;
            protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with two glycosyl residues at position 20
PRODUCT     protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with one glucosyl residue at position 3;
            D-glucopyranose [CPD:C00031];
            protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with no glycosidic modifications at position 3;
            protopanaxadiol-type ginsenoside with a single glucosyl residue at position 20;
            monosaccharide
COMMENT     Ginsenosidase type I is slightly activated by Mg2+ or Ca2+ [1]. The enzyme hydrolyses the 3-O-beta-D-(1->2)-glucosidic bond, the 3-O-beta-D-glucopyranosyl bond and the 20-O-beta-D-(1->6)-glycosidic bond of protopanaxadiol-type ginsenosides. It usually leaves a single glucosyl residue attached at position 20 and one or no glucosyl residues at position 3. Starting with a ginsenoside that is glycosylated at both positions (e.g. ginsenoside Rb1, Rb2, Rb3, Rc or Rd), the most common products are ginsenoside F2 and ginsenoside C-K, with low amounts of ginsenoside Rh2.
HISTORY     EC 3.2.1.193 created 2014
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:17268094]
  AUTHORS   Yu H, Zhang C, Lu M, Sun F, Fu Y, Jin F
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of new special ginsenosidase hydrolyzing multi-glycisides of protopanaxadiol ginsenosides, ginsenosidase type I.
  JOURNAL   Chem. Pharm. Bull. (Tokyo). 55 (2007) 231-5.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus sp.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.193
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.2.1.193
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.2.1.193
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.193
///
