ENTRY       EC 3.2.1.157                Enzyme
NAME        iota-carrageenase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Glycosylases;
            Glycosidases, i.e. enzymes that hydrolyse O- and S-glycosyl compounds
SYSNAME     iota-carrageenan 4-beta-D-glycanohydrolase (configuration-inverting)
REACTION    Endohydrolysis of (1->4)-beta-D-linkages between D-galactose 4-sulfate and 3,6-anhydro-D-galactose-2-sulfate in iota-carrageenans
COMMENT     The main products of hydrolysis are iota-neocarratetraose sulfate and iota-neocarrahexaose sulfate. iota-Neocarraoctaose is the shortest substrate oligomer that can be cleaved. Unlike EC 3.2.1.81, beta-agarase and EC 3.2.1.83, kappa-carrageenase, this enzyme proceeds with inversion of the anomeric configuration. iota-Carrageenan differs from kappa-carrageenan by possessing a sulfo group on O-2 of the 3,6-anhydro-D-galactose residues, in addition to that present in the kappa-compound on O-4 of the D-galactose residues.
HISTORY     EC 3.2.1.157 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10934194]
  AUTHORS   Barbeyron T, Michel G, Potin P, Henrissat B, Kloareg B.
  TITLE     iota-Carrageenases constitute a novel family of glycoside hydrolases, unrelated to that of kappa-carrageenases.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 275 (2000) 35499-505.
  ORGANISM  Alteromonas fortis, Zobellia galactanovorans
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9F5I8 Q9F284]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:11493601]
  AUTHORS   Michel G, Chantalat L, Fanchon E, Henrissat B, Kloareg B, Dideberg O.
  TITLE     The iota-carrageenase of Alteromonas fortis. A beta-helix fold-containing enzyme for the degradation of a highly polyanionic polysaccharide.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 276 (2001) 40202-9.
  ORGANISM  Alteromonas fortis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9F5I8]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:14623184]
  AUTHORS   Michel G, Helbert W, Kahn R, Dideberg O, Kloareg B.
  TITLE     The structural bases of the processive degradation of iota-carrageenan, a main cell wall polysaccharide of red algae.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 334 (2003) 421-33.
  ORGANISM  Alteromonas fortis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9F5I8]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.157
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.2.1.157
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.2.1.157
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.157
            CAS: 50936-37-3
///
