ENTRY       EC 3.2.1.165                Enzyme
NAME        exo-1,4-beta-D-glucosaminidase;
            CsxA;
            GlcNase;
            exochitosanase;
            GlmA;
            exo-beta-D-glucosaminidase;
            chitosan exo-1,4-beta-D-glucosaminidase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Glycosylases;
            Glycosidases, i.e. enzymes that hydrolyse O- and S-glycosyl compounds
SYSNAME     chitosan exo-(1->4)-beta-D-glucosaminidase
REACTION    Hydrolysis of chitosan or chitosan oligosaccharides to remove successive D-glucosamine residues from the non-reducing termini [RN:R06225 R08715]
ALL_REAC    R06225(G) R08715 > R01966 R06225(G)
COMMENT     Chitosan is a partially or totally N-deacetylated chitin derivative that is found in the cell walls of some phytopathogenic fungi and comprises D-glucosamine residues with a variable content of GlcNAc residues [4]. Acts specifically on chitooligosaccharides and chitosan, having maximal activity on chitotetraose, chitopentaose and their corresponding alcohols [1]. The enzyme can degrade GlcN-GlcNAc but not GlcNAc-GlcNAc [3]. A member of the glycoside hydrolase family 2 (GH-2) [4].
HISTORY     EC 3.2.1.165 created 2008
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:2351651]
  AUTHORS   Nanjo F, Katsumi R, Sakai K.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of an exo-beta-D-glucosaminidase, a novel type of enzyme, from Nocardia orientalis.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 265 (1990) 10088-94.
  ORGANISM  Amycolatopsis orientalis
  SEQUENCE  [aoi:AORI_5124]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16349528]
  AUTHORS   Nogawa M, Takahashi H, Kashiwagi A, Ohshima K, Okada H, Morikawa Y.
  TITLE     Purification and Characterization of Exo-beta-d-Glucosaminidase from a Cellulolytic Fungus, Trichoderma reesei PC-3-7.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 64 (1998) 890-895.
  ORGANISM  Trichoderma reesei
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q4R1C4]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16877749]
  AUTHORS   Fukamizo T, Fleury A, Cote N, Mitsutomi M, Brzezinski R.
  TITLE     Exo-beta-D-glucosaminidase from Amycolatopsis orientalis: catalytic residues, sugar recognition specificity, kinetics, and synergism.
  JOURNAL   Glycobiology. 16 (2006) 1064-72.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16316314]
  AUTHORS   Cote N, Fleury A, Dumont-Blanchette E, Fukamizo T, Mitsutomi M, Brzezinski R.
  TITLE     Two exo-beta-D-glucosaminidases/exochitosanases from actinomycetes define a new subfamily within family 2 of glycoside hydrolases.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 394 (2006) 675-86.
  ORGANISM  Amycolatopsis orientalis, Streptomyces avermitilis
  SEQUENCE  [aoi:AORI_5124] [sma:SAV_1223]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:16636831]
  AUTHORS   Ike M, Isami K, Tanabe Y, Nogawa M, Ogasawara W, Okada H, Morikawa Y.
  TITLE     Cloning and heterologous expression of the exo-beta-D-glucosaminidase-encoding gene (gls93) from a filamentous fungus, Trichoderma reesei PC-3-7.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 72 (2006) 687-95.
  ORGANISM  Trichoderma reesei
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q4R1C4]
PATHWAY     ec00520  Amino sugar and nucleotide sugar metabolism
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K15855  exo-1,4-beta-D-glucosaminidase
GENES       NCR: NCU09042
            SMP: SMAC_05835
            PAN: PODANSg2615
            TTT: THITE_2049779
            MTM: MYCTH_54601
            MGR: MGG_05864
            FGR: FG02314.1
            TRE: TRIREDRAFT_77299
            ANI: AN2824.2
            AFM: AFUA_4G00390
            AOR: AOR_1_2480154(AO090003001410)
            ANG: ANI_1_2638014(An01g06630)
            AFV: AFLA_024260
            ACT: ACLA_078510
            NFI: NFIA_045250
            PCS: Pc12g13420
            PBL: PAAG_02684
            URE: UREG_02485
            ABE: ARB_07888
            TVE: TRV_00950
            PNO: SNOG_15490
            PTE: PTT_07728
            DJI: CH75_09920
            HPK: Hprae_1313
            MSA: Mycsm_03422
            MCB: Mycch_2879
            SRT: Srot_2920
            SMA: SAV_1223
            SVL: Strvi_3876
            SBH: SBI_00935(bga4)
            SHY: SHJG_2189
            SHO: SHJGH_1954
            SCI: B446_04595
            SRC: M271_06075
            AMD: AMED_6094
            AMN: RAM_31240
            AMM: AMES_6008
            AMZ: B737_6008
            AOI: AORI_5124
            SESP: BN6_82410(csxA)
            KAL: KALB_8547 KALB_8660
            CAI: Caci_7497
            ABA: Acid345_1359
            ACA: ACP_1263
            TRS: Terro_3039
            SUS: Acid_7527
            GBA: J421_6020
            PRU: PRU_0394
            SHG: Sph21_1908
            RSI: Runsl_2770
            ZPR: ZPR_2497
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.165
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.2.1.165
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.2.1.165
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.2.1.165
///
