ENTRY       EC 3.2.2.28                 Enzyme
NAME        double-stranded uracil-DNA glycosylase;
            Mug;
            double-strand uracil-DNA glycosylase;
            Dug;
            dsUDG;
            double-stranded DNA specific UDG;
            dsDNA specific UDG;
            UdgB (ambiguous);
            G:T/U mismatch-specific DNA glycosylase;
            UDG (ambiguous)
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Glycosylases;
            Hydrolysing N-glycosyl compounds
SYSNAME     uracil-double-stranded DNA deoxyribohydrolase (uracil-releasing)
REACTION    Specifically hydrolyses mismatched double-stranded DNA and polynucleotides, releasing free uracil
COMMENT     No activity on DNA containing a T/G mispair or single-stranded DNA containing either a site-specific uracil or 3,N4-ethenocytosine residue [2], significant role for double-stranded uracil-DNA glycosylase in mutation avoidance in non-dividing E. coli [3]. Uracil-DNA glycosylases are widespread enzymes that are found in all living organisms. Uracil-DNA glycosylase (EC 3.2.2.27) and EC 3.2.2.28 form a central part of the DNA-repair machinery since they initiate the DNA base-excision repair pathway by hydrolysing the N-glycosidic bond between uracil and the deoxyribose sugar thereby catalysing the removal of mis-incorporated uracil from DNA.
HISTORY     EC 3.2.2.28 created 2009
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10581234]
  AUTHORS   Barrett TE, Scharer OD, Savva R, Brown T, Jiricny J, Verdine GL, Pearl LH
  TITLE     Crystal structure of a thwarted mismatch glycosylase DNA repair complex.
  JOURNAL   EMBO. J. 18 (1999) 6599-609.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b3068]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:10956012]
  AUTHORS   Sung JS, Mosbaugh DW
  TITLE     Escherichia coli double-strand uracil-DNA glycosylase: involvement in uracil-mediated DNA base excision repair and stimulation of activity by endonuclease IV.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 39 (2000) 10224-35.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11555290]
  AUTHORS   Mokkapati SK, Fernandez de Henestrosa AR, Bhagwat AS
  TITLE     Escherichia coli DNA glycosylase Mug: a growth-regulated enzyme required for mutation avoidance in stationary-phase cells.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 41 (2001) 1101-11.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b3068]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.2.2.28
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.2.2.28
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.2.2.28
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.2.2.28
///
