ENTRY       EC 3.3.2.10                 Enzyme
NAME        soluble epoxide hydrolase;
            epoxide hydrase (ambiguous);
            epoxide hydratase (ambiguous);
            arene-oxide hydratase (ambiguous);
            aryl epoxide hydrase (ambiguous);
            trans-stilbene oxide hydrolase;
            sEH;
            cytosolic epoxide hydrolase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on ether bonds;
            Ether hydrolases
SYSNAME     epoxide hydrolase
REACTION    an epoxide + H2O = a glycol [RN:R02822]
ALL_REAC    R02822 > R05842 R07108 R07109 R07110 R07111
SUBSTRATE   epoxide [CPD:C00722];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     glycol [CPD:C15588]
COMMENT     Catalyses the hydrolysis of trans-substituted epoxides, such as trans-stilbene oxide, as well as various aliphatic epoxides derived from fatty-acid metabolism [7]. It is involved in the metabolism of arachidonic epoxides (epoxyicosatrienoic acids; EETs) and linoleic acid epoxides. The EETs, which are endogenous chemical mediators, act at the vascular, renal and cardiac levels to regulate blood pressure [4,5]. The enzyme from mammals is a bifunctional enzyme: the C-terminal domain exhibits epoxide-hydrolase activity and the N-terminal domain has the activity of EC 3.1.3.76, lipid-phosphate phosphatase [1,2]. Like EC 3.3.2.9, microsomal epoxide hydrolase, it is probable that the reaction involves the formation of an hydroxyalkyl---enzyme intermediate [4,6]. The enzyme can also use leukotriene A4, the substrate of EC 3.3.2.6, leukotriene-A4 hydrolase, but it forms 5,6-dihydroxy-7,9,11,14-icosatetraenoic acid rather than leukotriene B4 as the product [9,10]. In vertebrates, five epoxide-hydrolase enzymes have been identified to date: EC 3.3.2.6 (leukotriene-A4 hydrolase), EC 3.3.2.7 (hepoxilin-epoxide hydrolase), EC 3.3.2.9 (microsomal epoxide hydrolase), EC 3.3.2.10 (soluble epoxide hydrolase) and EC 3.3.2.11 (cholesterol 5,6-oxide hydrolase) [7].
HISTORY     EC 3.3.2.10 created 2006 (EC 3.3.2.3 part-incorporated 2006)
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:12574510]
  AUTHORS   Newman JW, Morisseau C, Harris TR, Hammock BD.
  TITLE     The soluble epoxide hydrolase encoded by EPXH2 is a bifunctional enzyme with novel lipid phosphate phosphatase activity.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 100 (2003) 1558-63.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:2053]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12574508]
  AUTHORS   Cronin A, Mowbray S, Durk H, Homburg S, Fleming I, Fisslthaler B, Oesch F, Arand M.
  TITLE     The N-terminal domain of mammalian soluble epoxide hydrolase is a phosphatase.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 100 (2003) 1552-7.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Rattus norvegicus
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:2053] [rno:65030]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:4584115]
  AUTHORS   Oesch F.
  TITLE     Mammalian epoxide hydrases: inducible enzymes catalysing the inactivation of carcinogenic and cytotoxic metabolites derived from aromatic and olefinic compounds.
  JOURNAL   Xenobiotica. 3 (1973) 305-40.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Macaca mulatta, Mus musculus, Rattus norvegicus, Sus scofa, Cavia porcellus, Oryctolagus cuniculus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15822179]
  AUTHORS   Morisseau C, Hammock BD.
  TITLE     Epoxide hydrolases: mechanisms, inhibitor designs, and biological roles.
  JOURNAL   Annu. Rev. Pharmacol. Toxicol. 45 (2005) 311-33.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Mus musculus, Rattus norvegicus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:11090543]
  AUTHORS   Yu Z, Xu F, Huse LM, Morisseau C, Draper AJ, Newman JW, Parker C, Graham L, Engler MM, Hammock BD, Zeldin DC, Kroetz DL.
  TITLE     Soluble epoxide hydrolase regulates hydrolysis of vasoactive epoxyeicosatrienoic acids.
  JOURNAL   Circ. Res. 87 (2000) 992-8.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Mus musculus, Rattus norvegicus
REFERENCE   6
  AUTHORS   Lacourciere, G.M. and Armstrong, R.N.
  TITLE     The catalytic mechanism of microsomal epoxide hydrolase involves an ester intermediate.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 115 (1993) 10466-10456.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:11154734]
  AUTHORS   Fretland AJ, Omiecinski CJ.
  TITLE     Epoxide hydrolases: biochemistry and molecular biology.
  JOURNAL   Chem. Biol. Interact. 129 (2000) 41-59.
  ORGANISM  Rattus norvegicus
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:7840649]
  AUTHORS   Zeldin DC, Wei S, Falck JR, Hammock BD, Snapper JR, Capdevila JH.
  TITLE     Metabolism of epoxyeicosatrienoic acids by cytosolic epoxide hydrolase: substrate structural determinants of asymmetric catalysis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 316 (1995) 443-51.
  ORGANISM  Rattus norvegicus
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:3009453]
  AUTHORS   Haeggstrom J, Meijer J, Radmark O.
  TITLE     Leukotriene A4. Enzymatic conversion into 5,6-dihydroxy-7,9,11,14-eicosatetraenoic acid by mouse liver cytosolic epoxide hydrolase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 261 (1986) 6332-7.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
REFERENCE   10 [PMID:15748653]
  AUTHORS   Newman JW, Morisseau C, Hammock BD.
  TITLE     Epoxide hydrolases: their roles and interactions with lipid metabolism.
  JOURNAL   Prog. Lipid. Res. 44 (2005) 1-51.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Macaca mulatta, Mus musculus, Rattus norvegicus, Sus scofa, Equus caballus, Arabidopsis thaliana, Zea mays, Ananas comosus, Euphorbia lagascae, Oryctolagus cuniculus, Mesocricetus sp., Papio sp., Glycine max, Nicotiana tabacum, Brassica napus, Oryza sativa, Solanum tuberosum, Triticum aestivum, Citrus jambhiri, Spinacia oleracea, Malus pumila, Ricinus communis, Vicia sativa, Apium graveolens, Oncorhynchus mykiss, Oryzias latipes, Pimphales promelas, Stenotomus chrysops
PATHWAY     ec00590  Arachidonic acid metabolism
            ec00625  Chloroalkane and chloroalkene degradation
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01120  Microbial metabolism in diverse environments
ORTHOLOGY   K08726  soluble epoxide hydrolase
GENES       HSA: 2053(EPHX2)
            PTR: 464074(EPHX2)
            PPS: 100990932(EPHX2)
            GGO: 101136750(EPHX2)
            PON: 100172736(EPHX2)
            MCC: 712926(EPHX2)
            MCF: 102134633(EPHX2)
            MMU: 13850(Ephx2)
            RNO: 65030(Ephx2)
            CGE: 100757328(Ephx2)
            HGL: 101715352(Ephx2)
            TUP: 102480725(EPHX2)
            CFA: 477373(EPHX2)
            AML: 100483572(EPHX2)
            FCA: 101092355(EPHX2)
            PTG: 102957184(EPHX2)
            BTA: 511716(EPHX2) 785508
            BOM: 102267808(EPHX2)
            PHD: 102326909(EPHX2)
            CHX: 102185835(EPHX2)
            SSC: 414425(EPHX2)
            CFR: 102517269(EPHX2)
            ECB: 100060414(EPHX2)
            MYB: 102255588(EPHX2)
            MYD: 102755564(EPHX2)
            PALE: 102886924(EPHX2)
            MDO: 100030580(EPHX2)
            SHR: 100931196 100931720
            OAA: 100093187(EPHX2)
            GGA: 421999(EPHX2)
            MGP: 100550075
            FAB: 101820851(EPHX2)
            PHI: 102113903
            FPG: 101922601(EPHX2)
            FCH: 102047869(EPHX2)
            CLV: 102084991(EPHX2)
            ASN: 102382847(EPHX2)
            PSS: 102463793(EPHX2)
            CMY: 102944771(EPHX2)
            ACS: 100564154
            XLA: 447032(ephx2)
            XTR: 448759(ephx2)
            DRE: 494099(ephx2)
            TRU: 101078765
            MZE: 101483599
            OLA: 101157276
            XMA: 102235090
            BFO: BRAFLDRAFT_88467 BRAFLDRAFT_88468
            CIN: 100180417
            SPU: 590376 590472(EH1) 752510(eh2)
            NVE: NEMVE_v1g237970
            TAD: TRIADDRAFT_30313 TRIADDRAFT_59995 TRIADDRAFT_60010 TRIADDRAFT_60079 TRIADDRAFT_64238
            CIC: CICLE_v10001881mg
            YLI: YALI0A01441g YALI0C23224g YALI0E19899g
            NCR: NCU02924
            MGR: MGG_05826
            PNO: SNOG_14994
            PTE: PTT_13711
            LBC: LACBIDRAFT_303899 LACBIDRAFT_311540(LbEPHX1)
            CCI: CC1G_14690
            SCM: SCHCODRAFT_12753 SCHCODRAFT_62514
            UMA: UM04063.1
            PGR: PGTG_00491 PGTG_05962 PGTG_05973
            ACAN: ACA1_322160
            PIF: PITG_11920 PITG_11921 PITG_11922 PITG_15955 PITG_15956
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.3.2.10
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.3.2.10
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.3.2.10
            UM-BBD (Biocatalysis/Biodegradation Database): 3.3.2.10
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.3.2.10
            CAS: 9048-63-9
///
