ENTRY       EC 3.4.23.18                Enzyme
NAME        aspergillopepsin I;
            Aspergillus acid protease;
            Aspergillus acid proteinase;
            Aspergillus aspartic proteinase;
            Aspergillus awamori acid proteinase;
            Aspergillus carboxyl proteinase;
            (see also Comments);
            carboxyl proteinase;
            Aspergillus kawachii aspartic proteinase;
            Aspergillus saitoi acid proteinase;
            pepsin-type aspartic proteinase;
            Aspergillus niger acid proteinase;
            sumizyme AP;
            proctase P;
            denapsin;
            denapsin XP 271;
            proctase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Aspartic endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of proteins with broad specificity. Generally favours hydrophobic residues in P1 and P1', but also accepts Lys in P1, which leads to activation of trypsinogen. Does not clot milk
COMMENT     Found in a variety of Aspergillus species (imperfect fungi): Aspergillus awamori (awamorin, aspergillopepsin A: [8]), A. foetidus (aspergillopepsin F: [6]), A. fumigatus [7], A. kawachii [9], A. niger (proteinase B, proctase B: [2,4]), A. oryzae (trypsinogen kinase: [3,10]), A. saitoi (aspergillopeptidase A: [10]), and A. sojae [5,10]. In peptidase family A1 (pepsin A family). Formerly included in EC 3.4.23.6
HISTORY     EC 3.4.23.18 created 1992 (EC 3.4.23.6 created 1961 as EC 3.4.4.17, transferred 1972 to EC 3.4.23.6, modified 1981 [EC 3.4.23.7, EC 3.4.23.8, EC 3.4.23.9, EC 3.4.23.10, EC 3.4.99.1, EC 3.4.99.15 and EC 3.4.99.25 all created 1972 and incorporated 1978], part incorporated 1992)
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:4565799]
  AUTHORS   Kovaleva GG, Shimanskaya MP, Stepanov VM.
  TITLE     The site of diazoacetyl inhibitor attachment to acid proteinase of Aspergillus awamori--an analog of penicillopepsin and pepsin.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 49 (1972) 1075-81.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus awamori
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:4593189]
  AUTHORS   Morihara K, Oka T.
  TITLE     Comparative specificity of microbial acid proteinases for synthetic peptides. 3. Relationship with their trypsinogen activating ability.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 157 (1973) 561-72.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:239702]
  AUTHORS   Davidson R, Gertler A, Hofmann T.
  TITLE     Aspergillus oryzae acid proteinase. Purification and properties, and formation of pi-chymotrypsin.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 147 (1975) 45-53.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus oryzae
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12156]
  AUTHORS   Chang WJ, Horiuchi S, Takahashi K, Yamasaki M, Yamada Y.
  TITLE     The structure and function of acid proteases. VI. Effects of acid protease-specific inhibitors on the acid proteases from Aspergillus niger var. macrosporus.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 80 (1976) 975-81.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus niger
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:21699]
  AUTHORS   Tanaka N, Takeuchi M, Ichishima E.
  TITLE     Purification of an acid proteinase from Aspergillus saitoi and determination of peptide bond specificity.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 485 (1977) 406-16.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus saitoi
REFERENCE   6
  AUTHORS   Ostoslavskaya, V.I., Kotlova, E.K., Stepanov, V.M., Rudenskaya, G.H., Baratova, L.A. and Belyanova, L.P.
  TITLE     Aspergillopepsin F-A carboxylic proteinase from Aspergillus foetidus.
  JOURNAL   Bioorg. Khim. 5 (1976) 595-603.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:7024192]
  AUTHORS   Panneerselvam M, Dhar SC.
  TITLE     Studies on the peptide bond specificity and the essential groups of an acid proteinase from Aspergillus fumigatus.
  JOURNAL   Ital. J. Biochem. 30 (1981) 207-16.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus foetidus
REFERENCE   8
  AUTHORS   Ostoslavskaya, V.I., Revina, L.P., Kotlova, E.K., Surova, I.A., Levin, E.D., Timokhima, E.A. and Stepanov, V.M.
  TITLE     The primary structure of aspergillopepsin A, aspartic proteinase from Aspergillus awamori. IV. Amino acid sequence of the enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Bioorg. Khim. 12 (1986) 1030-1047.
REFERENCE   9
  AUTHORS   Yagi, F., Fan, J., Tadera, K. and Kobayashi, A.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of carboxyl proteinase from Aspergillus kawachii.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 50 (1986) 1029-1033.
REFERENCE   10
  AUTHORS   Majima, E., Oda, K., Murao, S. and Ichishima, E.
  TITLE     Comparative study on the specificities of several fungal aspartic and acidic proteinases towards the tetradecapeptide of a renin substrate.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 52 (1988) 787-793.
ORTHOLOGY   K06004  aspergillopepsin I
GENES       NCR: NCU00994
            PAN: PODANSg3853
            MGR: MGG_02898
            FGR: FG07775.1
            SSL: SS1G_03181
            BFU: BC1G_07521
            ANI: AN6888.2
            AFM: AFUA_2G15950 AFUA_3G01220 AFUA_5G13300
            AOR: AOR_1_830094(AO090120000474)
            ANG: ANI_1_654124(An14g04710)
            AFV: AFLA_094450
            ACT: ACLA_016280
            NFI: NFIA_073740
            PCS: Pc21g03510
            URE: UREG_04254
            ABE: ARB_05728
            TVE: TRV_03007
            PNO: SNOG_02018
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.18
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.23.18
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.23.18
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.18
            CAS: 9025-49-4
///
