ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.121               Enzyme
NAME        Lys-Lys/Arg-Xaa endopeptidase;
            ASP (Aeromonas sobria)-type peptidase;
            Aeromonas extracellular serine protease
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Cleavage of -Lys-Lys! and -Lys-Arg! bonds.
COMMENT     The enzyme is a serine peptidase, which has been shown to cleave prothrombin and prekallikrein. It hydrolyses the complement component C5 releasing complement component C5a.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.121 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:19654332]
  AUTHORS   Kobayashi H, Utsunomiya H, Yamanaka H, Sei Y, Katunuma N, Okamoto K, Tsuge H
  TITLE     Structural basis for the kexin-like serine protease from Aeromonas sobria as sepsis-causing factor.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 284 (2009) 27655-63.
  ORGANISM  Aeromonas sobria
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9L5A4]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:18067862]
  AUTHORS   Nitta H, Kobayashi H, Irie A, Baba H, Okamoto K, Imamura T
  TITLE     Activation of prothrombin by ASP, a serine protease released from Aeromonas sobria.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 581 (2007) 5935-9.
  ORGANISM  Aeromonas sobria
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16487335]
  AUTHORS   Kobayashi H, Takahashi E, Oguma K, Fujii Y, Yamanaka H, Negishi T, Arimoto-Kobayashi S, Tsuji T, Okamoto K
  TITLE     Cleavage specificity of the serine protease of Aeromonas sobria, a member of the  kexin family of subtilases.
  JOURNAL   FEMS. Microbiol. Lett. 256 (2006) 165-70.
  ORGANISM  Aeromonas sobria
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:18462393]
  AUTHORS   Imamura T, Nitta H, Wada Y, Kobayashi H, Okamoto K
  TITLE     Impaired plasma clottability induction through fibrinogen degradation by ASP, a serine protease released from Aeromonas sobria.
  JOURNAL   FEMS. Microbiol. Lett. 284 (2008) 35-42.
  ORGANISM  Aeromonas sobria
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:18714034]
  AUTHORS   Nitta H, Imamura T, Wada Y, Irie A, Kobayashi H, Okamoto K, Baba H
  TITLE     Production of C5a by ASP, a serine protease released from Aeromonas sobria.
  JOURNAL   J. Immunol. 181 (2008) 3602-8.
  ORGANISM  Aeromonas sobria
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.121
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.121
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.121
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.121
///
