ENTRY       EC 3.4.24.72                Enzyme
NAME        fibrolase;
            fibrinolytic proteinase;
            Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix metalloproteinase;
            Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix venom metalloproteinase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Metalloendopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of -Ala14!Leu- in insulin B chain and -Lys413!Leu- in Aalpha-chain of fibrinogen
COMMENT     A 23-kDa, non-hemorrhagic enzyme from the venom of the southern copperhead snake (Agkistrodon contortix contortix). In peptidase family M12 (astacin family)
HISTORY     EC 3.4.24.72 created 1996
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3232124]
  AUTHORS   Retzios AD, Markland FS Jr.
  TITLE     A direct-acting fibrinolytic enzyme from the venom of Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix: effects on various components of the human blood coagulation and fibrinolysis systems.
  JOURNAL   Thromb. Res. 52 (1988) 541-52.
  ORGANISM  Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:1898066]
  AUTHORS   Guan AL, Retzios AD, Henderson GN, Markland FS Jr.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of a fibrinolytic enzyme from venom of the southern copperhead snake (Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix).
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 289 (1991) 197-207.
  ORGANISM  Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix
  SEQUENCE  [up:P28891]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:1304358]
  AUTHORS   Randolph A, Chamberlain SH, Chu HL, Retzios AD, Markland FS Jr, Masiarz FR.
  TITLE     Amino acid sequence of fibrolase, a direct-acting fibrinolytic enzyme from Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix venom.
  JOURNAL   Protein. Sci. 1 (1992) 590-600.
  ORGANISM  Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix
  SEQUENCE  [up:P28891]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:7719479]
  AUTHORS   Loayza SL, Trikha M, Markland FS, Riquelme P, Kuo J.
  TITLE     Resolution of isoforms of natural and recombinant fibrolase, the fibrinolytic enzyme from Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix snake venom, and comparison of their EDTA sensitivities.
  JOURNAL   J. Chromatogr. B. Biomed. Appl. 662 (1994) 227-43.
  ORGANISM  Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:8085237]
  AUTHORS   Retzios AD, Markland FS.
  TITLE     Fibrinolytic enzymes from the venoms of Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix and Crotalus basiliscus basiliscus: cleavage site specificity towards the alpha-chain of fibrin.
  JOURNAL   Thromb. Res. 74 (1994) 355-67.
  ORGANISM  Agkistrodon contortrix contortrix, Crotalus basiliscus basiliscus
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.72
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.24.72
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.24.72
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.72
            CAS: 116036-70-5
///
