ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.50                Enzyme
NAME        lysyl endopeptidase;
            Achromobacter proteinase I (also see Comment);
            Achromobacter lyticus alkaline proteinase I;
            protease I;
            achromopeptidase;
            lysyl bond specific proteinase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Preferential cleavage: Lys!, including -Lys!Pro-
COMMENT     From Achromobacter lyticus [6]. Enzymes with similar specificity are produced by Lysobacter enzymogenes (Endoproteinase Lys-C; [3]) and Pseudomonas aeruginosa (Ps-1; [4]). In peptidase family S1 (trypsin family)
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.50 created 1983
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:6791693]
  AUTHORS   Masaki T, Tanabe M, Nakamura K, Soejima M.
  TITLE     Studies on a new proteolytic enzyme from A chromobacter lyticus M497-1. I. Purification and some enzymatic properties.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 660 (1981) 44-50.
  ORGANISM  Achromobacter lyticus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:6168293]
  AUTHORS   Masaki T, Fujihashi T, Nakamura K, Soejima M.
  TITLE     Studies on a new proteolytic enzyme from Achromobacter lyticus M497-1. II. specificity and inhibition studies of Achromobacter protease I.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 660 (1981) 51-5.
  ORGANISM  Achromobacter lyticus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:6359954]
  AUTHORS   Jekel PA, Weijer WJ, Beintema JJ.
  TITLE     Use of endoproteinase Lys-C from Lysobacter enzymogenes in protein sequence analysis.
  JOURNAL   Anal. Biochem. 134 (1983) 347-54.
  ORGANISM  Lysobacter enzymogenes
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:3090046]
  AUTHORS   Elliott BW Jr, Cohen C.
  TITLE     Isolation and characterization of a lysine-specific protease from Pseudomonas aeruginosa.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 261 (1986) 11259-65.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas aeruginosa
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:2684982]
  AUTHORS   Ohara T, Makino K, Shinagawa H, Nakata A, Norioka S, Sakiyama F.
  TITLE     Cloning, nucleotide sequence, and expression of Achromobacter protease I gene.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 264 (1989) 20625-31.
  ORGANISM  Achromobacter lyticus
  SEQUENCE  [up:P15636]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:2492988]
  AUTHORS   Tsunasawa S, Masaki T, Hirose M, Soejima M, Sakiyama F.
  TITLE     The primary structure and structural characteristics of Achromobacter lyticus protease I, a lysine-specific serine protease.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 264 (1989) 3832-9.
  ORGANISM  Achromobacter lyticus
  SEQUENCE  [up:P15636]
ORTHOLOGY   K01337  lysyl endopeptidase
GENES       SRU: SRU_1622
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.50
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.50
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.50
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.50
            CAS: 123175-82-6
///
