ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.66                Enzyme
NAME        thermitase;
            thermophilic Streptomyces serine proteinase;
            Thermoactinomyces vulgaris serine proteinase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of proteins, including collagen
COMMENT     A peptidase of family S8 (subtilisin family) from Thermoactinomyces vulgaris containing a single Cys, near the active site His, and inhibited by p-mercuribenzoate. The N-terminal extension of the polypeptide chain relative to subtilisin contributes to Ca2+-binding and the high thermostability. The amino acid composition and properties of the thermostable enzyme from Streptomyces rectus var. proteolyticus (formerly included in EC 3.4.21.14) are closely similar [1,2].
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.66 created 1992
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:4711613]
  AUTHORS   Mizusawa K, Yoshida F.
  TITLE     Thermophilic Streptomyces alkaline proteinase. II. The role of a sulfhydryl group and the conformational stability.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 248 (1973) 4417-23.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces rectus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:4373436]
  AUTHORS   Borgia P, Campbell LL.
  TITLE     Properties of two homologous alkaline proteases from Streptomyces rectus.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 120 (1974) 1109-15.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces rectus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:7051706]
  AUTHORS   Kleine R.
  TITLE     Properties of thermitase, a thermostable serine protease from Thermoactinomyces vulgaris.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Biol. Med. Ger. 41 (1982) 89-102.
  ORGANISM  Thermoactinomyces vulgaris
REFERENCE   4
  AUTHORS   Meloun, B., Baudy, M., Kostka, V., Hausdorf, G., Frommel, C. and Hohne, W.E.
  TITLE     Complete primary structure of thermitase from Thermoactinomyces vulgaris and its structural features related to the subtilisin-type proteinases.
  JOURNAL   FEBS Lett. 183 (1985) 195-200.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:2196375]
  AUTHORS   Teplyakov AV, Kuranova IP, Harutyunyan EH, Vainshtein BK, Frommel C, Hohne WE, Wilson KS.
  TITLE     Crystal structure of thermitase at 1.4 A resolution.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 214 (1990) 261-79.
  ORGANISM  Thermoactinomyces vulgaris
  SEQUENCE  [up:P04072]
ORTHOLOGY   K08651  thermitase
GENES       BAN: BA_2380
            BAR: GBAA_2380
            BAT: BAS2216
            BAH: BAMEG_2220
            BAI: BAA_2438
            BAL: BACI_c23250
            BCE: BC2316
            BCA: BCE_2410
            BCZ: BCZK2139
            BCR: BCAH187_A2480
            BCB: BCB4264_A2345
            BCU: BCAH820_2398
            BCG: BCG9842_B2980
            BCQ: BCQ_2306
            BCX: BCA_2447
            BTK: BT9727_2155
            BTL: BALH_2119
            BTB: BMB171_C2085
            BTHT: H175_ch2313
            HHY: Halhy_2718
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.66
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.66
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.66
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.66
            CAS: 69772-87-8
///
