ENTRY       EC 3.4.23.20                Enzyme
NAME        penicillopepsin;
            peptidase A;
            Penicillium janthinellum aspartic proteinase;
            acid protease A;
            Penicillium citrinum acid proteinase;
            Penicillium cyclopium acid proteinase;
            Penicillium expansum acid proteinase;
            Penicillium janthinellum acid proteinase;
            Penicillium expansum aspartic proteinase;
            Penicillium aspartic proteinase;
            Penicillium caseicolum aspartic proteinase;
            Penicillium roqueforti acid proteinase;
            Penicillium duponti aspartic proteinase;
            Penicillium citrinum aspartic proteinase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Aspartic endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of proteins with broad specificity similar to that of pepsin A, preferring hydrophobic residues at P1 and P1', but also cleaving Gly20!Glu in the B chain of insulin. Clots milk, and activates trypsinogen
COMMENT     From the imperfect fungus Penicillium janthinellum. In peptidase family A1 (pepsin A family). Closely related enzymes have been isolated from P. roqueforti [2] and P. duponti [3].
HISTORY     EC 3.4.23.20 created 1992 (EC 3.4.23.6 created 1992 (EC 3.4.23.6 created 1961 as EC 3.4.4.17, transferred 1972 to EC 3.4.23.6, modified 1981 [EC 3.4.23.7, EC 3.4.23.8, EC 3.4.23.9, EC 3.4.23.10, EC 3.4.99.1, EC 3.4.99.15 and EC 3.4.99.25 all created 1972 and incorporated 1978], part incorporated 1992)
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:4946839]
  AUTHORS   Mains G, Takahashi M, Sodek J, Hofmann T.
  TITLE     The specificity of penicillopepsin.
  JOURNAL   Can. J. Biochem. 49 (1971) 1134-49.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:4790849]
  AUTHORS   Zevaco C, Hermier J, Gripon JC.
  TITLE     [Proteolytic system in Penicillium roqueforti. 2. Purification and properties of acid protease]
  JOURNAL   Biochimie. 55 (1973) 1353-60.
  ORGANISM  Penicillium roqueforti
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:2287]
  AUTHORS   Emi S, Myers DV, Iacobucci GA.
  TITLE     Purification and properties of the thermostable acid protease of Penicillium duponti.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 15 (1976) 842-8.
  ORGANISM  Penicillium duponti
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:1012008]
  AUTHORS   Hofmann T.
  TITLE     Penicillopepsin.
  JOURNAL   Methods. Enzymol. 45 (1976) 434-52.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:323722]
  AUTHORS   Hsu IN, Delbaere LT, James MN, Hofmann T.
  TITLE     Penicillopepsin from Penicillium janthinellum crystal structure at 2.8 A and sequence homology with porcine pepsin.
  JOURNAL   Nature. 266 (1977) 140-5.
  ORGANISM  Penicillium janthinellum
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.20
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.23.20
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.23.20
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.20
            CAS: 9074-08-2
///
