ENTRY       EC 3.4.22.65                Enzyme
NAME        peptidase 1 (mite);
            allergen Der f 1;
            allergen Der p 1;
            antigen Der p 1;
            antigen Eur m 1;
            antigen Pso o 1;
            major mite fecal allergen Der p 1;
            Der p 1;
            Der f 1;
            Eur m 1;
            endopeptidase 1 (mite)
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Cysteine endopeptidases
REACTION    Broad endopeptidase specificity
COMMENT     This enzyme, derived from the house dust mite, is a major component of the allergic immune response [2]. The substrate specificity of this enzyme is not altogether clear. It cleaves the low-affinity IgE receptor CD23 at Glu298!Ser299 and Ser155!Ser156 [1]. It also cleaves the pulmonary structural proteins occludin and claudin at Leu!Leu, Asp!Leu and at Gly!Thr bonds [1,2]. It can also cleave the alpha subunit of the interleukin-2 (IL-2) receptor (CD25) [4]. Using a positional scanning combinatorial library, it was found that the major substrate-specificity determinant is for Ala in the P2 position [3]. The enzyme shows only a slight preference for basic amino acids in the P1 and P3 positions and a preference for aliphatic amino acids such as Ile, Pro, Val, Leu and norleucine in the P4 position [3]. Belongs in peptidase family C1A.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.22.65 created 2007
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Meighan, P. and Pirzad, R.
  TITLE     Mite endopeptidase 1.
  JOURNAL   In: Barrett, A.J., Rawlings, N.D. and Woessner, J.F. (Eds.), Handbook of Proteolytic Enzymes, 2nd ed., Elsevier, London, 2004, p. 1187-1189.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8660343]
  AUTHORS   Kalsheker NA, Deam S, Chambers L, Sreedharan S, Brocklehurst K, Lomas DA.
  TITLE     The house dust mite allergen Der p1 catalytically inactivates alpha 1-antitrypsin by specific reactive centre loop cleavage: a mechanism that promotes airway inflammation and asthma.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 221 (1996) 59-61.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:15489163]
  AUTHORS   Harris J, Mason DE, Li J, Burdick KW, Backes BJ, Chen T, Shipway A, Van Heeke G, Gough L, Ghaemmaghami A, Shakib F, Debaene F, Winssinger N.
  TITLE     Activity profile of dust mite allergen extract using substrate libraries and functional proteomic microarrays.
  JOURNAL   Chem. Biol. 11 (2004) 1361-72.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9432986]
  AUTHORS   Schulz O, Sewell HF, Shakib F.
  TITLE     Proteolytic cleavage of CD25, the alpha subunit of the human T cell interleukin 2 receptor, by Der p 1, a major mite allergen with cysteine protease activity.
  JOURNAL   J. Exp. Med. 187 (1998) 271-5.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:9893750]
  AUTHORS   Schulz O, Sewell HF, Shakib F.
  TITLE     A sensitive fluorescent assay for measuring the cysteine protease activity of Der p 1, a major allergen from the dust mite Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Pathol. 51 (1998) 222-4.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:15707969]
  AUTHORS   Takai T, Kato T, Sakata Y, Yasueda H, Izuhara K, Okumura K, Ogawa H.
  TITLE     Recombinant Der p 1 and Der f 1 exhibit cysteine protease activity but no serine protease activity.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 328 (2005) 944-52.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.65
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.22.65
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.22.65
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.65
///
