ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.81                Enzyme
NAME        streptogrisin B;
            Streptomyces griseus protease B;
            pronase B;
            serine proteinase B;
            Streptomyces griseus proteinase B;
            Streptomyces griseus proteinase 1;
            Streptomyces griseus serine proteinase B
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of proteins with trypsin-like specificity
COMMENT     From Streptomyces griseus. A component of Pronase, in peptidase family S1 (trypsin family), distinct from Streptomyces trypsin
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.81 created 1993
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:4899581]
  AUTHORS   Jurasek L, Fackre D, Smillie LB.
  TITLE     Remarkable homology about the disulfide bridges of a trypsin-like enzyme from Streptomyces griseus.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 37 (1969) 99-105.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces griseus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:6750612]
  AUTHORS   Fujinaga M, Read RJ, Sielecki A, Ardelt W, Laskowski M Jr, James MN.
  TITLE     Refined crystal structure of the molecular complex of Streptomyces griseus protease B, a serine protease, with the third domain of the ovomucoid inhibitor from turkey.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 79 (1982) 4868-72.
  ORGANISM  Meleagris gallopavo
  SEQUENCE  [mgp:100541469]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:6414511]
  AUTHORS   Read RJ, Fujinaga M, Sielecki AR, James MN.
  TITLE     Structure of the complex of Streptomyces griseus protease B and the third domain of the turkey ovomucoid inhibitor at 1.8-A resolution.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 22 (1983) 4420-33.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces griseus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:3112129]
  AUTHORS   Henderson G, Krygsman P, Liu CJ, Davey CC, Malek LT.
  TITLE     Characterization and structure of genes for proteases A and B from Streptomyces griseus.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 169 (1987) 3778-84.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces griseus
  SEQUENCE  [sgr:SGR_5762]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:2494344]
  AUTHORS   Greenblatt HM, Ryan CA, James MN.
  TITLE     Structure of the complex of Streptomyces griseus proteinase B and polypeptide chymotrypsin inhibitor-1 from Russet Burbank potato tubers at 2.1 A resolution.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 205 (1989) 201-28.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces griseus
  SEQUENCE  [sgr:SGR_5762]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.81
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.81
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.81
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.81
            CAS: 55071-87-9
///
