ENTRY       EC 3.4.15.4                 Enzyme
NAME        peptidyl-dipeptidase B;
            dipeptidyl carboxyhydrolase;
            atriopeptin convertase;
            atrial di-(tri)peptidyl carboxyhydrolase;
            peptidyldipeptidase B;
            atrial dipeptidyl carboxyhydrolase;
            atrial peptide convertase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Peptidyl-dipeptidases
REACTION    Release of a C-terminal dipeptide or exceptionally a tripeptide
COMMENT     A membrane-bound, zinc metallopeptidase located in mammalian atrial, but not ventricular, myocytes. Although it is capable of converting the 126-residue atriopeptin III directly to atriopeptin I by releasing a C-terminal tripeptide Phe-Arg-Tyr, it is generally restricted to the release of dipeptides. In contrast to peptidyl-dipeptidase A (EC 3.4.15.1) it displays no Cl- dependence and shows no action on angiotensin I. Conversely, peptidyl-dipeptidase A is unable to release Phe-Arg from the C-terminus of atriopeptin II
HISTORY     EC 3.4.15.4 created 1992
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:6385859]
  AUTHORS   Harris RB, Wilson IB.
  TITLE     Atrial tissue contains a metallo dipeptidyl carboxyhydrolase not present in ventricular tissue: partial purification and characterization.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 233 (1984) 667-75.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:2999723]
  AUTHORS   Harris RB, Wilson IB.
  TITLE     Conversion of atriopeptin II to atriopeptin I by atrial dipeptidyl carboxy hydrolase.
  JOURNAL   Peptides. 6 (1985) 393-6.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:3146555]
  AUTHORS   Soler DF, Harris RB.
  TITLE     Continuous fluorogenic substrates for atrial dipeptidyl carboxyhydrolase. Importance of Ser in the P1 position.
  JOURNAL   Int. J. Pept. Protein. Res. 32 (1988) 35-40.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:2501770]
  AUTHORS   Soler DF, Harris RB.
  TITLE     Atrial dipeptidyl carboxyhydrolase is a zinc-metallo proteinase which possesses tripeptidyl carboxyhydrolase activity.
  JOURNAL   Peptides. 10 (1989) 63-8.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.15.4
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.15.4
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.15.4
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.15.4
            CAS: 147014-93-5
///
