ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.118               Enzyme
NAME        kallikrein 8;
            KLK8;
            PRSS19;
            human kallikrein 8;
            hK8;
            mK8;
            ovasin;
            tumor-associated differentially expressed gene 14;
            TADG-14;
            NP;
            neuropsin
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Cleavage of amide substrates following the basic amino acids Arg or Lys at the P1 position, with a preference for Arg over Lys
COMMENT     The enzyme is activated by removal of an N-terminal prepropeptide [2,4]. The highest amidolytic activity is observed using Boc-Val-Pro-Arg!7-amido-4-methylcoumarin, which is a substrate of alpha-thrombin [2,4]. Substrates lacking basic amino acids in the P1 position are not cleaved [4]. The enzyme degrades casein, fibronectin, gelatin, collagen type IV, fibrinogen, and high-molecular-mass kininogen [3] and is associated with diseases such as ovarian cancer and Alzheimer's disease [4]. Belongs in peptidase family S1A.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.118 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:7623137]
  AUTHORS   Chen ZL, Yoshida S, Kato K, Momota Y, Suzuki J, Tanaka T, Ito J, Nishino H, Aimoto S, Kiyama H, et al.
  TITLE     Expression and activity-dependent changes of a novel limbic-serine protease gene in the hippocampus.
  JOURNAL   J. Neurosci. 15 (1995) 5088-97.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
  SEQUENCE  [mmu:259277]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9556608]
  AUTHORS   Shimizu C, Yoshida S, Shibata M, Kato K, Momota Y, Matsumoto K, Shiosaka T, Midorikawa R, Kamachi T, Kawabe A, Shiosaka S.
  TITLE     Characterization of recombinant and brain neuropsin, a plasticity-related serine protease.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 273 (1998) 11189-96.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
  SEQUENCE  [mmu:259277]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16337200]
  AUTHORS   Rajapakse S, Ogiwara K, Takano N, Moriyama A, Takahashi T.
  TITLE     Biochemical characterization of human kallikrein 8 and its possible involvement in the degradation of extracellular matrix proteins.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 579 (2005) 6879-84.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:11202]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16800733]
  AUTHORS   Kishi T, Cloutier SM, Kundig C, Deperthes D, Diamandis EP.
  TITLE     Activation and enzymatic characterization of recombinant human kallikrein 8.
  JOURNAL   Biol. Chem. 387 (2006) 723-31.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
ORTHOLOGY   K08650  kallikrein 8 (neuropsin/ovasin)
GENES       HSA: 11202(KLK8)
            PTR: 456239(KLK8)
            PPS: 100970185(KLK8)
            GGO: 101151682(KLK8)
            PON: 100437370(KLK8)
            MCC: 719488(KLK8)
            MCF: 102143235(KLK8)
            MMU: 259277(Klk8)
            RNO: 308565(Klk8)
            CGE: 100752953
            HGL: 101715440(Klk8)
            CFA: 484352(KLK8)
            AML: 100476177
            FCA: 101090308(KLK8)
            PTG: 102964756(KLK8)
            BTA: 618438(KLK8)
            BOM: 102281911(KLK8)
            PHD: 102316246(KLK8)
            CHX: 102178849(KLK8)
            CFR: 102521031
            ECB: 100067301(KLK8)
            MYB: 102241466(KLK8)
            MYD: 102764579(KLK8)
            PALE: 102893463(KLK8)
            SHR: 100933656(KLK8)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.118
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.118
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.118
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.118
            CAS: 171715-15-4
///
