ENTRY       EC 3.4.24.42                Enzyme
NAME        atrolysin C;
            Crotalus atrox metalloendopeptidase c;
            hemorrhagic toxin c and d
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Metalloendopeptidases
REACTION    Cleavage of His5!Leu, His10!Leu, Ala14!Leu, Tyr16!Leu and Gly23!Phe bonds in B chain of insulin. With small molecule substrates prefers hydrophobic residue at P2' and small residue such as Ala, Gly at P1
COMMENT     A 24 kDa hemorrhagic endopeptidase from the venom of the western diamondback rattlesnake (Crotalus atrox) that digests type IV collagen, and exists as two forms, c and d. Phosphoramidon inhibits in the 0.1 mM range. In peptidase family M12 (astacin family). Hemorrhagic toxin-2 of C. ruber ruber has the same Mr and specificity and is a homologue [4,6].
HISTORY     EC 3.4.24.42 created 1992
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:210790]
  AUTHORS   Bjarnason JB, Tu AT.
  TITLE     Hemorrhagic toxins from Western diamondback rattlesnake (Crotalus atrox) venom: isolation and characterization of five toxins and the role of zinc in hemorrhagic toxin e.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 17 (1978) 3395-404.
  ORGANISM  Crotalus atrox
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:3514216]
  AUTHORS   Fox JW, Campbell R, Beggerly L, Bjarnason JB.
  TITLE     Substrate specificities and inhibition of two hemorrhagic zinc proteases Ht-c and Ht-d from Crotalus atrox venom.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 156 (1986) 65-72.
  ORGANISM  Crotalus atrox
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:3101740]
  AUTHORS   Bjarnason JB, Fox JW.
  TITLE     Characterization of two hemorrhagic zinc proteinases, toxin c and toxin d, from western diamondback rattlesnake (Crotalus atrox) venom.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 911 (1987) 356-63.
  ORGANISM  Crotalus atrox
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:2949699]
  AUTHORS   Mori N, Nikai T, Sugihara H, Tu AT.
  TITLE     Biochemical characterization of hemorrhagic toxins with fibrinogenase activity isolated from Crotalus ruber ruber venom.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 253 (1987) 108-21.
  ORGANISM  Crotalus ruber ruber
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:2745407]
  AUTHORS   Shannon JD, Baramova EN, Bjarnason JB, Fox JW.
  TITLE     Amino acid sequence of a Crotalus atrox venom metalloproteinase which cleaves type IV collagen and gelatin.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 264 (1989) 11575-83.
  ORGANISM  Crotalus atrox
  SEQUENCE  [up:P15167]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:2081731]
  AUTHORS   Takeya H, Onikura A, Nikai T, Sugihara H, Iwanaga S.
  TITLE     Primary structure of a hemorrhagic metalloproteinase, HT-2, isolated from the venom of Crotalus ruber ruber.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 108 (1990) 711-9.
  ORGANISM  Crotalus ruber ruber
  SEQUENCE  [up:P20897]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.42
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.24.42
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.24.42
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.42
            CAS: 158886-17-0
///
