ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.119               Enzyme
NAME        kallikrein 13;
            KLK13;
            kallikrein mK13;
            mGK-13;
            mK13;
            mKLK13;
            prorenin converting enzyme 1;
            PRECE-1;
            prorenin-converting enzyme;
            PRECE;
            proteinase P
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolyses mouse Ren2 protein (a species of prorenin present in the submandibular gland) on the carboxy side of the arginine residue at the Lys-Arg! pair in the N-terminus, to yield mature renin
COMMENT     The enzyme is specific for prorenin from the mouse submandibular gland, as prorenin from the mouse kidney (Ren1) and human prorenin are not substrates [1]. Site-directed mutagenesis studies have shown that the enzyme will also cleave prorenin when Lys-Arg is replaced by Arg-Arg or Gln-Arg but the rate of reaction is much slower when Lys-Lys is used. This enzyme is also able to process pro-interleukin-1beta (pro-IL-1beta) in mouse submandibular gland to form IL-1beta [4]. Belongs in peptidase family S1A.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.119 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:2250008]
  AUTHORS   Nakayama K, Kim WS, Nakagawa T, Nagahama M, Murakami K.
  TITLE     Substrate specificity of prorenin converting enzyme of mouse submandibular gland. Analysis using site-directed mutagenesis.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 265 (1990) 21027-31.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:2180937]
  AUTHORS   Kim WS, Hatsuzawa K, Ishizuka Y, Hashiba K, Murakami K, Nakayama K.
  TITLE     A processing enzyme for prorenin in mouse submandibular gland. Purification and characterization.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 265 (1990) 5930-3.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9507064]
  AUTHORS   Kikkawa Y, Yamanaka N, Tada J, Kanamori N, Tsumura K, Hosoi K.
  TITLE     Prorenin processing and restricted endoproteolysis by mouse tissue kallikrein family enzymes (mK1, mK9, mK13, and mK22).
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1382 (1998) 55-64.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16423834]
  AUTHORS   Yao C, Karabasil MR, Purwanti N, Li X, Akamatsu T, Kanamori N, Hosoi K.
  TITLE     Tissue kallikrein mK13 is a candidate processing enzyme for the precursor of interleukin-1beta in the submandibular gland of mice.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 281 (2006) 7968-76.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
ORTHOLOGY   K09462  glandular kallikrein 13
GENES       MMU: 13647(Egfbp2)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.119
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.119
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.119
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.119
            CAS: 342900-44-1
///
