ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.113               Enzyme
NAME        pestivirus NS3 polyprotein peptidase;
            border disease virus NS3 endopeptidase;
            BDV NS3 endopeptidase;
            bovine viral diarrhea virus NS3 endopeptidase;
            BVDV NS3 endopeptidase;
            classical swine fever virus NS3 endopeptidase;
            CSFV NS3 endopeptidase;
            p80
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Leu is conserved at position P1 for all four cleavage sites. Alanine is found at position P1' of the NS4A-NS4B cleavage site, whereas serine is found at position P1' of the NS3-NS4A, NS4B-NS5A and NS5A-NS5B cleavage sites
COMMENT     The polyprotein of noncytopathogenic pestiviruses is cleaved co- and post-translationally into at least 11 proteins (Npro, C, Erns, E1, E2, p7, NS2-3, NS4A, NS4B, NS5A, and NS5B) [2]. The genomes of cytopathogenic pestivirus strains express at least one additional protein, called NS3 (p80) [2]. This enzyme, which resides in the N-terminal region of NS3 (nonstructural protein 3), is essential for generation of its own C-terminus and for processing of the downstream cleavage sites, leading to the release of the pestivirus nonstructural proteins NS4A, NS4B, NS5A and NS5B [1,2]. Belongs in peptidase family S31.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.113 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1651596]
  AUTHORS   Wiskerchen M, Collett MS.
  TITLE     Pestivirus gene expression: protein p80 of bovine viral diarrhea virus is a proteinase involved in polyprotein processing.
  JOURNAL   Virology. 184 (1991) 341-50.
  ORGANISM  Bovine viral diarrhea virus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9188613]
  AUTHORS   Tautz N, Elbers K, Stoll D, Meyers G, Thiel HJ.
  TITLE     Serine protease of pestiviruses: determination of cleavage sites.
  JOURNAL   J. Virol. 71 (1997) 5415-22.
  ORGANISM  Bovine viral diarrhea virus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q96662]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9188600]
  AUTHORS   Xu J, Mendez E, Caron PR, Lin C, Murcko MA, Collett MS, Rice CM.
  TITLE     Bovine viral diarrhea virus NS3 serine proteinase: polyprotein cleavage sites, cofactor requirements, and molecular model of an enzyme essential for pestivirus replication.
  JOURNAL   J. Virol. 71 (1997) 5312-22.
  ORGANISM  Bovine viral diarrhea virus
  SEQUENCE  [up:P19711]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:10915606]
  AUTHORS   Tautz N, Kaiser A, Thiel HJ.
  TITLE     NS3 serine protease of bovine viral diarrhea virus: characterization of active site residues, NS4A cofactor domain, and protease-cofactor interactions.
  JOURNAL   Virology. 273 (2000) 351-63.
  ORGANISM  Bovine viral diarrhea virus
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.113
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.113
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.113
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.113
///
