ENTRY       EC 3.4.22.63                Enzyme
NAME        caspase-10;
            FLICE2, Mch4;
            CASP-10;
            ICE-like apoptotic protease 4;
            apoptotic protease Mch-4;
            FAS-associated death domain protein interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme 2
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Cysteine endopeptidases
REACTION    Strict requirement for Asp at position P1 and has a preferred cleavage sequence of Leu-Gln-Thr-Asp!Gly
COMMENT     Caspase-10 is an initiator caspase, as are caspase-2 (EC 3.4.22.55), caspase-8 (EC 3.4.22.61) and caspase-9 (EC 3.4.22.62) [1]. Like caspase-8, caspase-10 contains two tandem death effector domains (DEDs) in its N-terminal prodomain, and these play a role in procaspase activation [1]. The enzyme has many overlapping substrates in common with caspase-8, such as RIP (the cleavage of which impairs NF-kappaB survival signalling and starts the cell-death process) and PAK2 (associated with some of the morphological features of apoptosis, such as cell rounding and apoptotic body formation) [2]. Bid, a Bcl2 protein, can be cleaved by caspase-3 (EC 3.4.22.56), caspase-8 and caspase-10 at Lys-Gln-Thr-Asp! to yield the pro-apoptotic p15 fragment. The p15 fragment is N-myristoylated and enhances the release of cytochrome c from mitochondria (which, in turn, initiatiates the intrinsic apoptosis pathway). Bid can be further cleaved by caspase-10 and granzyme B but not by caspase-3 or caspase-8 at Ile-Glu-Thr-Asp! to yield a p13 fragment that is not N-myristoylated [2]. Belongs in peptidase family C14.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.22.63 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:11104820]
  AUTHORS   Chang HY, Yang X.
  TITLE     Proteases for cell suicide: functions and regulation of caspases.
  JOURNAL   Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev. 64 (2000) 821-46.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16186808]
  AUTHORS   Fischer U, Stroh C, Schulze-Osthoff K.
  TITLE     Unique and overlapping substrate specificities of caspase-8 and caspase-10.
  JOURNAL   Oncogene. 25 (2006) 152-9.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:12884866]
  AUTHORS   Shikama Y, Yamada M, Miyashita T.
  TITLE     Caspase-8 and caspase-10 activate NF-kappaB through RIP, NIK and IKKalpha kinases.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Immunol. 33 (2003) 1998-2006.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15209560]
  AUTHORS   Boatright KM, Deis C, Denault JB, Sutherlin DP, Salvesen GS.
  TITLE     Activation of caspases-8 and -10 by FLIP(L).
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 382 (2004) 651-7.
ORTHOLOGY   K04400  caspase 10
GENES       HSA: 843(CASP10)
            PTR: 459873(CASP10)
            PPS: 100972863(CASP10)
            GGO: 101131419(CASP10)
            PON: 100174433(CASP10)
            MCC: 701295(CASP10)
            MCF: 102144792(CASP10)
            HGL: 101712620(Casp10)
            TUP: 102496563(CASP10)
            CFA: 488472(CASP10)
            AML: 100475128
            FCA: 101085995(CASP10)
            PTG: 102962753(CASP10)
            PHD: 102318392(CASP10)
            CHX: 102172107(CASP10)
            SSC: 100154896(CASP10)
            CFR: 102514092(CASP10)
            ECB: 100068201(CASP10)
            MYB: 102253536
            MYD: 102763065(CASP10)
            PALE: 102877929(CASP10)
            MDO: 100016987(CASP10)
            SHR: 100930260(CASP10)
            OAA: 100092695
            GGA: 424081(CASP10)
            MGP: 100550034
            TGU: 100220453(CASP10)
            FAB: 101815409(CASP10)
            PHI: 102103849(CASP10)
            APLA: 101799731(CASP10)
            FPG: 101918719(CASP10)
            FCH: 102057122(CASP10)
            CLV: 102085114(CASP10)
            ASN: 102380890(CASP10)
            PSS: 102463731
            CMY: 102931579(CASP10)
            ACS: 100564281
            XLA: 397820(casp10) 398762(MGC68465)
            XTR: 548432(casp10)
            TRU: 101061322
            XMA: 102237443
            LCM: 102349989
            BFO: BRAFLDRAFT_68000
            PHU: Phum_PHUM574530
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.63
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.22.63
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.22.63
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.63
            CAS: 189088-85-5
///
