ENTRY       EC 3.4.22.66                Enzyme
NAME        calicivirin;
            Camberwell virus processing peptidase;
            Chiba virus processing peptidase;
            Norwalk virus processing peptidase;
            Southampton virus processing peptidase;
            Southampton virus;
            norovirus virus processing peptidase;
            calicivirus trypsin-like cysteine protease;
            calicivirus TCP;
            calicivirus 3C-like protease;
            calicivirus endopeptidase;
            rabbit hemorrhagic disease virus 3C endopeptidase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Cysteine endopeptidases
REACTION    Endopeptidase with a preference for cleavage when the P1 position is occupied by Glu! and the P1' position is occupied by Gly!
COMMENT     Viruses that are members of the Norovirus genus (Caliciviridae family) are a major cause of epidemic acute viral gastroenteritis [4]. The nonstructural proteins of these viruses are produced by proteolytic cleavage of a large precursor polyprotein, performed by a protease that is incorporated into the polyprotein [6]. Cleavage sites are apparently defined by features based on both sequence and structure since several sites in the polyprotein fulfilling the identified sequence requirements are not cleaved [1]. The presence of acidic (Asp), basic (Arg), aromatic (Tyr) or aliphatic (Leu) amino acids at the P1' position results in only minor differences in cleavage efficiency, suggesting that steric or conformational constraints may play a role in determining specificity [1]. Changes to the amino acid at the P2 position do not alter cleavage efficiency [1,2]. Belongs in peptidase family C37.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.22.66 created 2007
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Meyers, G., Rossi, C. and Thiel, H.J.
  TITLE     Calicivirus endopeptidases.
  JOURNAL   In: Barrett, A.J., Rawlings, N.D. and Woessner, J.F. (Eds.), Handbook of Proteolytic Enzymes, 2nd ed., Elsevier, London, 2004, p. 1380-1382.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7474137]
  AUTHORS   Wirblich C, Sibilia M, Boniotti MB, Rossi C, Thiel HJ, Meyers G.
  TITLE     3C-like protease of rabbit hemorrhagic disease virus: identification of cleavage sites in the ORF1 polyprotein and analysis of cleavage specificity.
  JOURNAL   J. Virol. 69 (1995) 7159-68.
  ORGANISM  Rabbit hemorrhagic disease virus
  SEQUENCE  [up:P27410]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8551592]
  AUTHORS   Martin Alonso JM, Casais R, Boga JA, Parra F.
  TITLE     Processing of rabbit hemorrhagic disease virus polyprotein.
  JOURNAL   J. Virol. 70 (1996) 1261-5.
  ORGANISM  Rabbit hemorrhagic disease virus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q86119]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:8642693]
  AUTHORS   Liu B, Clarke IN, Lambden PR.
  TITLE     Polyprotein processing in Southampton virus: identification of 3C-like protease cleavage sites by in vitro mutagenesis.
  JOURNAL   J. Virol. 70 (1996) 2605-10.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:10073687]
  AUTHORS   Liu BL, Viljoen GJ, Clarke IN, Lambden PR.
  TITLE     Identification of further proteolytic cleavage sites in the Southampton calicivirus polyprotein by expression of the viral protease in E. coli.
  JOURNAL   J. Gen. Virol. 80 ( Pt 2) (1999) 291-6.
  ORGANISM  Southampton virus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q04544]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.66
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.22.66
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.22.66
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.66
///
