ENTRY       EC 3.4.22.57                Enzyme
NAME        caspase-4;
            ICErelII;
            ICErel-II;
            Ich-2;
            transcript X;
            TX;
            TX protease;
            caspase 4;
            CASP-4
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Cysteine endopeptidases
REACTION    Strict requirement for Asp at the P1 position. It has a preferred cleavage sequence of Tyr-Val-Ala-Asp! but also cleaves at Asp-Glu-Val-Asp!
COMMENT     This enzyme is part of the family of inflammatory caspases, which also includes caspase-1 (EC 3.4.22.36) and caspase-5 (EC 3.4.22.58) in humans and caspase-11 (EC 3.4.22.64), caspase-12, caspase-13 and caspase-14 in mice. Contains a caspase-recruitment domain (CARD) in its N-terminal prodomain, which plays a role in procaspase activation [3,5,6]. The enzyme is able to cleave itself and the p30 caspase-1 precursor, but, unlike caspase-1, it is very inefficient at generating mature interleukin-1beta (IL-1beta) from pro-IL-1beta [1,4]. Both this enzyme and caspase-5 can cleave pro-caspase-3 to release the small subunit (p12) but not the large subunit (p17) [3]. The caspase-1 inhibitor Ac-Tyr-Val-Ala-Asp-CHO can also inhibit this enzyme, but more slowly [4]. Belongs in peptidase family C14.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.22.57 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:7743998]
  AUTHORS   Faucheu C, Diu A, Chan AW, Blanchet AM, Miossec C, Herve F, Collard-Dutilleul V, Gu Y, Aldape RA, Lippke JA, et al.
  TITLE     A novel human protease similar to the interleukin-1 beta converting enzyme induces apoptosis in transfected cells.
  JOURNAL   EMBO. J. 14 (1995) 1914-22.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:837]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7797510]
  AUTHORS   Kamens J, Paskind M, Hugunin M, Talanian RV, Allen H, Banach D, Bump N, Hackett M, Johnston CG, Li P, et al.
  TITLE     Identification and characterization of ICH-2, a novel member of the interleukin-1 beta-converting enzyme family of cysteine proteases.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 270 (1995) 15250-6.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:837]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16465268]
  AUTHORS   Kamada S, Funahashi Y, Tsujimoto Y.
  TITLE     Caspase-4 and caspase-5, members of the ICE/CED-3 family of cysteine proteases, are CrmA-inhibitable proteases.
  JOURNAL   Cell. Death. Differ. 4 (1997) 473-8.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9578463]
  AUTHORS   Fassy F, Krebs O, Rey H, Komara B, Gillard C, Capdevila C, Yea C, Faucheu C, Blanchet AM, Miossec C, Diu-Hercend A.
  TITLE     Enzymatic activity of two caspases related to interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 253 (1998) 76-83.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15163405]
  AUTHORS   Martinon F, Tschopp J.
  TITLE     Inflammatory caspases: linking an intracellular innate immune system to autoinflammatory diseases.
  JOURNAL   Cell. 117 (2004) 561-74.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:11104820]
  AUTHORS   Chang HY, Yang X.
  TITLE     Proteases for cell suicide: functions and regulation of caspases.
  JOURNAL   Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev. 64 (2000) 821-46.
ORTHOLOGY   K04394  caspase 4
GENES       HSA: 837(CASP4)
            PTR: 451518(CASP4)
            PPS: 100991353
            GGO: 101139012(CASP4)
            PON: 100436933(CASP4)
            MCC: 704864(CASP4)
            MCF: 102116921(CASP4)
            RNO: 114555(Casp4)
            HGL: 101700797(Casp4)
            TUP: 102489894(CASP4)
            CFA: 403724(CASP4)
            AML: 100464921
            BTA: 338039(CASP4)
            BOM: 102272500
            CHX: 102191063(CASP4)
            SSC: 100522887(CASP4)
            ECB: 100069303(CASP4)
            MYD: 102774240
            PALE: 102887403
            MDO: 100032600
            SHR: 100914382
            ACS: 100554079
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.57
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.22.57
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.22.57
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.57
            CAS: 182762-08-9
///
