ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.37                Enzyme
NAME        leukocyte elastase;
            lysosomal elastase;
            neutrophil elastase;
            polymorphonuclear leukocyte elastase;
            elastase;
            elaszym;
            serine elastase;
            lysosomal elastase;
            granulocyte elastase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of proteins, including elastin. Preferential cleavage Val! > Ala!
COMMENT     Differs from pancreatic elastase in specificity on synthetic substrates and in inhibitor sensitivity. In peptidase family S1 (trypsin family). Formerly included in EC 3.4.21.11
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.37 created 1981 (EC 3.4.4.7 created 1961, transferred 1972 to EC 3.4.21.11 created 1972, part incorporated 1984)
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:7043201]
  AUTHORS   Barrett AJ.
  TITLE     Leukocyte elastase.
  JOURNAL   Methods. Enzymol. 80 Pt C (1981) 581-8.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:6380580]
  AUTHORS   Harper JW, Cook RR, Roberts CJ, McLaughlin BJ, Powers JC.
  TITLE     Active site mapping of the serine proteases human leukocyte elastase, cathepsin G, porcine pancreatic elastase, rat mast cell proteases I and II. Bovine chymotrypsin A alpha, and Staphylococcus aureus protease V-8 using tripeptide thiobenzyl ester substrates.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 23 (1984) 2995-3002.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Rattus norvegicus, Bos taurus, Staphylococcus aureus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:3646070]
  AUTHORS   Stein RL, Strimpler AM, Hori H, Powers JC.
  TITLE     Catalysis by human leukocyte elastase: mechanistic insights into specificity requirements.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 26 (1987) 1301-5.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:2655701]
  AUTHORS   Bode W, Meyer E Jr, Powers JC.
  TITLE     Human leukocyte and porcine pancreatic elastase: X-ray crystal structures, mechanism, substrate specificity, and mechanism-based inhibitors.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 28 (1989) 1951-63.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Sus scofa
ORTHOLOGY   K01327  leukocyte elastase
GENES       HSA: 1991(ELANE)
            PTR: 749897(ELANE)
            PPS: 100969272(ELANE) 100970329
            GGO: 101136126(ELANE)
            PON: 100452808(ELANE)
            MCF: 102135637(ELANE)
            MMU: 50701(Elane)
            RNO: 299606(Elane)
            CGE: 100752732
            HGL: 101705441 101715199
            TUP: 102488298(ELANE)
            CFA: 442980(ELANE)
            FCA: 100301482(ELANE)
            PTG: 102951727(ELANE)
            BTA: 100126050(ELANE)
            BOM: 102274925(ELANE)
            PHD: 102322848(ELANE)
            CHX: 102173292(ELANE)
            SSC: 100522182(ELANE)
            CFR: 102507529(ELANE)
            MYD: 102756029(ELANE)
            PALE: 102888696(ELANE)
            MDO: 100030465(ELANE)
            SHR: 100932763(ELANE)
            OAA: 791113
            XTR: 448597(prtn3)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.37
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.37
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.37
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.37
            CAS: 9004-06-2
///
