ENTRY       EC 3.4.19.13                Enzyme
NAME        glutathione hydrolase;
            glutathionase;
            GGT (ambiguous);
            gamma-glutamyltranspeptidase (ambiguous)
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Omega peptidases
REACTION    glutathione + H2O = L-cysteinylglycine + L-glutamate [RN:R00494]
ALL_REAC    R00494
SUBSTRATE   glutathione [CPD:C00051];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     L-cysteinylglycine [CPD:C01419];
            L-glutamate [CPD:C00025]
COMMENT     This protein also has EC 2.3.2.2 (gamma-glutamyltransferase) activity. The enzyme consists of two chains that are created by the proteolytic cleavage of a single precursor polypeptide. The N-terminal L-threonine of the C-terminal subunit functions as the active site for both the cleavage and the hydrolysis reactions [2-5]. The human enzyme also hydrolyses oxidized glutathione and leukotriene C4 with similar efficiency, while the mouse enzyme does not [6-7].
HISTORY     EC 3.4.19.13 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8099811]
  AUTHORS   Hanigan MH, Ricketts WA
  TITLE     Extracellular glutathione is a source of cysteine for cells that express gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 32 (1993) 6302-6.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12207027]
  AUTHORS   Suzuki H, Kumagai H
  TITLE     Autocatalytic processing of gamma-glutamyltranspeptidase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 277 (2002) 43536-43.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16618936]
  AUTHORS   Okada T, Suzuki H, Wada K, Kumagai H, Fukuyama K
  TITLE     Crystal structures of gamma-glutamyltranspeptidase from Escherichia coli, a key enzyme in glutathione metabolism, and its reaction intermediate.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 103 (2006) 6471-6.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [up:P18956]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:17107958]
  AUTHORS   Boanca G, Sand A, Okada T, Suzuki H, Kumagai H, Fukuyama K, Barycki JJ
  TITLE     Autoprocessing of Helicobacter pylori gamma-glutamyltranspeptidase leads to the formation of a threonine-threonine catalytic dyad.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 282 (2007) 534-41.
  ORGANISM  Helicobacter pylori
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:17135273]
  AUTHORS   Okada T, Suzuki H, Wada K, Kumagai H, Fukuyama K
  TITLE     Crystal structure of the gamma-glutamyltranspeptidase precursor protein from Escherichia coli. Structural changes upon autocatalytic processing and implications for the maturation mechanism.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 282 (2007) 2433-9.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [up:P18956]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:21447318]
  AUTHORS   Wickham S, West MB, Cook PF, Hanigan MH
  TITLE     Gamma-glutamyl compounds: substrate specificity of gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase  enzymes.
  JOURNAL   Anal. Biochem. 414 (2011) 208-14.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:9139674]
  AUTHORS   Carter BZ, Wiseman AL, Orkiszewski R, Ballard KD, Ou CN, Lieberman MW
  TITLE     Metabolism of leukotriene C4 in gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase-deficient mice.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 272 (1997) 12305-10.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.19.13
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.19.13
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.19.13
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.19.13
///
