ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.114               Enzyme
NAME        equine arterivirus serine peptidase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Cleavage of (Glu/Gln)!(Gly/Ser/Ala) in arterivirus replicase translation products ORF1a and ORF1ab
COMMENT     In the equine arterivirus (EAV), the replicase gene is translated into open reading frame 1a (ORF1a) and ORF1ab polyproteins. This enzyme is the main viral proteinase and processes five cleavage sites in the ORF1a protein and three in the ORF1b-encoded part of the ORF1ab protein to yield nonstructural proteins (nsp5-nsp12) [3]. It combines the catalytic system of a chymotrypsin-like serine peptidase (His-Asp-Ser catalytic triad) with the substrate specificity of a 3C-like serine peptidase (Glu or Gln) at the P1 position and a small amino-acid residue (Gly, Ser or Ala) at the P1' position [1]. Cleavage of ORF1ab by this enzyme is essential for viral replication [2]. Belongs in peptidase family S32.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.114 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8617757]
  AUTHORS   Snijder EJ, Wassenaar AL, van Dinten LC, Spaan WJ, Gorbalenya AE.
  TITLE     The arterivirus nsp4 protease is the prototype of a novel group of chymotrypsin-like enzymes, the 3C-like serine proteases.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 271 (1996) 4864-71.
  ORGANISM  equine arteritis virus
  SEQUENCE  [up:P19811]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9971783]
  AUTHORS   van Dinten LC, Rensen S, Gorbalenya AE, Snijder EJ.
  TITLE     Proteolytic processing of the open reading frame 1b-encoded part of arterivirus replicase is mediated by nsp4 serine protease and Is essential for virus replication.
  JOURNAL   J. Virol. 73 (1999) 2027-37.
  ORGANISM  equine arteritis virus
  SEQUENCE  [up:P19811]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:12163505]
  AUTHORS   Barrette-Ng IH, Ng KK, Mark BL, Van Aken D, Cherney MM, Garen C, Kolodenko Y, Gorbalenya AE, Snijder EJ, James MN.
  TITLE     Structure of arterivirus nsp4. The smallest chymotrypsin-like proteinase with an alpha/beta C-terminal extension and alternate conformations of the oxyanion hole.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 277 (2002) 39960-6.
  ORGANISM  equine arteritis virus
  SEQUENCE  [up:P19811]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.114
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.114
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.114
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.114
///
