ENTRY       EC 3.4.22.58                Enzyme
NAME        caspase-5;
            ICErel-III;
            Ich-3;
            ICH-3 protease;
            transcript Y;
            TY;
            CASP-5
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Cysteine endopeptidases
REACTION    Strict requirement for Asp at the P1 position. It has a preferred cleavage sequence of Tyr-Val-Ala-Asp! but also cleaves at Asp-Glu-Val-Asp!
COMMENT     This enzyme is part of the family of inflammatory caspases, which also includes caspase-1 (EC 3.4.22.36) and caspase-4 (EC 3.4.22.57) in humans and caspase-11 (EC 3.4.22.64), caspase-12, caspase-13 and caspase-14 in mice. Contains a caspase-recruitment domain (CARD) in its N-terminal prodomain, which plays a role in procaspase activation [3,5,6]. The enzyme is able to cleave itself and the p30 caspase-1 precursor, but is very inefficient at generating mature interleukin-1beta (IL-1beta) from pro-IL-1beta [1,4]. Both this enzyme and caspase-4 can cleave pro-caspase-3 to release the small subunit (p12) but not the large subunit (p17) [3]. Unlike caspase-4, this enzyme can be induced by lipopolysaccharide [3]. Belongs in peptidase family C14.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.22.58 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8617266]
  AUTHORS   Faucheu C, Blanchet AM, Collard-Dutilleul V, Lalanne JL, Diu-Hercend A.
  TITLE     Identification of a cysteine protease closely related to interleukin-1 beta-converting enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 236 (1996) 207-13.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:838]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16465268]
  AUTHORS   Kamada S, Funahashi Y, Tsujimoto Y.
  TITLE     Caspase-4 and caspase-5, members of the ICE/CED-3 family of cysteine proteases, are CrmA-inhibitable proteases.
  JOURNAL   Cell. Death. Differ. 4 (1997) 473-8.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10986288]
  AUTHORS   Lin XY, Choi MS, Porter AG.
  TITLE     Expression analysis of the human caspase-1 subfamily reveals specific regulation of the CASP5 gene by lipopolysaccharide and interferon-gamma.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 275 (2000) 39920-6.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9578463]
  AUTHORS   Fassy F, Krebs O, Rey H, Komara B, Gillard C, Capdevila C, Yea C, Faucheu C, Blanchet AM, Miossec C, Diu-Hercend A.
  TITLE     Enzymatic activity of two caspases related to interleukin-1beta-converting enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 253 (1998) 76-83.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15163405]
  AUTHORS   Martinon F, Tschopp J.
  TITLE     Inflammatory caspases: linking an intracellular innate immune system to autoinflammatory diseases.
  JOURNAL   Cell. 117 (2004) 561-74.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:11104820]
  AUTHORS   Chang HY, Yang X.
  TITLE     Proteases for cell suicide: functions and regulation of caspases.
  JOURNAL   Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev. 64 (2000) 821-46.
ORTHOLOGY   K04395  caspase 5
GENES       HSA: 838(CASP5)
            PTR: 735478(CASP5)
            PPS: 100990344(CASP5)
            GGO: 101136926(CASP5)
            PON: 100437308(CASP5)
            MCC: 704964(CASP5)
            MCF: 102120532(CASP5)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.58
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.22.58
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.22.58
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.58
            CAS: 192465-11-5
///
