ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.111               Enzyme
NAME        aqualysin 1;
            caldolysin
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Exhibits low specificity towards esters of amino acids with small hydrophobic or aromatic residues at the P1 position
COMMENT     This enzyme from the extreme thermophile, Thermus aquaticus, is an alkaline serine peptidase. It has three subsites, S1, S2, and S3, in the substrate binding site. The preferred amino acids at the S1 site are Ala and Phe, at the S2 site are Ala and norleucine and at the S3 site are Phe and Ile [3]. These specificities are similar to those of EC 3.4.21.64 (peptidase K) and EC 3.4.21.62 (subtilisin BPN') [3]. The enzyme displays broad specificity for cleavage of insulin B-chain and hydrolyses elastin substrates such as succinyl-(Ala)n-p-nitroanilide (n = 1,2,3) and some peptide esters [1,3]. Belongs in peptidase family S8A.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.111 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3162211]
  AUTHORS   Matsuzawa H, Tokugawa K, Hamaoki M, Mizoguchi M, Taguchi H, Terada I, Kwon ST, Ohta T.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of aqualysin I (a thermophilic alkaline serine protease) produced by Thermus aquaticus YT-1.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 171 (1988) 441-7.
  ORGANISM  Thermus aquaticus
  SEQUENCE  [up:P08594]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9882104]
  AUTHORS   Tanaka T, Matsuzawa H, Kojima S, Kumagai I, Miura K, Ohta T.
  TITLE     P1 specificity of aqualysin I (a subtilisin-type serine protease) from Thermus aquaticus YT-1, using P1-substituted derivatives of Streptomyces subtilisin inhibitor.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 62 (1998) 2035-8.
  ORGANISM  Thermus aquaticus
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   Tanaka, T., Matsuzawa, H. and Ohta, T.
  TITLE     Substrate specificity of aqualysin I, a bacterial thermophilic alkaline serine protease from Thermus aquaticus YT-1: Comparison with proteinase K, subtilisin BPN' and subtilisin Carlsberg.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 62 (1998) 2161-2165.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.111
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.111
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.111
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.111
            CAS: 88747-68-6
///
