ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.32                Enzyme
NAME        brachyurin;
            Uca pugilator collagenolytic proteinase;
            crab protease I;
            crab protease II
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of proteins, with broad specificity for peptide bonds. Native collagen is cleaved about 75% of the length of the molecule from the N-terminus. Low activity on small molecule substrates of both trypsin and chymotrypsin
COMMENT     From hepatopancreas of the fiddler crab, Uca pugilator. In peptidase family S1 (trypsin family). Other serine endopeptidases that degrade collagen, but are not listed separately here, include a second endopeptidase from Uca pugilator [4], digestive enzymes from other decapod crustacea [5,6], and an enzyme from the fungus Entomophthora coronata [1].
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.32 created 1978
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:219780]
  AUTHORS   Hurion N, Fromentin H, Keil B.
  TITLE     Specificity of the collagenolytic enzyme from the fungus Entomophthora coronata: comparison with the bacterial collagenase from Achromobacter iophagus.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 192 (1979) 438-45.
  ORGANISM  Uca pugilator
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Grant, G.A., Eisen, A.Z. and Bradshaw, R.A.
  TITLE     Collagenolytic protease from fiddler crab (Uca pugilator).
  JOURNAL   Methods Enzymol. 80 (1981) 722-734.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:6756469]
  AUTHORS   Welgus HG, Grant GA, Jeffrey JJ, Eisen AZ.
  TITLE     Substrate specificity of the collagenolytic serine protease from Uca pugilator: studies with collagenous substrates.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 21 (1982) 5183-9.
  ORGANISM  Uca pugilator
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:6305411]
  AUTHORS   Welgus HG, Grant GA.
  TITLE     Degradation of collagen substrates by a trypsin-like serine protease from the fiddler crab Uca pugilator.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 22 (1983) 2228-33.
  ORGANISM  Uca pugilator
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:2154979]
  AUTHORS   Klimova OA, Borukhov SI, Solovyeva NI, Balaevskaya TO, Strongin AYa.
  TITLE     The isolation and properties of collagenolytic proteases from crab hepatopancreas.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 166 (1990) 1411-20.
  ORGANISM  Paralithodes camtschaticus
  SEQUENCE  [up:P20731 P20732 P20733 P20734]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:1963309]
  AUTHORS   Lu PJ, Liu HC, Tsai IH.
  TITLE     The midgut trypsins of shrimp (Penaeus monodon). High efficiency toward native protein substrates including collagens.
  JOURNAL   Biol. Chem. Hoppe. Seyler. 371 (1990) 851-9.
  ORGANISM  Penaeus monodon
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.32
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.32
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.32
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.32
            CAS: 848900-32-3
///
