ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.110               Enzyme
NAME        C5a peptidase;
            streptococcal C5a peptidase;
            ScpA;
            ScpB;
            SCPA
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    The primary cleavage site is at His67!Lys68 in human C5a with a minor secondary cleavage site at Ala58!Ser59
COMMENT     This enzyme is a surface-associated subtilisin-like serine peptidase with very specific substrate specificity. Virulent strains of streptococci, including Streptococcus pyogenes, can evade human detection and phagocytosis by destroying the complement chemotaxin C5a. Cleavage of human C5a by this enzyme reduces the ability of C5a to bind receptors on the surface of polymorphonuclear neutrophil leukocytes (PMNLs) and thereby abolishes its chemotactic properties [1,4]. Belongs in peptidase family S8A.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.110 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3906656]
  AUTHORS   Wexler DE, Chenoweth DE, Cleary PP.
  TITLE     Mechanism of action of the group A streptococcal C5a inactivator.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 82 (1985) 8144-8.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:1996961]
  AUTHORS   Bohnsack JF, Mollison KW, Buko AM, Ashworth JC, Hill HR.
  TITLE     Group B streptococci inactivate complement component C5a by enzymic cleavage at the C-terminus.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 273 ( Pt 3) (1991) 635-40.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:1452354]
  AUTHORS   Cleary PP, Prahbu U, Dale JB, Wexler DE, Handley J.
  TITLE     Streptococcal C5a peptidase is a highly specific endopeptidase.
  JOURNAL   Infect. Immun. 60 (1992) 5219-23.
  ORGANISM  Streptococcus pyogenes
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12354115]
  AUTHORS   Anderson ET, Wetherell MG, Winter LA, Olmsted SB, Cleary PP, Matsuka YV.
  TITLE     Processing, stability, and kinetic parameters of C5a peptidase from Streptococcus pyogenes.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 269 (2002) 4839-51.
  ORGANISM  Streptococcus pyogenes
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:10809707]
  AUTHORS   Stafslien DK, Cleary PP.
  TITLE     Characterization of the streptococcal C5a peptidase using a C5a-green fluorescent protein fusion protein substrate.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 182 (2000) 3254-8.
  ORGANISM  Streptococcus pyogenes
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:16565520]
  AUTHORS   Terao Y, Yamaguchi M, Hamada S, Kawabata S.
  TITLE     Multifunctional glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase of Streptococcus pyogenes is essential for evasion from neutrophils.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 281 (2006) 14215-23.
  ORGANISM  Streptococcus pyogenes
ORTHOLOGY   K08652  C5a peptidase
GENES       SPY: SPy_2010(scpA)
            SPZ: M5005_Spy_1715(scpA)
            SPM: spyM18_2074(scpA)
            SPG: SpyM3_1726(scpA)
            SPS: SPs1724
            SPH: MGAS10270_Spy1782(scpA)
            SPI: MGAS10750_Spy1807(scpA)
            SPJ: MGAS2096_Spy1744(scpA)
            SPK: MGAS9429_Spy1720(scpA)
            SPF: SpyM51681(scpA)
            SPA: M6_Spy1718
            SPB: M28_Spy1700(scpA)
            SOZ: Spy49_1669c(scpA)
            SAG: SAG0416
            SAN: gbs0451 gbs1308(scpB)
            SAK: SAK_1320(scpB)
            SEQ: SZO_10150
            SEZ: Sez_0946(scpZ)
            SUB: SUB1154(scpA)
            SDS: SDEG_0933(scpB)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.110
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.110
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.110
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.110
            CAS: 100179-39-3
///
