ENTRY       EC 3.4.24.69                Enzyme
NAME        bontoxilysin;
            botulinum neurotoxin;
            BoNT
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Metalloendopeptidases
REACTION    Limited hydrolysis of proteins of the neuroexocytosis apparatus, synaptobrevin (also known as neuronal vesicle-associated membrane protein, VAMP), synaptosome-associated protein of 25 kDa (SNAP25) or syntaxin. No detected action on small molecule substrates
COMMENT     This zinc enzyme, produced by Clostridium botulinum, occurs as forms A-G that differ in specificity of action on the proteins of the neuroexocytosis apparatus [1-5]. The 150-kDa proenzymes of bontoxilysin are processed to disulfide-linked subunits of 100 and 50 kDa, the latter being responsible for the endopeptidase activities. Weakly inhibited by captopril, and phosphoramidon. Toxicity is due to action at the neuromuscular junctions that blocks release of acetylcholine, causing flaccid paralysis, in contrast to the spastic paralysis caused by tentoxilysin. In peptidase family M27 (tentoxilysin family)
HISTORY     EC 3.4.24.69 created 1995
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8226912]
  AUTHORS   Schiavo G, Rossetto O, Catsicas S, Polverino de Laureto P, DasGupta BR, Benfenati F, Montecucco C.
  TITLE     Identification of the nerve terminal targets of botulinum neurotoxin serotypes A, D, and E.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 268 (1993) 23784-7.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8243676]
  AUTHORS   Schiavo G, Santucci A, Dasgupta BR, Mehta PP, Jontes J, Benfenati F, Wilson MC, Montecucco C.
  TITLE     Botulinum neurotoxins serotypes A and E cleave SNAP-25 at distinct COOH-terminal peptide bonds.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 335 (1993) 99-103.
  ORGANISM  Clostridium botulinum
  SEQUENCE  [up:P10845 Q00496]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8505288]
  AUTHORS   Schiavo G, Shone CC, Rossetto O, Alexander FC, Montecucco C.
  TITLE     Botulinum neurotoxin serotype F is a zinc endopeptidase specific for VAMP/synaptobrevin.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 268 (1993) 11516-9.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:8051110]
  AUTHORS   Schiavo G, Malizio C, Trimble WS, Polverino de Laureto P, Milan G, Sugiyama H, Johnson EA, Montecucco C.
  TITLE     Botulinum G neurotoxin cleaves VAMP/synaptobrevin at a single Ala-Ala peptide bond.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 269 (1994) 20213-6.
  ORGANISM  Clostridium botulinum
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:7527117]
  AUTHORS   Montecucco C, Schiavo G.
  TITLE     Mechanism of action of tetanus and botulinum neurotoxins.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 13 (1994) 1-8.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:7674951]
  AUTHORS   Schiavo G, Montecucco C.
  TITLE     Tetanus and botulism neurotoxins: isolation and assay.
  JOURNAL   Methods. Enzymol. 248 (1995) 643-52.
ORTHOLOGY   K06011  botulinum neurotoxin
GENES       CBO: CBO0806(atx)
            CBA: CLB_0848(boNT_A1)
            CBH: CLC_0862(boNT_A1)
            CBY: CLM_0897(botA)
            CBL: CLK_A0076(boNT_A3)
            CBK: CLL_0038
            CBB: CLD_A0068(boNT_B)
            CBI: CLJ_0004(boNT_BvA4) CLJ_0133(boNT_BvB)
            CBN: CbC4_4096
            CBT: CLH_1110(boNT_E3)
            CBF: CLI_0851(boNT_A1)
            CBM: CBF_0821(boNT_F)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.69
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.24.69
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.24.69
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.69
            CAS: 107231-12-9
///
