ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.74                Enzyme
NAME        venombin A;
            alpha-fibrinogenase;
            habutobin;
            zinc metalloproteinase Cbfib1.1;
            zinc metalloproteinase Cbfib1.2;
            zinc metalloproteinase Cbfib2;
            ancrod;
            (see also Comments)
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Selective cleavage of Arg! bond in fibrinogen, to form fibrin, and release fibrinopeptide A. The specificity of further degradation of fibrinogen varies with species origin of the enzyme
COMMENT     A somewhat thrombin-like enzyme from venoms of snakes of the viper/rattlesnake group. Species variants of the enzyme include ancrod from Agkistrodon rhodostoma (Malayan pit viper) (formerly EC 3.4.21.28) [1], batroxobin from Bothrops atrox (South American pit viper) (formerly EC 3.4.21.29) [2,5] and crotalase from Crotalus adamanteus (Eastern diamondback rattlesnake) (formerly EC 3.4.21.30) [3,4]. In peptidase family S1 (trypsin family). Does not require activation by Ca2+
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.74 created 1992 (EC 3.4.21.28, EC 3.4.21.29 and 3.4.21.30 all created 1978 and incorporated 1992)
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1011992]
  AUTHORS   Nolan C, Hall LS, Barlow GH.
  TITLE     Ancrod, the coagulating enzyme from Malayan pit viper (Agkistrodon rhodostoma) venom.
  JOURNAL   Methods. Enzymol. 45 (1976) 205-13.
  ORGANISM  Agkistrodon rhodostoma
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:1011993]
  AUTHORS   Stocker K, Barlow GH.
  TITLE     The coagulant enzyme from Bothrops atrox venom (batroxobin).
  JOURNAL   Methods. Enzymol. 45 (1976) 214-23.
  ORGANISM  Bothrops atrox
  SEQUENCE  [up:P04971]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:7043462]
  AUTHORS   Markland FS, Kettner C, Schiffman S, Shaw E, Bajwa SS, Reddy KN, Kirakossian H, Patkos GB, Theodor I, Pirkle H.
  TITLE     Kallikrein-like activity of crotalase, a snake venom enzyme that clots fibrinogen.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 79 (1982) 1688-92.
  ORGANISM  Crotalus adamanteus
  SEQUENCE  [up:F8S114]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:2934864]
  AUTHORS   Simmons G, Bundalian M, Theodor I, Martinoli J, Pirkle H.
  TITLE     Action of crotalase, an enzyme with thrombin-like and kallikrein-like specificities, on tripeptide nitroanilide derivatives.
  JOURNAL   Thromb. Res. 40 (1985) 555-61.
  ORGANISM  Crotalus adamanteus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:3163691]
  AUTHORS   Itoh N, Tanaka N, Funakoshi I, Kawasaki T, Mihashi S, Yamashina I.
  TITLE     Organization of the gene for batroxobin, a thrombin-like snake venom enzyme. Homology with the trypsin/kallikrein gene family.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 263 (1988) 7628-31.
  ORGANISM  Bothrops atrox, Bothrops moojeni
  SEQUENCE  [up:P04971]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.74
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.74
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.74
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.74
            CAS: 146240-35-9
///
