ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.106               Enzyme
NAME        hepsin
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Cleavage after basic amino-acid residues, with Arg strongly preferred to Lys
COMMENT     This type-II membrane-associated serine peptidase has been implicated in cell growth and development [1,3]. The enzyme has been shown to activate blood coagulation factor VII by cleavage of the Arg152!Ile153 peptide bound in BHK cells, thus indicating a possible role in the initiation of blood coagulation [2]. There is no cleavage after aromatic or aliphatic residues [1]. The occupancy of the S2 site is an absolute requirement for catalysis and a basic residue at that site is preferred to an aliphatic residue. The nature of the residue at S3 also affects hydrolysis, with Gln being much more favourable than Ala [1]. Belongs in peptidase family S1A.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.106 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9003440]
  AUTHORS   Zhukov A, Hellman U, Ingelman-Sundberg M.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of hepsin from rat liver microsomes.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1337 (1997) 85-95.
  ORGANISM  Rattus norvegicus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7814421]
  AUTHORS   Kazama Y, Hamamoto T, Foster DC, Kisiel W.
  TITLE     Hepsin, a putative membrane-associated serine protease, activates human factor VII and initiates a pathway of blood coagulation on the cell surface leading to thrombin formation.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 270 (1995) 66-72.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8346233]
  AUTHORS   Torres-Rosado A, O'Shea KS, Tsuji A, Chou SH, Kurachi K.
  TITLE     Hepsin, a putative cell-surface serine protease, is required for mammalian cell growth.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 90 (1993) 7181-5.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:3249]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.106
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.106
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.106
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.106
            CAS: 112398-23-9
///
