ENTRY       EC 3.4.24.74                Enzyme
NAME        fragilysin;
            Bacteroides fragilis (entero)toxin
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Metalloendopeptidases
REACTION    Broad proteolytic specificity, bonds hydrolysed including -Gly!Leu-, -Met!Leu-, -Phe!Leu-, -Cys!Leu-, Leu!Gly
COMMENT     Thought to be a cause of diarrhoea in animals and humans. Hydrolyses extracellular matrix proteins, and disrupts tight junctions of intestinal epithelial cells. Also degrades intracellular, cytoskeletal proteins actin, myosin and others. In peptidase family M10 (interstitial collagenase family)
HISTORY     EC 3.4.24.74 created 1997
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:7806355]
  AUTHORS   Moncrief JS, Obiso R Jr, Barroso LA, Kling JJ, Wright RL, Van Tassell RL, Lyerly DM, Wilkins TD.
  TITLE     The enterotoxin of Bacteroides fragilis is a metalloprotease.
  JOURNAL   Infect. Immun. 63 (1995) 175-81.
  ORGANISM  Bacteroides fragilis
  SEQUENCE  [up:P54355]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7558286]
  AUTHORS   Obiso RJ Jr, Lyerly DM, Van Tassell RL, Wilkins TD.
  TITLE     Proteolytic activity of the Bacteroides fragilis enterotoxin causes fluid secretion and intestinal damage in vivo.
  JOURNAL   Infect. Immun. 63 (1995) 3820-6.
  ORGANISM  Bacteroides fragilis
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8557328]
  AUTHORS   Donelli G, Fabbri A, Fiorentini C.
  TITLE     Bacteroides fragilis enterotoxin induces cytoskeletal changes and surface blebbing in HT-29 cells.
  JOURNAL   Infect. Immun. 64 (1996) 113-9.
  ORGANISM  Bacteroides fragilis
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:8945541]
  AUTHORS   Koshy SS, Montrose MH, Sears CL.
  TITLE     Human intestinal epithelial cells swell and demonstrate actin rearrangement in response to the metalloprotease toxin of Bacteroides fragilis.
  JOURNAL   Infect. Immun. 64 (1996) 5022-8.
  ORGANISM  Bacteroides fragilis
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:9011050]
  AUTHORS   Kling JJ, Wright RL, Moncrief JS, Wilkins TD.
  TITLE     Cloning and characterization of the gene for the metalloprotease enterotoxin of Bacteroides fragilis.
  JOURNAL   FEMS. Microbiol. Lett. 146 (1997) 279-84.
  ORGANISM  Bacteroides fragilis
  SEQUENCE  [up:P54355]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.74
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.24.74
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.24.74
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.74
            CAS: 188596-63-6
///
