ENTRY       EC 3.4.22.64                Enzyme
NAME        caspase-11;
            CASP-11
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Cysteine endopeptidases
REACTION    Strict requirement for Asp at the P1 position and has a preferred cleavage sequence of (Ile/Leu/Val/Phe)-Gly-His-Asp!
COMMENT     This murine enzyme is part of the family of inflammatory caspases, which also includes caspase-1 (EC 3.4.22.36), caspase-4 (EC 3.4.22.57) and caspase-5 (EC 3.4.22.58) in humans and caspase-12, caspase-13 and caspase-14 in mice. Contains a caspase-recruitment domain (CARD) in its N-terminal prodomain, which plays a role in procaspase activation. Like caspase-5, but unlike caspase-4, this enzyme can be induced by lipopolysaccharide [1]. This enzyme not only activates caspase-1, which is required for the maturation of proinflammatory cytokines such as interleukin-1beta (IL-1beta) and IL-18, but it also activates caspase-3 (EC 3.4.22.56), which leads to cellular apoptosis under pathological conditions [1,2]. Belongs in peptidase family C14.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.22.64 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10791975]
  AUTHORS   Kang SJ, Wang S, Hara H, Peterson EP, Namura S, Amin-Hanjani S, Huang Z, Srinivasan A, Tomaselli KJ, Thornberry NA, Moskowitz MA, Yuan J.
  TITLE     Dual role of caspase-11 in mediating activation of caspase-1 and caspase-3 under pathological conditions.
  JOURNAL   J. Cell. Biol. 149 (2000) 613-22.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:11684090]
  AUTHORS   Hur J, Kim SY, Kim H, Cha S, Lee MS, Suk K.
  TITLE     Induction of caspase-11 by inflammatory stimuli in rat astrocytes: lipopolysaccharide induction through p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase pathway.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 507 (2001) 157-62.
  ORGANISM  Rattus norvegicus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9491891]
  AUTHORS   Wang S, Miura M, Jung YK, Zhu H, Li E, Yuan J.
  TITLE     Murine caspase-11, an ICE-interacting protease, is essential for the activation of ICE.
  JOURNAL   Cell. 92 (1998) 501-9.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16670335]
  AUTHORS   Endo M, Mori M, Akira S, Gotoh T.
  TITLE     C/EBP homologous protein (CHOP) is crucial for the induction of caspase-11 and the pathogenesis of lipopolysaccharide-induced inflammation.
  JOURNAL   J. Immunol. 176 (2006) 6245-53.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
  SEQUENCE  [mmu:12363]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:11104820]
  AUTHORS   Chang HY, Yang X.
  TITLE     Proteases for cell suicide: functions and regulation of caspases.
  JOURNAL   Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev. 64 (2000) 821-46.
ORTHOLOGY   K12808  caspase 11
GENES       MMU: 12363(Casp4)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.64
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.22.64
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.22.64
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.64
///
