ENTRY       EC 3.4.24.68                Enzyme
NAME        tentoxilysin;
            tetanus neurotoxin
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Metalloendopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of -Gln76!Phe- bond in synaptobrevin (also known as neuronal vesicle-associated membrane protein, VAMP)
COMMENT     Zinc enzyme produced by Clostridium tetani. Proenzyme of 150 kDa is processed to disulfide-linked subunits of 100 and 50 kDa, the latter being responsible for the endopeptidase activity. Weakly inhibited by captopril, and phosphoramidon. The clostridial neurotoxins disable the neuroexocytosis apparatus, and have been described as the most toxic substances known. Tentoxilysin acts at the spinal inhibitory interneurons, blocking the release of various neurotransmitters to produce spastic paralysis. Type example of peptidase family M27 (tentoxilysin family)
HISTORY     EC 3.4.24.68 created 1995
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1376283]
  AUTHORS   Izumi H, Adachi T, Fujii N, Matsuda T, Nakamura R, Tanaka K, Urisu A, Kurosawa Y.
  TITLE     Nucleotide sequence of a cDNA clone encoding a major allergenic protein in rice seeds. Homology of the deduced amino acid sequence with members of alpha-amylase/trypsin inhibitor family.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 302 (1992) 213-6.
  ORGANISM  Oryza sativa japonica
  SEQUENCE  [osa:4342722]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:1331807]
  AUTHORS   Schiavo G, Benfenati F, Poulain B, Rossetto O, Polverino de Laureto P, DasGupta BR, Montecucco C.
  TITLE     Tetanus and botulinum-B neurotoxins block neurotransmitter release by proteolytic cleavage of synaptobrevin.
  JOURNAL   Nature. 359 (1992) 832-5.
  ORGANISM  Clostridium tetani
  SEQUENCE  [ctc:pE88_60]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:1429690]
  AUTHORS   Schiavo G, Rossetto O, Santucci A, DasGupta BR, Montecucco C.
  TITLE     Botulinum neurotoxins are zinc proteins.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 267 (1992) 23479-83.
  ORGANISM  Clostridium botulinum
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:7527117]
  AUTHORS   Montecucco C, Schiavo G.
  TITLE     Mechanism of action of tetanus and botulinum neurotoxins.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 13 (1994) 1-8.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:7674951]
  AUTHORS   Schiavo G, Montecucco C.
  TITLE     Tetanus and botulism neurotoxins: isolation and assay.
  JOURNAL   Methods. Enzymol. 248 (1995) 643-52.
ORTHOLOGY   K08644  tentoxilysin
GENES       CTC: pE88_60(tetX)
            CTET: BN906_02977(tetX)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.68
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.24.68
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.24.68
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.68
            CAS: 107231-12-9
///
