ENTRY       EC 3.4.23.41                Enzyme
NAME        yapsin 1;
            yeast aspartic protease 3;
            Yap3 gene product (Saccharomyces cerevisiae)
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Aspartic endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolyses various precursor proteins with Arg or Lys in P1, and commonly Arg or Lys also in P2. The P3 amino acid is usually non-polar, but otherwise additional basic amino acids are favourable in both non-prime and prime positions
COMMENT     In peptidase family A1 of pepsin, and weakly inhibited by pepstatin. Can partially substitute for kexin in a deficient strain of yeast. The homologous product of the Mkc7 gene (Saccharomyces cerevisiae) has similar catalytic activity and has been termed yapsin 2 [2]
HISTORY     EC 3.4.23.41 created 2000
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8626758]
  AUTHORS   Cawley NX, Chen HC, Beinfeld MC, Loh YP.
  TITLE     Specificity and kinetic studies on the cleavage of various prohormone mono- and paired-basic residue sites by yeast aspartic protease 3.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 271 (1996) 4168-76.
  ORGANISM  Saccharomyces cerevisiae
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Fuller, R.S.
  TITLE     Yapsin 2.
  JOURNAL   In: Barrett, A.J., Rawlings, N.D. and Woessner, J.F. (Eds.), Handbook of Proteolytic Enzymes, Academic Press, London, 1998, p. 908-909.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9485427]
  AUTHORS   Olsen V, Guruprasad K, Cawley NX, Chen HC, Blundell TL, Loh YP.
  TITLE     Cleavage efficiency of the novel aspartic protease yapsin 1 (Yap3p) enhanced for substrates with arginine residues flanking the P1 site: correlation with electronegative active-site pockets predicted by molecular modeling.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 37 (1998) 2768-77.
  ORGANISM  Saccharomyces cerevisiae
  SEQUENCE  [sce:YLR120C]
ORTHOLOGY   K06009  yapsin 1
GENES       SCE: YDR144C(MKC7) YLR120C(YPS1)
            AGO: AGOS_AGL192W
            KLA: KLLA0E04049g
            LTH: KLTH0G12386g
            PPA: PAS_chr4_0584
            VPO: Kpol_543p61
            ZRO: ZYRO0F10230g
            CGR: CAGL0M04191g
            DHA: DEHA2A11858g
            PIC: PICST_68459
            PGU: PGUG_01925
            LEL: LELG_02108
            CLU: CLUG_03179
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.41
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.23.41
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.23.41
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.41
            CAS: 205132-58-7
///
