ENTRY       EC 3.4.23.21                Enzyme
NAME        rhizopuspepsin;
            Rhizopus aspartic proteinase;
            neurase;
            Rhizopus acid protease;
            Rhizopus acid proteinase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Aspartic endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of proteins with broad specificity similar to that of pepsin A, preferring hydrophobic residues at P1 and P1'. Clots milk and activates trypsinogen. Does not cleave Gln4-His, but does cleave His10!Leu and Val12!Glu in B chain of insulin
COMMENT     From the zygomycete fungus Rhizopus chinensis. A similar endopeptidase is found in R. niveus [2]. In peptidase family A1 (pepsin A family).
HISTORY     EC 3.4.23.21 created 1992 (EC 3.4.23.6 created 1992 (EC 3.4.23.6 created 1961 as EC 3.4.4.17, transferred 1972 to EC 3.4.23.6, modified 1981 [EC 3.4.23.7, EC 3.4.23.8, EC 3.4.23.9, EC 3.4.23.10, EC 3.4.99.1, EC 3.4.99.15 and EC 3.4.99.25 all created 1972 and incorporated 1978], part incorporated 1992)
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Tsuru, D., Hattori, A., Tsuji, H., Yamamoto, T. and Fukumoto, J.
  TITLE     Studies on mold proteases. Part II. Substrate specificity of acid protease of Rhizopus chinensis.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 33 (1969) 1419-1426.
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Kurono, Y., Chidimatsu, M., Horikoshi, K. and Ikeda, Y.
  TITLE     Isolation of a protease from a Rhizopus product.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 35 (1971) 1668-1675.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:6751894]
  AUTHORS   Ohtsuru M, Tang J, Delaney R.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of rhizopuspepsin isozymes from a liquid culture of Rhizopus chinensis.
  JOURNAL   Int. J. Biochem. 14 (1982) 925-32.
  ORGANISM  Rhizopus chinensis
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:3313384]
  AUTHORS   Suguna K, Padlan EA, Smith CW, Carlson WD, Davies DR.
  TITLE     Binding of a reduced peptide inhibitor to the aspartic proteinase from Rhizopus chinensis: implications for a mechanism of action.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 84 (1987) 7009-13.
  ORGANISM  Rhizopus chinensis
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.21
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.23.21
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.23.21
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.21
            CAS: 9074-09-3
///
