ENTRY       EC 3.4.23.32                Enzyme
NAME        scytalidopepsin B;
            Scytalidium aspartic proteinase B;
            Ganoderma lucidum carboxyl proteinase;
            Ganoderma lucidum aspartic proteinase;
            Scytalidium lignicolum aspartic proteinase B;
            SLB
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Aspartic endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of proteins with broad specificity, cleaving Phe24!Phe, but not Leu15-Tyr and Phe25-Tyr in the B chain of insulin
COMMENT     A second endopeptidase from Scytalidium lignicolum (see scytalidopepsin A) that is insensitive to pepstatin and methyl 2-diazoacetamidohexanoate. 1,2-Epoxy-3-(p-nitrophenoxy)propane reacts with Glu53, which replaces one of the aspartic residues at the active centre. One of the smallest aspartic endopeptidases active as the monomer, with Mr 22,000. Similarly inhibitor-resistant endopeptidases are found in the basidiomycetes Lentinus edodes [1] and Ganoderma lucidum [3], and in Polyporus tulipiferae [4], a second endopeptidase distinct from polyporopepsin, but these are of typical aspartic endopeptidase size, Mr about 36,000. Type example of peptidase family G1.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.23.32 created 1992
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Terashita, T., Oda, K., Kono, M. and Murao, S.
  TITLE     Streptomyces pepsin inhibitor-insensitive carboxyl proteinase from Lentinus edodes.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 45 (1981) 1937-1943.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:6370989]
  AUTHORS   Maita T, Nagata S, Matsuda G, Maruta S, Oda K, Murao S, Tsuru D.
  TITLE     Complete amino acid sequence of Scytalidium lignicolum acid protease B.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 95 (1984) 465-75.
  ORGANISM  Scytalidium lignicolum
  SEQUENCE  [up:P15369]
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   Terashita, T., Oda, K., Kono, M. and Murao, S.
  TITLE     Streptomyces pepsin inhibitor-insensitive carboxyl proteinase from Ganoderma lucidum.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 48 (1984) 1029-1035.
REFERENCE   4
  AUTHORS   Kobayashi, H., Kusakabe, I. and Murakami, K.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of a pepstatin-insensitive carboxyl proteinase from Polyporus tulipiferae (Irpex lacteus).
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 49 (1985) 2393-2397.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:3519605]
  AUTHORS   Tsuru D, Shimada S, Maruta S, Yoshimoto T, Oda K, Murao S, Miyata T, Iwanaga S.
  TITLE     Isolation and amino acid sequence of a peptide containing an epoxide-reactive residue from the thermolysin-digest of Scytalidium lignicolum acid protease B.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 99 (1986) 1537-9.
  ORGANISM  Scytalidium lignicolum
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.32
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.23.32
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.23.32
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.32
            CAS: 104781-89-7
///
