ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.84                Enzyme
NAME        limulus clotting factor _overbar_C_;
            factor C;
            limulus factor C
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Selective cleavage of -Arg103!Ser- and -Ile124!Ile- bonds in limulus clotting factor B to form factor _overbar_B_. Cleavage of -Pro-Arg! bonds in synthetic substrates
COMMENT     From the hemocyte granules of the horseshoe crabs Limulus and Tachypleus. Factor C is activated by Gram-negative bacterial lipopolysaccharides and chymotrypsin. Inhibited by antithrombin III. In peptidase family S1 (trypsin family)
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.84 created 1993
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3512266]
  AUTHORS   Nakamura T, Morita T, Iwanaga S.
  TITLE     Lipopolysaccharide-sensitive serine-protease zymogen (factor C) found in Limulus hemocytes. Isolation and characterization.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 154 (1986) 511-21.
  ORGANISM  Limulus polyphemus, Tachypleus tridentatus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:2007602]
  AUTHORS   Muta T, Miyata T, Misumi Y, Tokunaga F, Nakamura T, Toh Y, Ikehara Y, Iwanaga S.
  TITLE     Limulus factor C. An endotoxin-sensitive serine protease zymogen with a mosaic structure of complement-like, epidermal growth factor-like, and lectin-like domains.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 266 (1991) 6554-61.
  ORGANISM  Limulus sp.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:2016264]
  AUTHORS   Tokunaga F, Nakajima H, Iwanaga S.
  TITLE     Further studies on lipopolysaccharide-sensitive serine protease zymogen (factor C): its isolation from Limulus polyphemus hemocytes and identification as an intracellular zymogen activated by alpha-chymotrypsin, not by trypsin.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 109 (1991) 150-7.
  ORGANISM  Limulus polyphemus, Tachypleus tridentatus
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.84
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.84
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.84
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.84
            CAS: 115743-27-6
///
