ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.103               Enzyme
NAME        physarolisin;
            Dictyostelium discoideum aspartic proteinase;
            Dictyostelium discoideum aspartic proteinase E;
            Physarum flavicomum aspartic proteinase;
            Physarum polycephalum acid proteinase;
            Physarum aspartic proteinase;
            physaropepsin
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Milk clotting activity. Preferential cleavage of Gly8!Ser in B chain of insulin most rapidly, followed by Leu11!Val, Cys(SO3H)19!Gly and Phe24!Phe. No action on Ac-Phe-Tyr(I)2.
COMMENT     Belongs in peptidase family S53. From the slime mold Physarum polycephalum. Is not inhibited by pepstatin, but is blocked by methyl 2-diazoacetamidohexanoate. Closely similar enzymes are found in Dictyostelium discoideum and P. flavicomum. Formerly included in EC 3.4.23.6.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.103 created 1992 as EC 3.4.23.27 (EC 3.4.23.6 created 1992 (EC 3.4.23.6 created 1961 as EC 3.4.4.17, transferred 1972 to EC 3.4.23.6, modified 1981 [EC 3.4.23.7, EC 3.4.23.8, EC 3.4.23.9, EC 3.4.23.10, EC 3.4.99.1, EC 3.4.99.15 and EC 3.4.99.25 all created 1972 and incorporated 1978], part incorporated 1992), transferred 2003 to EC 3.4.21.103
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Henney, H.R. and Tavana, G.
  TITLE     Purification and some properties of an intracellular acid (carboxyl) proteinase from differentiating haploid cells of Physarum flavicomum.
  JOURNAL   Exp. Mycol. 6 (1982) 161-170.
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Murakami-Murofushi, K., Hiratsuka, A. and Ohta, J.
  TITLE     A novel acid protease from haploid amoebae of Physarum polycephalum, and its changes during mating and subsequent differentiation into diploid plasmodia.
  JOURNAL   Cell Struct. Funct. 9 (1984) 311-315.
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   North, M.J. and Whyte, A.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of two acid proteinases from Dictyostelium discoideum.
  JOURNAL   J. Gen. Microbiol. 130 (1984) 123-134.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12673349]
  AUTHORS   Wlodawer A, Li M, Gustchina A, Oyama H, Dunn BM, Oda K.
  TITLE     Structural and enzymatic properties of the sedolisin family of serine-carboxyl peptidases.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Biochim. Pol. 50 (2003) 81-102.
  ORGANISM  Physarum polycephalum
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:12589815]
  AUTHORS   Nishii W, Ueki T, Miyashita R, Kojima M, Kim YT, Sasaki N, Murakami-Murofushi K, Takahashi K.
  TITLE     Structural and enzymatic characterization of physarolisin (formerly physaropepsin) proves that it is a unique serine-carboxyl proteinase.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 301 (2003) 1023-9.
  ORGANISM  Physarum polycephalum
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8MZS4]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.103
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.103
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.103
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.103
            CAS: 94949-28-7
///
