ENTRY       EC 3.4.22.33                Enzyme
NAME        fruit bromelain;
            juice bromelain;
            ananase;
            bromelase;
            bromelin;
            extranase;
            juice bromelain;
            pinase;
            pineapple enzyme;
            traumanase;
            fruit bromelain FA2
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Cysteine endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of proteins with broad specificity for peptide bonds. Bz-Phe-Val-Arg!NHMec is a good synthetic substrate, but there is no action on Z-Arg-Arg-NHMec (c.f. stem bromelain)
COMMENT     From the pineapple plant, Ananas comosus. Scarcely inhibited by chicken cystatin. Another cysteine endopeptidase, with similar action on small molecule substrates, pinguinain, is obtained from the related plant, Bromelia pinguin, but pinguinain differs from fruit bromelain in being inhibited by chicken cystatin [4].
HISTORY     EC 3.4.22.33 created 1965 as EC 3.4.4.24, transferred 1972 to EC 3.4.22.4, part transferred 1992 to EC 3.4.22.33
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:4127920]
  AUTHORS   Sasaki M, Kato T, Iida S.
  TITLE     Antigenic determinant common to four kinds of thiol proteases of plant origin.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 74 (1973) 635-7.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:956152]
  AUTHORS   Yamada F, Takahashi N, Murachi T.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of a proteinase from pineapple fruit, fruit bromelain FA2.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 79 (1976) 1223-34.
  ORGANISM  Ananas comosus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:4044551]
  AUTHORS   Ota S, Muta E, Katahira Y, Okamoto Y.
  TITLE     Reinvestigation of fractionation and some properties of the proteolytically active components of stem and fruit bromelains.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 98 (1985) 219-28.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:2327970]
  AUTHORS   Rowan AD, Buttle DJ, Barrett AJ.
  TITLE     The cysteine proteinases of the pineapple plant.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 266 (1990) 869-75.
  ORGANISM  Ananas comosus
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.33
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.22.33
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.22.33
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.33
            CAS: 9001-00-7
///
