ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.104               Enzyme
NAME        mannan-binding lectin-associated serine protease-2;
            MASP-2;
            MASP2;
            MBP-associated serine protease-2;
            mannose-binding lectin-associated serine protease-2;
            p100;
            mannan-binding lectin-associated serine peptidase 2
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Selective cleavage after Arg223 in complement component C2 (-Ser-Leu-Gly-Arg!Lys-Ile-Gln-Ile) and after Arg76 in complement component C4 (-Gly-Leu-Gln-Arg!Ala-Leu-Glu-Ile)
COMMENT     Mannan-binding lectin (MBL) recognizes patterns of neutral carbohydrates, such as mannose and N-acetylglucosamine, on a wide range of microbial surfaces and is able to initiate activation of the lectin pathway of complement [7]. This enzyme displays C_overbar_1s_-like esterolytic activity (cf. EC 3.4.21.42, complement subcomponent C_overbar_1s_). It also cleaves C4 and C2 with efficiencies that are relatively higher than those of EC 3.4.21.42 [3]. Belongs in peptidase family S1A.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.104 created 2005
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1460414]
  AUTHORS   Matsushita M, Fujita T.
  TITLE     Activation of the classical complement pathway by mannose-binding protein in association with a novel C1s-like serine protease.
  JOURNAL   J. Exp. Med. 176 (1992) 1497-502.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9087411]
  AUTHORS   Thiel S, Vorup-Jensen T, Stover CM, Schwaeble W, Laursen SB, Poulsen K, Willis AC, Eggleton P, Hansen S, Holmskov U, Reid KB, Jensenius JC.
  TITLE     A second serine protease associated with mannan-binding lectin that activates complement.
  JOURNAL   Nature. 386 (1997) 506-10.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:10747]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11527969]
  AUTHORS   Rossi V, Cseh S, Bally I, Thielens NM, Jensenius JC, Arlaud GJ.
  TITLE     Substrate specificities of recombinant mannan-binding lectin-associated serine proteases-1 and -2.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 276 (2001) 40880-7.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12538697]
  AUTHORS   Ambrus G, Gal P, Kojima M, Szilagyi K, Balczer J, Antal J, Graf L, Laich A, Moffatt BE, Schwaeble W, Sim RB, Zavodszky P.
  TITLE     Natural substrates and inhibitors of mannan-binding lectin-associated serine protease-1 and -2: a study on recombinant catalytic fragments.
  JOURNAL   J. Immunol. 170 (2003) 1374-82.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15364579]
  AUTHORS   Harmat V, Gal P, Kardos J, Szilagyi K, Ambrus G, Vegh B, Naray-Szabo G, Zavodszky P.
  TITLE     The structure of MBL-associated serine protease-2 reveals that identical substrate specificities of C1s and MASP-2 are realized through different sets of enzyme-substrate interactions.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 342 (2004) 1533-46.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:15060079]
  AUTHORS   Chen CB, Wallis R.
  TITLE     Two mechanisms for mannose-binding protein modulation of the activity of its associated serine proteases.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 279 (2004) 26058-65.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:15728497]
  AUTHORS   Teillet F, Dublet B, Andrieu JP, Gaboriaud C, Arlaud GJ, Thielens NM.
  TITLE     The two major oligomeric forms of human mannan-binding lectin: chemical characterization, carbohydrate-binding properties, and interaction with MBL-associated serine proteases.
  JOURNAL   J. Immunol. 174 (2005) 2870-7.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
ORTHOLOGY   K03993  mannan-binding lectin serine protease 2
GENES       HSA: 10747(MASP2)
            PTR: 736039(MASP2)
            PPS: 100981899(MASP2)
            GGO: 101126677(MASP2)
            PON: 100458970(MASP2)
            MCC: 722701(MASP2)
            MCF: 102131322(MASP2)
            MMU: 17175(Masp2)
            RNO: 64459(Masp2)
            CGE: 100756295 100770654
            HGL: 101696699(Masp2) 101706103
            TUP: 102488905(MASP2)
            CFA: 487447(MASP2)
            AML: 100466924
            FCA: 101099568(MASP2)
            PTG: 102955677(MASP2)
            BTA: 505819(MASP2)
            BOM: 102280596(MASP2)
            PHD: 102330968 102331327(MASP2)
            CHX: 102169785(MASP2)
            SSC: 100302537(MASP2)
            CFR: 102513488(MASP2)
            ECB: 100056770(MASP2)
            MYB: 102250852 102255311
            MYD: 102764933(MASP2)
            PALE: 102885750(MASP2)
            MDO: 100018957(MASP2)
            SHR: 100932261(MASP2)
            OAA: 100079601(MASP2)
            GGA: 407089(MASP2)
            MGP: 100547191(MASP2)
            PHI: 102110924(MASP2)
            APLA: 101801331(MASP2)
            FPG: 101919004(MASP2)
            FCH: 102051305(MASP2)
            CLV: 102091890(MASP2)
            ASN: 102370755(MASP2)
            PSS: 102453425(MASP2)
            CMY: 102929438(MASP2)
            XLA: 373654(masp2)
            XTR: 496446(masp2)
            DRE: 560277(masp2)
            XMA: 102236233
            LCM: 102360645(MASP2)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.104
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.104
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.104
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.104
            CAS: 214915-16-9
///
