ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.117               Enzyme
NAME        stratum corneum chymotryptic enzyme;
            kallikrein 7;
            SCCE;
            KLK7;
            PRSS6;
            hK7
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Cleavage of proteins with aromatic side chains in the P1 position
COMMENT     This enzyme has wide substrate specificity, being able to degrade heat-denatured bovine casein and the alpha-chain of native human fibrinogen. It cleaves the B chain of bovine insulin at Leu6!Cya7, Tyr16!Leu17, Phe25!Tyr26 and Tyr26!Thr27 [1]. It is thought to play a role in the desquamation (skin-shedding) of the outer layer of skin, the stratum corneum, by degrading intercellular cohesive structures [1,2]. Belongs in peptidase family S1A.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.117 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:7794273]
  AUTHORS   Skytt A, Stromqvist M, Egelrud T.
  TITLE     Primary substrate specificity of recombinant human stratum corneum chymotryptic enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 211 (1995) 586-9.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:5650]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8393902]
  AUTHORS   Egelrud T.
  TITLE     Purification and preliminary characterization of stratum corneum chymotryptic enzyme: a proteinase that may be involved in desquamation.
  JOURNAL   J. Invest. Dermatol. 101 (1993) 200-4.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8034709]
  AUTHORS   Hansson L, Stromqvist M, Backman A, Wallbrandt P, Carlstein A, Egelrud T.
  TITLE     Cloning, expression, and characterization of stratum corneum chymotryptic enzyme. A skin-specific human serine proteinase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 269 (1994) 19420-6.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:5650]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:10974542]
  AUTHORS   Yousef GM, Scorilas A, Magklara A, Soosaipillai A, Diamandis EP.
  TITLE     The KLK7 (PRSS6) gene, encoding for the stratum corneum chymotryptic enzyme is a new member of the human kallikrein gene family - genomic characterization, mapping, tissue expression and hormonal regulation.
  JOURNAL   Gene. 254 (2000) 119-28.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:5650]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15191543]
  AUTHORS   Vasilopoulos Y, Cork MJ, Murphy R, Williams HC, Robinson DA, Duff GW, Ward SJ, Tazi-Ahnini R.
  TITLE     Genetic association between an AACC insertion in the 3'UTR of the stratum corneum chymotryptic enzyme gene and atopic dermatitis.
  JOURNAL   J. Invest. Dermatol. 123 (2004) 62-6.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Mus musculus
ORTHOLOGY   K08668  kallikrein 7 (chymotryptic, stratum corneum)
GENES       HSA: 5650(KLK7)
            PTR: 468973(KLK7)
            PPS: 100981390(KLK7)
            GGO: 101148068(KLK7)
            PON: 100173841(KLK7)
            MCC: 722683
            MCF: 102134711
            MMU: 23993(Klk7)
            RNO: 292852(Klk7)
            CGE: 100753553
            HGL: 101705516(Klk7)
            TUP: 102467699(KLK7)
            CFA: 611780(KLK7)
            AML: 100476432
            FCA: 101088894(KLK7)
            PTG: 102964470(KLK7)
            BTA: 506380(KLK7)
            BOM: 102282184(KLK7)
            PHD: 102315895(KLK7)
            CHX: 102178562(KLK7)
            SSC: 100359349(KLK7)
            ECB: 100146194(KLK7)
            MYB: 102249473 102249777 102250372 102251959
            MYD: 102764448 102764733(KLK7) 102768344 102768913
            PALE: 102897729(KLK7)
            MDO: 100012470(KLK7)
            SHR: 100933396 100933649
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.117
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.117
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.117
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.117
            CAS: 155215-90-0
///
