ENTRY       EC 3.4.22.44                Enzyme
NAME        nuclear-inclusion-a endopeptidase;
            potyvirus NIa protease
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Cysteine endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolyses glutaminyl bonds, and activity is further restricted by preferences for the amino acids in P6 - P1' that vary with the species of potyvirus, e.g. Glu-Xaa-Xaa-Tyr-Xaa-Gln!(Ser or Gly) for the enzyme from tobacco etch virus. The natural substrate is the viral polyprotein, but other proteins and oligopeptides containing the appropriate consensus sequence are also cleaved.
COMMENT     The potyviruses cause diseases in plants, and inclusion bodies appear in the host cell nuclei; protein a of the inclusion bodies is the endopeptidase. The enzyme finds practical use when encoded in vectors for the artificial expression of recombinant fusion proteins, since it can confer on them the capacity for autolytic cleavage. It is also reported that transgenic plants expressing the enzyme are resistant to viral infection. Type example of peptidase family C4.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.22.44 created 2000
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Fellers, J.P., Collins, G.B. and Hunt, A.G.
  TITLE     The NIa-proteinase of different plant potyviruses provides specific resistance to viral infection.
  JOURNAL   Crop Sci. 38 (1998) 1309-1319.
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Kim, D.-H. and Choi, K.Y.
  TITLE     Potyvirus NIa protease.
  JOURNAL   In: Barrett, A.J., Rawlings, N.D. and Woessner, J.F. (Eds.), Handbook of Proteolytic Enzymes, Academic Press, London, 1998, p. 721-723.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9648226]
  AUTHORS   Takahashi T, Nakanishi M, Yao Y, Uyeda I, Serizawa N.
  TITLE     Direct formation of human interleukin-11 by cis-acting system of plant virus protease in Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 62 (1998) 953-8.
  ORGANISM  clover yellow vein virus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:8955037]
  AUTHORS   Kim DH, Hwang DC, Kang BH, Lew J, Han J, Song BD, Choi KY.
  TITLE     Effects of internal cleavages and mutations in the C-terminal region of NIa protease of turnip mosaic potyvirus on the catalytic activity.
  JOURNAL   Virology. 226 (1996) 183-90.
  ORGANISM  turnip mosaic potyvirus
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.44
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.22.44
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.22.44
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.22.44
            CAS: 139946-51-3
///
