ENTRY       EC 3.4.23.23                Enzyme
NAME        mucorpepsin;
            Mucor rennin;
            Mucor aspartic proteinase;
            Mucor acid proteinase;
            Mucor acid protease;
            Mucor miehei aspartic proteinase;
            Mucor miehei aspartic protease;
            Mucor aspartic proteinase;
            Mucor pusillus emporase;
            Fromase 100;
            Mucor pusillus rennin;
            Fromase 46TL;
            Mucor miehei rennin
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Aspartic endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of proteins, favouring hydrophobic residues at P1 and P1'. Clots milk. Does not accept Lys at P1, and hence does not activate trypsinogen
COMMENT     Isolated from the zygomycete fungi Mucor pusillus and M. miehei. The two species variants show 83% sequence identity and are immunologically crossreactive. In peptidase family A1 (pepsin A family). Formerly included in EC 3.4.23.6
HISTORY     EC 3.4.23.23 created 1992 (EC 3.4.23.6 created 1992 (EC 3.4.23.6 created 1961 as EC 3.4.4.17, transferred 1972 to EC 3.4.23.6, modified 1981 [EC 3.4.23.7, EC 3.4.23.8, EC 3.4.23.9, EC 3.4.23.10, EC 3.4.99.1, EC 3.4.99.15 and EC 3.4.99.25 all created 1972 and incorporated 1978], part incorporated 1992)
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Arima, K., Yu, J. and Iwasaki, S.
  TITLE     Milk-clotting enzyme from Mucor pusillus var. lindt.
  JOURNAL   Methods Enzymol. 19 (1970) 446-459.
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Ottesen, M. and Rickert, W.
  TITLE     The acid protease of Mucor miehei.
  JOURNAL   Methods Enzymol. 19 (1970) 459-460.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:4573298]
  AUTHORS   Sternberg M.
  TITLE     Bond specificity, active site and milk clotting mechanism of the Mucor miehei protease.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 285 (1972) 383-92.
  ORGANISM  Mucor miehei
REFERENCE   4
  AUTHORS   Oka, T., Ishino, K., Tsuzuki, H., Morihara, K. and Arima, K.
  TITLE     On the specificity of a rennin-like enzyme from Mucor pusillus.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 37 (1973) 1177-1184.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:3042459]
  AUTHORS   Baudys M, Foundling S, Pavlik M, Blundell T, Kostka V.
  TITLE     Protein chemical characterization of Mucor pusillus aspartic proteinase. Amino acid sequence homology with the other aspartic proteinases, disulfide bond arrangement and site of carbohydrate attachment.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 235 (1988) 271-4.
  ORGANISM  Mucor pusillus
  SEQUENCE  [up:P09177]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.23
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.23.23
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.23.23
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.23
            CAS: 148465-73-0
///
