ENTRY       EC 3.4.24.62                Enzyme
NAME        magnolysin;
            bovine neurosecretory granule protease cleaving pro-oxytocin/neurophysin;
            pro-oxytocin/neurophysin convertase;
            prooxyphysin proteinase;
            pro-oxytocin convertase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Metalloendopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of polypeptides with Arg or Lys in P1 and P2, e.g. to hydrolyse pro-oxytocin at -Lys-Arg!Ala-Val-. The specificity further depends on the organization of a beta-turn-alpha-helix of nine or more residues containing the paired basic amino acids near the centre [3]
COMMENT     An endopeptidase of 58 kDa known from bovine pituitary neurosecretory granules and bovine and human corpus luteum [4,5]. Inhibited by EDTA [1]
HISTORY     EC 3.4.24.62 created 1995
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:2825769]
  AUTHORS   Clamagirand C, Creminon C, Fahy C, Boussetta H, Cohen P.
  TITLE     Partial purification and functional properties of an endoprotease from bovine neurosecretory granules cleaving proocytocin/neurophysin peptides at the basic amino acid doublet.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 26 (1987) 6018-23.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:3042797]
  AUTHORS   Creminon C, Rholam M, Boussetta H, Marrakchi N, Cohen P.
  TITLE     Synthetic peptide substrates as models to study a pro-ocytocin/neurophysin converting enzyme.
  JOURNAL   J. Chromatogr. 440 (1988) 439-48.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:2674120]
  AUTHORS   Brakch N, Boussetta H, Rholam M, Cohen P.
  TITLE     Processing endoprotease recognizes a structural feature at the cleavage site of peptide prohormones. The pro-ocytocin/neurophysin model.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 264 (1989) 15912-6.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:2659078]
  AUTHORS   Plevrakis I, Clamagirand C, Creminon C, Brakch N, Rholam M, Cohen P.
  TITLE     Proocytocin/neurophysin convertase from bovine neurohypophysis and corpus luteum secretory granules: complete purification, structure-function relationships, and competitive inhibitor.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 28 (1989) 2705-10.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:7931007]
  AUTHORS   Guillou MD, Camier M, Clamagirand C.
  TITLE     Evidence for the presence of pro-oxytocin/neurophysin-converting enzyme in the human ovary.
  JOURNAL   J. Endocrinol. 142 (1994) 345-52.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.62
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.24.62
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.24.62
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.62
            CAS: 162875-09-4
///
