ENTRY       EC 3.4.23.26                Enzyme
NAME        rhodotorulapepsin;
            Rhodotorula aspartic proteinase;
            Cladosporium acid protease;
            Cladosporium acid proteinase;
            Paecilomyces proteinase;
            Cladosporium aspartic proteinase;
            Paecilomyces proteinase;
            Rhodotorula glutinis aspartic proteinase;
            Rhodotorula glutinis acid proteinase;
            Rhodotorula glutinis aspartic proteinase II;
            Rhodotorula acid proteinase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Aspartic endopeptidases
REACTION    Specificity similar to that of pepsin A. Cleaves Z-Lys!Ala-Ala-Ala and activates trypsinogen
COMMENT     From the imperfect yeast Rhodotorula glutinis. Somewhat similar enzymes have been isolated from the imperfect yeast-like organism Cladosporium sp. [4,6] and the imperfect fungus Paecilomyces varioti [1,2].
HISTORY     EC 3.4.23.26 created 1992 (EC 3.4.23.6 created 1992 (EC 3.4.23.6 created 1961 as EC 3.4.4.17, transferred 1972 to EC 3.4.23.6, modified 1981 [EC 3.4.23.7, EC 3.4.23.8, EC 3.4.23.9, EC 3.4.23.10, EC 3.4.99.1, EC 3.4.99.15 and EC 3.4.99.25 all created 1972 and incorporated 1978], part incorporated 1992)
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Sawada, J.
  TITLE     Studies on the acid-protease of Paecilomyces varioti Bainier TPR-220. Part I. Crystallization of the acid-protease of Paecilomyces varioti Bainier TPR-220.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 27 (1963) 677-683.
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Sawada, J.
  TITLE     The acid-protease of Paecilomyces varioti. III. The specificity of the crystalline acid-protease on synthetic substrates.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 28 (1964) 869-875.
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   Kamada, M., Oda, K. and Murao, S.
  TITLE     The purification of the extracellular acid protease of Rhodotorula glutinis K-24 and its general properties.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 36 (1972) 1095-1101.
REFERENCE   4
  AUTHORS   Murao, S., Funakoshi, S. and Oda, K.
  TITLE     Purification, crystallization and some enzymatic properties of acid protease of Cladosporium sp. No. 45-2.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 36 (1972) 1327-1333.
REFERENCE   5
  AUTHORS   Oda, K., Kamada, M. and Murao, S.
  TITLE     Some physicochemical properties and substrate specificity of acid protease of Rhodotorula glutinis K-24.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 36 (1972) 1103-1108.
REFERENCE   6
  AUTHORS   Oda, K., Funakoshi, S. and Murao, S.
  TITLE     Some physicochemical properties and substrate specificity of acid protease isolated from Cladosporium sp. No. 45-2.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 37 (1973) 1723-1729.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:10290]
  AUTHORS   Takahashi K, Chang WJ.
  TITLE     The structure and function of acid proteases. V. Comparative studies on the specific inhibition of acid proteases by diazoacetyl-DL-norleucine methyl ester, 1,2-epoxy-3-(p-nitrophenoxy) propane and pepstatin.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 80 (1976) 497-506.
REFERENCE   8
  AUTHORS   Majima, E., Oda, K., Murao, S. and Ichishima, E.
  TITLE     Comparative study on the specificities of several fungal aspartic and acidic proteinases towards the tetradecapeptide of a renin substrate.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 52 (1988) 787-793.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.26
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.23.26
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.23.26
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.26
            CAS: 37259-59-9
///
