ENTRY       EC 3.4.24.40                Enzyme
NAME        serralysin;
            Pseudomonas aeruginosa alkaline proteinase;
            Escherichia freundii proteinase;
            Serratia marcescens extracellular proteinase;
            Serratia marcescens metalloproteinase;
            Pseudomonas aeruginosa alk. protease;
            Serratia marcescens metalloprotease
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Metalloendopeptidases
REACTION    Preferential cleavage of bonds with hydrophobic residues in P1'
COMMENT     A 50 kDa extracellular endopeptidase from Pseudomonas aeruginosa [1,2,6], Escherichia freundii [3], Serratia marcescens [4,5,6] and Erwinia chrysanthemi [7]. There is broad specificity in cleavage of the insulin B chain, with some species variations. The pH optimum for digesting various proteins is about 9 - 10. In peptidase family M10 (interstitial collagenase family). Formerly included in EC 3.4.24.4
HISTORY     EC 3.4.24.40 created 1972 as EC 3.4.24.4, part transferred 1992 to EC 3.4.24.40
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:4967801]
  AUTHORS   Morihara K, Tsuzuki H, Oka T.
  TITLE     Comparison of the specificities of various neutral proteinases from microorganisms.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 123 (1968) 572-88.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:4199986]
  AUTHORS   Morihara K, Tsuzuki H, Oka T.
  TITLE     On the specificity of Pseudomonas aeruginosa alkaline proteinase with synthetic peptides.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 309 (1973) 414-29.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas aeruginosa
  SEQUENCE  [pae:PA1249]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:4212288]
  AUTHORS   Nakajima M, Mizusawa K, Yoshida F.
  TITLE     Purification and properties of an extracellular proteinase of psychrophilic Escherichia freundii.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 44 (1974) 87-96.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia freundii
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:383155]
  AUTHORS   Decedue CJ, Broussard EA 2nd, Larson AD, Braymer HD.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of the extracellular proteinase of Serratia marcescens.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 569 (1979) 293-301.
  ORGANISM  Serratia marcescens
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:6380155]
  AUTHORS   Doerr M, Traub WH.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of two Serratia marcescens proteases.
  JOURNAL   Zentralbl. Bakteriol. Mikrobiol. Hyg. [A]. 257 (1984) 6-19.
  ORGANISM  Serratia marcescens
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:3016665]
  AUTHORS   Nakahama K, Yoshimura K, Marumoto R, Kikuchi M, Lee IS, Hase T, Matsubara H.
  TITLE     Cloning and sequencing of Serratia protease gene.
  JOURNAL   Nucleic. Acids. Res. 14 (1986) 5843-55.
  ORGANISM  Serratia marcescens
  SEQUENCE  [smaf:D781_0184]
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:2211513]
  AUTHORS   Dahler GS, Barras F, Keen NT.
  TITLE     Cloning of genes encoding extracellular metalloproteases from Erwinia chrysanthemi EC16.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 172 (1990) 5803-15.
  ORGANISM  Erwinia chrysanthemi
  SEQUENCE  [up:P19144]
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:2123832]
  AUTHORS   Okuda K, Morihara K, Atsumi Y, Takeuchi H, Kawamoto S, Kawasaki H, Suzuki K, Fukushima J.
  TITLE     Complete nucleotide sequence of the structural gene for alkaline proteinase from Pseudomonas aeruginosa IFO 3455.
  JOURNAL   Infect. Immun. 58 (1990) 4083-8.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas aeruginosa
  SEQUENCE  [pae:PA1249]
ORTHOLOGY   K01406  serralysin
GENES       YPP: YPDSF_3337
            SPE: Spro_0210 Spro_2387
            PSB: Psyr_3163
            PFL: PFL_3210(aprA)
            PEN: PSEEN1550(aprA)
            PMY: Pmen_4542
            RSH: Rsph17029_1872
            MMR: Mmar10_2493
            AVA: Ava_3643
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.40
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.24.40
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.24.40
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.40
            CAS: 70851-98-8
///
