ENTRY       EC 3.4.24.67                Enzyme
NAME        choriolysin H;
            teleost hatching enzyme (component);
            high choriolytic enzyme (HCE)
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Metalloendopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of the inner layer of fish egg envelope. Also hydrolysis of casein and small molecule substrates such as succinyl-Leu-Leu-Val-Tyr!7-(4-methyl)coumarylamide
COMMENT     Known from the teleost fish Oryzias latipes (medaka). Efficient dissolution of the egg membrane requires concerted action with choriolysin L. A 25.5 kDa peptidase in family M12 (astacin family)
HISTORY     EC 3.4.24.67 created 1995
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:4652273]
  AUTHORS   Yamagami K.
  TITLE     Isolation of a choriolytic enzyme (hatching enzyme) of the teleost, Oryzias latipes.
  JOURNAL   Dev. Biol. 29 (1972) 343-8.
  ORGANISM  Oryzias latipes
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:2656664]
  AUTHORS   Yasumasu S, Iuchi I, Yamagami K.
  TITLE     Purification and partial characterization of high choriolytic enzyme (HCE), a component of the hatching enzyme of the teleost, Oryzias latipes.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 105 (1989) 204-11.
  ORGANISM  Oryzias latipes
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:2751672]
  AUTHORS   Yasumasu S, Katow S, Umino Y, Iuchi I, Yamagami K.
  TITLE     A unique proteolytic action of HCE, a constituent protease of a fish hatching enzyme: tight binding to its natural substrate, egg envelope.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 162 (1989) 58-63.
  ORGANISM  Oryzias latipes
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:1397682]
  AUTHORS   Yasumasu S, Yamada K, Akasaka K, Mitsunaga K, Iuchi I, Shimada H, Yamagami K.
  TITLE     Isolation of cDNAs for LCE and HCE, two constituent proteases of the hatching enzyme of Oryzias latipes, and concurrent expression of their mRNAs during development.
  JOURNAL   Dev. Biol. 153 (1992) 250-8.
  ORGANISM  Oryzias latipes
  SEQUENCE  [ola:100529164 100049452]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:8112467]
  AUTHORS   Lee KS, Yasumasu S, Nomura K, Iuchi I.
  TITLE     HCE, a constituent of the hatching enzymes of Oryzias latipes embryos, releases unique proline-rich polypeptides from its natural substrate, the hardened chorion.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 339 (1994) 281-4.
  ORGANISM  Oryzias latipes
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.67
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.24.67
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.24.67
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.67
            CAS: 177529-16-7
///
