ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.120               Enzyme
NAME        oviductin;
            oviductal protease
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Preferential cleavage at Gly-Ser-Arg373! of glycoprotein gp43 in Xenopus laevis coelemic egg envelope to yield gp41
COMMENT     The egg envelope of the South African clawed frog (Xenopus laevis) is modified during transit of the egg through the pars rectus oviduct, changing the egg envelope from an unfertilizable form to a fertilizable form. This process involves the conversion of glycoprotein gp43 to gp41 (ZPC) by the pars recta protease oviductin. It is thought that the enzymically active protease molecule comprises the N-terminal protease domain coupled to two C-terminal CUB domains, which are related to the mammalian spermadhesin molecules implicated in mediating sperm-envelope interactions [2]. The enzyme is also found in the Japanese toad (Bufo japonicus) [3]. Belongs in peptidase family S1.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.120 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1581303]
  AUTHORS   Hardy DM, Hedrick JL.
  TITLE     Oviductin. Purification and properties of the oviductal protease that processes the molecular weight 43,000 glycoprotein of the Xenopus laevis egg envelope.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 31 (1992) 4466-72.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:10084976]
  AUTHORS   Lindsay LL, Wieduwilt MJ, Hedrick JL.
  TITLE     Oviductin, the Xenopus laevis oviductal protease that processes egg envelope glycoprotein gp43, increases sperm binding to envelopes, and is translated as part of an unusual mosaic protein composed of two protease and several CUB domains.
  JOURNAL   Biol. Reprod. 60 (1999) 989-95.
  ORGANISM  Xenopus laevis
  SEQUENCE  [xla:398108]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11846486]
  AUTHORS   Hiyoshi M, Takamune K, Mita K, Kubo H, Sugimoto Y, Katagiri C.
  TITLE     Oviductin, the oviductal protease that mediates gamete interaction by affecting the vitelline coat in Bufo japonicus: its molecular cloning and analyses of expression and posttranslational activation.
  JOURNAL   Dev. Biol. 243 (2002) 176-84.
  ORGANISM  Bufo japonicus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q90WD8]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.120
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.120
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.120
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.120
///
