ENTRY       EC 3.4.11.24                Enzyme
NAME        aminopeptidase S;
            Mername-AA022 peptidase;
            SGAP;
            aminopeptidase (Streptomyces griseus);
            Streptomyces griseus aminopeptidase;
            S. griseus AP;
            double-zinc aminopeptidase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Aminopeptidases
REACTION    Release of an N-terminal amino acid with a preference for large hydrophobic amino-terminus residues
COMMENT     Aminopeptidases are associated with many biological functions, including protein maturation, protein degradation, cell-cycle control and hormone-level regulation [3,4]. This enzyme contains two zinc molecules in its active site and is activated by Ca2+ [4]. In the presence of Ca2+, the best substrates are Leu-Phe, Leu-Ser, Leu-pNA (aminoacyl-p-nitroanilide), Phe-Phe-Phe and Phe-Phe [3]. Peptides with proline in the P1' position are not substrates [3]. Belongs in peptidase family M28.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.11.24 created 2008
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:2503378]
  AUTHORS   Spungin A, Blumberg S.
  TITLE     Streptomyces griseus aminopeptidase is a calcium-activated zinc metalloprotein. Purification and properties of the enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 183 (1989) 471-7.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces griseus
  SEQUENCE  [sgr:SGR_5809]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8444149]
  AUTHORS   Ben-Meir D, Spungin A, Ashkenazi R, Blumberg S.
  TITLE     Specificity of Streptomyces griseus aminopeptidase and modulation of activity by divalent metal ion binding and substitution.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 212 (1993) 107-12.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces griseus
  SEQUENCE  [sgr:SGR_5809]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16080009]
  AUTHORS   Arima J, Uesugi Y, Iwabuchi M, Hatanaka T.
  TITLE     Study on peptide hydrolysis by aminopeptidases from Streptomyces griseus, Streptomyces septatus and Aeromonas proteolytica.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 70 (2006) 541-7.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15280041]
  AUTHORS   Fundoiano-Hershcovitz Y, Rabinovitch L, Langut Y, Reiland V, Shoham G, Shoham Y.
  TITLE     Identification of the catalytic residues in the double-zinc aminopeptidase from Streptomyces griseus.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 571 (2004) 192-6.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:10771423]
  AUTHORS   Gilboa R, Greenblatt HM, Perach M, Spungin-Bialik A, Lessel U, Wohlfahrt G, Schomburg D, Blumberg S, Shoham G.
  TITLE     Interactions of Streptomyces griseus aminopeptidase with a methionine product analogue: a structural study at 1.53 A resolution.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 56 (2000) 551-8.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.11.24
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.11.24
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.11.24
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.11.24
///
