ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.99                Enzyme
NAME        spermosin
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolyses arginyl bonds, preferably with Pro in the P2 position
COMMENT     The enzyme from the ascidian (Prochordate) Halocynthia roretzi is localized in the sperm head, and released during sperm activation. A proline-rich region is involved in binding to the vitelline coat of the egg. Belongs in peptidase family S1 (trypsin family).
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.99 created 2001
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:6365918]
  AUTHORS   Sawada H, Yokosawa H, Ishii S.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of two types of trypsin-like enzymes from sperm of the ascidian (Prochordata) Halocynthia roretzi. Evidence for the presence of spermosin, a novel acrosin-like enzyme.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 259 (1984) 2900-4.
  ORGANISM  Halocynthia roretzi
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q966V2]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:6381175]
  AUTHORS   Sawada H, Yokosawa H, Someno T, Saino T, Ishii S.
  TITLE     Evidence for the participation of two sperm proteases, spermosin and acrosin, in fertilization of the ascidian, Halocynthia roretzi: inhibitory effects of leupeptin analogs on enzyme activities and fertilization.
  JOURNAL   Dev. Biol. 105 (1984) 246-9.
  ORGANISM  Halocynthia roretzi
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q966V2]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8670234]
  AUTHORS   Sawada H, Iwasaki K, Kihara-Negishi F, Ariga H, Yokosawa H.
  TITLE     Localization, expression, and the role in fertilization of spermosin, an ascidian sperm trypsin-like protease.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 222 (1996) 499-504.
  ORGANISM  Halocynthia roretzi
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q966V2]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:8914083]
  AUTHORS   Sawada H, Someno T.
  TITLE     Substrate specificity of ascidian sperm trypsin-like proteases, spermosin and acrosin.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Reprod. Dev. 45 (1996) 240-3.
  ORGANISM  Halocynthia roretzi
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q966V2]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.99
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.99
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.99
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.99
            CAS: 89925-67-7
///
