ENTRY       EC 3.4.23.12                Enzyme
NAME        nepenthesin;
            Nepenthes aspartic proteinase;
            Nepenthes acid proteinase;
            nepenthacin;
            nepenthasin;
            aspartyl endopeptidase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Aspartic endopeptidases
REACTION    Similar to pepsin, but also cleaves on either side of Asp and at Lys!Arg
COMMENT     From the insectivorous plants Nepenthes spp. (secretions) and Drosera peltata (ground-up leaves). Aspartic endopeptidases are probably present in many other plants, including Lotus [3] and sorghum [2]. In peptidase family A1 (pepsin A family)
HISTORY     EC 3.4.23.12 created 1972 as EC 3.4.99.4, transferred 1978 to EC 3.4.23.12, modified 1981
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:5354017]
  AUTHORS   Amagase S, Nakayama S, Tsugita A.
  TITLE     Acid protease in Nepenthes. II. Study on the specificity of nepenthesin.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 66 (1969) 431-9.
  ORGANISM  Nepenthes sp.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:5486576]
  AUTHORS   Garg GK, Virupaksha TK.
  TITLE     Acid protease from germinated sorghum. 2. Substrate specificity with synthetic peptides and ribonuclease A.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 17 (1970) 13-8.
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   Shinano, S. and Fukushima, K.
  TITLE     Studies on lotus seed protease. Part III. Some physicochemical and enzymic properties.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 35 (1971) 1488-1494.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:5069751]
  AUTHORS   Amagase S.
  TITLE     Digestive enzymes in insectivorous plants. 3. Acid proteases in the genus Nepenthes and Drosera peltata.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 72 (1972) 73-81.
  ORGANISM  Drosera peltata, Nepenthes sp.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:4436292]
  AUTHORS   Takahashi K, Chang W, Ko J.
  TITLE     Specific inhibition of acid proteases from brain, kidney, skeletal muscle, and insectivorous plants by diazoacetyl-DL-norleucine methyl ester and by pepstatin.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 76 (1974) 897-9.
  ORGANISM  Nepenthes macferlanei
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:16526095]
  AUTHORS   Coiras M, Camafeita E, Urena T, Lopez JA, Caballero F, Fernandez B, Lopez-Huertas MR, Perez-Olmeda M, Alcami J.
  TITLE     Modifications in the human T cell proteome induced by intracellular HIV-1 Tat protein expression.
  JOURNAL   Proteomics. 6 Suppl 1 (2006) S63-73.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.12
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.23.12
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.23.12
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.23.12
            CAS: 9073-80-7
///
