ENTRY       EC 3.4.24.60                Enzyme
NAME        dactylysin;
            peptide hormone inactivating endopeptidase;
            PHIE
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Metalloendopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of peptides of at least six residues, with bulky hydrophobic residues in the P1' position. Shows a preference for hydrophobic doublets such as -Phe!Phe- and -Phe!Leu- in somatostatin-(1-14)-peptide and dynorphin A-(1-6)-peptide, respectively
COMMENT     An endopeptidase of 100 kDa secreted from the skin of the amphibian, Xenopus laevis (Dactyletre du Cap). Resembles neprilysin in insensitivity to 1 muM captopril, but differs from it in being insensitive to thiorphan (1 muM) and unable to digest [Met5]enkephalin, [Leu5]enkephalin, oxytocin, and substance P-(7-11)-peptide. A similar endopeptidase is found in human neuroblastoma cells [2]
HISTORY     EC 3.4.24.60 created 1995
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1729723]
  AUTHORS   Carvalho KM, Joudiou C, Boussetta H, Leseney AM, Cohen P.
  TITLE     A peptide-hormone-inactivating endopeptidase in Xenopus laevis skin secretion.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 89 (1992) 84-8.
  ORGANISM  Xenopus laevis
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:1531011]
  AUTHORS   Delporte C, Carvalho KM, Leseney AM, Winand J, Christophe J, Cohen P.
  TITLE     A new metallo- endopeptidase from human neuroblastoma NB-OK-1 cells which inactivates atrial natriuretic peptide by selective cleavage at the Ser123-Phe124 bond.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 182 (1992) 158-64.
  ORGANISM  Xenopus laevis
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8507636]
  AUTHORS   Joudiou C, Carvalho KM, Camarao G, Boussetta H, Cohen P.
  TITLE     Characterization of the thermolysin-like cleavage of biologically active peptides by Xenopus laevis peptide hormone inactivating enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 32 (1993) 5959-66.
  ORGANISM  Xenopus laevis
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.60
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.24.60
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.24.60
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.60
            CAS: 139466-40-3
///
