ENTRY       EC 3.4.24.27                Enzyme
NAME        thermolysin;
            Bacillus thermoproteolyticus neutral proteinase;
            thermoase;
            thermoase Y10;
            TLN
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Metalloendopeptidases
REACTION    Preferential cleavage: !Leu > !Phe
COMMENT     A thermostable extracellular metalloendopeptidase containing four calcium ions. Enzymes that may be species variants of thermolysin are reported from Micrococcus caseolyticus [4] and Aspergillus oryzae [5]. Type example of peptidase family M4. Closely related but distinct enzymes are aeromonolysin, pseudolysin, bacillolysin, aureolysin and mycolysin
HISTORY     EC 3.4.24.27 created 1972 as EC 3.4.24.4, part transferred 1992 to EC 3.4.24.27
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:5954368]
  AUTHORS   Ohta Y, Ogura Y, Wada A.
  TITLE     Thermostable protease from thermophilic bacteria. I. Thermostability, physiocochemical properties, and amino acid composition.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 241 (1966) 5919-25.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus thermoproteolyticus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:4967801]
  AUTHORS   Morihara K, Tsuzuki H, Oka T.
  TITLE     Comparison of the specificities of various neutral proteinases from microorganisms.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 123 (1968) 572-88.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:5823940]
  AUTHORS   Latt SA, Holmquist B, Vallee BL.
  TITLE     Thermolysin: a zinc metalloenzyme.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 37 (1969) 333-9.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus thermoproteolyticus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:5551628]
  AUTHORS   Desmazeaud MJ, Hermier JH.
  TITLE     [Specificity of the nuclear protease produced by Micrococcus caseolyticus]
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 19 (1971) 51-5.
  ORGANISM  Micrococcus caseolyticus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:5004124]
  AUTHORS   Morihara K, Tsuzuki H.
  TITLE     Comparative study of various neutral proteinases from microorganisms: specificity with oligopeptides.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 146 (1971) 291-6.
REFERENCE   6
  AUTHORS   Titani, K., Hermodson, M.
  TITLE     A., Ericson, L. H., Walsh, K. A. and Neurath, H. Amino-acid sequence of thermolysin.
  JOURNAL   Nature New Biol. 238 (1972) 35-37.
REFERENCE   7
  AUTHORS   Matthews, B.
  TITLE     W. Structural basis of the action of thermolysin and related zinc peptidases.
  JOURNAL   Acc. Chem. Res. 21 (1988) 333-340.
ORTHOLOGY   K08603  thermolysin
GENES       BAN: BA_0599
            BAR: GBAA_0599
            BAT: BAS0567
            BCY: Bcer98_0515
            BWE: BcerKBAB4_0514
            GKA: GK2838
            ESI: Exig_2940
            EAT: EAT1b_0125
            FRA: Francci3_1623
            HAU: Haur_3645
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.27
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.24.27
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.24.27
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.27
            CAS: 9073-78-3
///
