ENTRY       EC 3.4.21.82                Enzyme
NAME        glutamyl endopeptidase II;
            GluSGP
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Serine endopeptidases
REACTION    Preferential cleavage: -Glu! >> -Asp! . Preference for Pro or Leu at P2 and Phe at P3. Cleavage of -Glu!Asp- and -Glu!Pro- bonds is slow
COMMENT     From Streptomyces griseus. A peptidase of family S1 (trypsin family). Inhibited by [Leu18->Glu]-modified turkey ovomucoid third domain
HISTORY     EC 3.4.21.82 created 1993
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3149277]
  AUTHORS   Yoshida N, Tsuruyama S, Nagata K, Hirayama K, Noda K, Makisumi S.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of an acidic amino acid specific endopeptidase of Streptomyces griseus obtained from a commercial preparation (Pronase).
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 104 (1988) 451-6.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces griseus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:1674942]
  AUTHORS   Komiyama T, Bigler TL, Yoshida N, Noda K, Laskowski M Jr.
  TITLE     Replacement of P1 Leu18 by Glu18 in the reactive site of turkey ovomucoid third domain converts it into a strong inhibitor of Glu-specific Streptomyces griseus proteinase (GluSGP).
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 266 (1991) 10727-30.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces griseus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:1794975]
  AUTHORS   Nagata K, Yoshida N, Ogata F, Araki M, Noda K.
  TITLE     Subsite mapping of an acidic amino acid-specific endopeptidase from Streptomyces griseus, GluSGP, and protease V8.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. (Tokyo). 110 (1991) 859-62.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces griseus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:1959600]
  AUTHORS   Svendsen I, Jensen MR, Breddam K.
  TITLE     The primary structure of the glutamic acid-specific protease of Streptomyces griseus.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 292 (1991) 165-7.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces griseus
  SEQUENCE  [sgr:SGR_1986]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:1587264]
  AUTHORS   Breddam K, Meldal M.
  TITLE     Substrate preferences of glutamic-acid-specific endopeptidases assessed by synthetic peptide substrates based on intramolecular fluorescence quenching.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 206 (1992) 103-7.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces griseus, Bacillus licheniformis
  SEQUENCE  [sgr:SGR_1986]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.82
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.21.82
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.21.82
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.21.82
            CAS: 137010-42-5
///
