ENTRY       EC 3.4.24.26                Enzyme
NAME        pseudolysin;
            Pseudomonas elastase;
            Pseudomonas aeruginosa neutral metalloproteinase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on peptide bonds (peptidases);
            Metalloendopeptidases
REACTION    Hydrolysis of proteins including elastin, collagen types III and IV, fibronectin and immunoglobulin A, generally with bulky hydrophobic group at P1'. Insulin B chain cleavage pattern identical to that of thermolysin, but specificity differs in other respects
COMMENT     In peptidase family M4 (thermolysin family). From the pathogenic bacteria Pseudomonas aeruginosa and Legionella pneumophila, and causes tissue damage.
HISTORY     EC 3.4.24.26 created 1972 as EC 3.4.24.4, part transferred 1992 to EC 3.4.24.26
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Morihara, K. and Tsuzuki, H.
  TITLE     Pseudomonas aeruginosa elastase: affinity chromatography and some properties as a metallo-neutral proteinase.
  JOURNAL   Agric. Biol. Chem. 39 (1975) 1123-1128.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:6767718]
  AUTHORS   Nishino N, Powers JC.
  TITLE     Pseudomonas aeruginosa elastase. Development of a new substrate, inhibitors, and an affinity ligand.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 255 (1980) 3482-6.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas aeruginosa
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:3512431]
  AUTHORS   Dreyfus LA, Iglewski BH.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of an extracellular protease of Legionella pneumophila.
  JOURNAL   Infect. Immun. 51 (1986) 736-43.
  ORGANISM  Legionella pneumophila
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:2842313]
  AUTHORS   Bever RA, Iglewski BH.
  TITLE     Molecular characterization and nucleotide sequence of the Pseudomonas aeruginosa elastase structural gene.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 170 (1988) 4309-14.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas aeruginosa
  SEQUENCE  [pae:PA3724]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:2110146]
  AUTHORS   Black WJ, Quinn FD, Tompkins LS.
  TITLE     Legionella pneumophila zinc metalloprotease is structurally and functionally homologous to Pseudomonas aeruginosa elastase.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 172 (1990) 2608-13.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas aeruginosa
ORTHOLOGY   K01399  pseudolysin
GENES       PAE: PA3724(lasB)
            PAU: PA14_16250(lasB)
            PAP: PSPA7_1397(lasB)
            PAG: PLES_12581(lasB)
            PAF: PAM18_1222(lasB)
            PNC: NCGM2_4855(lasB)
            PDK: PADK2_05720
            PSG: G655_06175
            PRP: M062_19690
            PAEP: PA1S_gp1580
            PAER: PA1R_gp1580
            PAEM: U769_06260
            PAEL: T223_06195
            PAES: SCV20265_1285
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.26
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.4.24.26
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.4.24.26
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.4.24.26
            CAS: 171715-23-4
///
