ENTRY       EC 3.5.1.93                 Enzyme
NAME        glutaryl-7-aminocephalosporanic-acid acylase;
            7beta-(4-carboxybutanamido)cephalosporanic acid acylase;
            cephalosporin C acylase;
            glutaryl-7-ACA acylase;
            CA;
            GCA;
            GA;
            cephalosporin acylase;
            glutaryl-7-aminocephalosporanic acid acylase;
            GL-7-ACA acylase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on carbon-nitrogen bonds, other than peptide bonds;
            In linear amides
SYSNAME     (7R)-7-(4-carboxybutanamido)cephalosporanate amidohydrolase
REACTION    (7R)-7-(4-carboxybutanamido)cephalosporanate + H2O = (7R)-7-aminocephalosporanate + glutarate [RN:R07402]
ALL_REAC    R07402
SUBSTRATE   (7R)-7-(4-carboxybutanamido)cephalosporanate [CPD:C15666];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     (7R)-7-aminocephalosporanate [CPD:C07756];
            glutarate [CPD:C00489]
COMMENT     Forms 7-aminocephalosporanic acid, a key intermediate in the synthesis of cephem antibiotics. It reacts only weakly with cephalosporin C.
HISTORY     EC 3.5.1.93 created 2005
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:7607251]
  AUTHORS   Ishii Y, Saito Y, Fujimura T, Sasaki H, Noguchi Y, Yamada H, Niwa M, Shimomura K.
  TITLE     High-level production, chemical modification and site-directed mutagenesis of a cephalosporin C acylase from Pseudomonas strain N176.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 230 (1995) 773-8.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas sp.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:10739919]
  AUTHORS   Kinoshita T, Tada T, Saito Y, Ishii Y, Sato A, Murata M.
  TITLE     Crystallization and preliminary X-ray analysis of cephalosporin C acylase from Pseudomonas sp. strain N176.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 56 ( Pt 4) (2000) 458-9.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas sp.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10972935]
  AUTHORS   Monti D, Carrea G, Riva S, Baldaro E, Frare G.
  TITLE     Characterization of an industrial biocatalyst: immobilized glutaryl-7-ACA acylase.
  JOURNAL   Biotechnol. Bioeng. 70 (2000) 239-44.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:10945972]
  AUTHORS   Kwon TH, Rhee S, Lee YS, Park SS, Kim KH.
  TITLE     Crystallization and preliminary X-Ray diffraction analysis of glutaryl-7-aminocephalosporanic acid acylase from Pseudomonas sp. GK16.
  JOURNAL   J. Struct. Biol. 131 (2000) 79-81.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas sp.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:11080627]
  AUTHORS   Kim Y, Yoon K, Khang Y, Turley S, Hol WG.
  TITLE     The 2.0 A crystal structure of cephalosporin acylase.
  JOURNAL   Structure. Fold. Des. 8 (2000) 1059-68.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas diminuta
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9L5D6]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:11782466]
  AUTHORS   Huang X, Zeng R, Ding X, Mao X, Ding Y, Rao Z, Xie Y, Jiang W, Zhao G.
  TITLE     Affinity alkylation of the Trp-B4 residue of the beta -subunit of the glutaryl 7-aminocephalosporanic acid acylase of Pseudomonas sp. 130.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 277 (2002) 10256-64.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas sp.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:12680762]
  AUTHORS   Kim JK, Yang IS, Rhee S, Dauter Z, Lee YS, Park SS, Kim KH.
  TITLE     Crystal structures of glutaryl 7-aminocephalosporanic acid acylase: insight into autoproteolytic activation.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 42 (2003) 4084-93.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas sp.
  SEQUENCE  [up:P07662]
PATHWAY     ec00311  Penicillin and cephalosporin biosynthesis
ORTHOLOGY   K12748  glutaryl-7-aminocephalosporanic-acid acylase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.5.1.93
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.5.1.93
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.5.1.93
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.5.1.93
            CAS: 56645-46-6
///
