ENTRY       EC 3.5.1.114                Enzyme
NAME        N-acyl-aromatic-L-amino acid amidohydrolase;
            aminoacylase 3;
            aminoacylase III;
            ACY3 (gene name)
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on carbon-nitrogen bonds, other than peptide bonds;
            In linear amides
SYSNAME     N-acyl-aromatic-L-amino acid amidohydrolase (carboxylate-forming)
REACTION    (1) an N-acyl-aromatic-L-amino acid + H2O = an aromatic-L-amino acid + a carboxylate [RN:R10621];
            (2) an N-acetyl-L-cysteine-S-conjugate + H2O = an L-cysteine-S-conjugate + acetate [RN:R10553]
ALL_REAC    R10553 R10621
SUBSTRATE   N-acyl-aromatic-L-amino acid [CPD:C20735];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            N-acetyl-L-cysteine S-conjugate [CPD:C05727]
PRODUCT     aromatic-L-amino acid [CPD:C01021];
            carboxylate [CPD:C00060];
            L-cysteine S-conjugate [CPD:C05726];
            acetate [CPD:C00033]
COMMENT     This enzyme is found in animals and is involved in the hydrolysis of N-acylated or N-acetylated amino acids (except L-aspartate). It preferentially deacetylates Nalpha-acetylated aromatic amino acids and mercapturic acids (S-conjugates of N-acetyl-L-cysteine) that are usually not deacetylated by EC 3.5.1.14, N-acyl-aliphatic-L-amino acid amidohydrolase. The enzyme is significantly activated by Co2+ and Ni2+ [3]. Some bacterial aminoacylases demonstrate substrate specificity for both EC 3.5.1.14 and EC 3.5.1.114. cf. EC 3.5.1.14, N-acyl-aliphatic-L-amino acid amidohydrolase and EC 3.5.1.15, aspartoacylase.
HISTORY     EC 3.5.1.114 created 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:14656720]
  AUTHORS   Pushkin A, Carpenito G, Abuladze N, Newman D, Tsuprun V, Ryazantsev S, Motemoturu S, Sassani P, Solovieva N, Dukkipati R, Kurtz I
  TITLE     Structural characterization, tissue distribution, and functional expression of murine aminoacylase III.
  JOURNAL   Am. J. Physiol. Cell. Physiol. 286 (2004) C848-56.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
  SEQUENCE  [mmu:71670]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:17012540]
  AUTHORS   Newman D, Abuladze N, Scholz K, Dekant W, Tsuprun V, Ryazantsev S, Bondar G, Sassani P, Kurtz I, Pushkin A
  TITLE     Specificity of aminoacylase III-mediated deacetylation of mercapturic acids.
  JOURNAL   Drug. Metab. Dispos. 35 (2007) 43-50.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
  SEQUENCE  [mmu:71670]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:19362172]
  AUTHORS   Tsirulnikov K, Abuladze N, Newman D, Ryazantsev S, Wolak T, Magilnick N, Koag MC, Kurtz I, Pushkin A
  TITLE     Mouse aminoacylase 3: a metalloenzyme activated by cobalt and nickel.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1794 (2009) 1049-57.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:20921362]
  AUTHORS   Hsieh JM, Tsirulnikov K, Sawaya MR, Magilnick N, Abuladze N, Kurtz I, Abramson J, Pushkin A
  TITLE     Structures of aminoacylase 3 in complex with acetylated substrates.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 107 (2010) 17962-7.
  ORGANISM  Mus musculus
  SEQUENCE  [mmu:71670]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:22819785]
  AUTHORS   Tsirulnikov K, Abuladze N, Bragin A, Faull K, Cascio D, Damoiseaux R, Schibler MJ, Pushkin A
  TITLE     Inhibition of aminoacylase 3 protects rat brain cortex neuronal cells from the toxicity of 4-hydroxy-2-nonenal mercapturate and 4-hydroxy-2-nonenal.
  JOURNAL   Toxicol. Appl. Pharmacol. 263 (2012) 303-14.
  ORGANISM  Rattus norvegicus, Mus musculus, Homo sapiens
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.5.1.114
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.5.1.114
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.5.1.114
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.5.1.114
///
