ENTRY       EC 3.5.1.104                Enzyme
NAME        peptidoglycan-N-acetylglucosamine deacetylase;
            HP310;
            PgdA;
            SpPgdA;
            BC1960;
            peptidoglycan deacetylase;
            N-acetylglucosamine deacetylase;
            peptidoglycan GlcNAc deacetylase;
            peptidoglycan N-acetylglucosamine deacetylase;
            PG N-deacetylase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on carbon-nitrogen bonds, other than peptide bonds;
            In linear amides
SYSNAME     peptidoglycan-N-acetylglucosamine amidohydrolase
REACTION    peptidoglycan-N-acetyl-D-glucosamine + H2O = peptidoglycan-D-glucosamine + acetate [RN:R09721]
ALL_REAC    R09721
SUBSTRATE   peptidoglycan-N-acetyl-D-glucosamine;
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     peptidoglycan-D-glucosamine [CPD:C19842];
            acetate [CPD:C00033]
COMMENT     Modification of peptidoglycan by N-deacetylation is an important factor in virulence of Helicobacter pylori, Listeria monocytogenes and Streptococcus suis [4-6]. The enzyme from Streptococcus pneumoniae is a metalloenzyme using a His-His-Asp zinc-binding triad with a nearby aspartic acid and histidine acting as the catalytic base and acid, respectively [3].
HISTORY     EC 3.5.1.104 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:15961396]
  AUTHORS   Psylinakis E, Boneca IG, Mavromatis K, Deli A, Hayhurst E, Foster SJ, Varum KM, Bouriotis V
  TITLE     Peptidoglycan N-acetylglucosamine deacetylases from Bacillus cereus, highly conserved proteins in Bacillus anthracis.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 280 (2005) 30856-63.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus cereus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:18323609]
  AUTHORS   Tsalafouta A, Psylinakis E, Kapetaniou EG, Kotsifaki D, Deli A, Roidis A, Bouriotis V, Kokkinidis M
  TITLE     Purification, crystallization and preliminary X-ray analysis of the peptidoglycan N-acetylglucosamine deacetylase BC1960 from Bacillus cereus in the presence of its substrate (GlcNAc)6.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. Sect. F. Struct. Biol. Cryst. Commun. 64 (2008) 203-5.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus cereus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16221761]
  AUTHORS   Blair DE, Schuttelkopf AW, MacRae JI, van Aalten DM
  TITLE     Structure and metal-dependent mechanism of peptidoglycan deacetylase, a streptococcal virulence factor.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 102 (2005) 15429-34.
  ORGANISM  Streptococcus pneumoniae
  SEQUENCE  [spr:spr1333]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:19147492]
  AUTHORS   Wang G, Olczak A, Forsberg LS, Maier RJ
  TITLE     Oxidative stress-induced peptidoglycan deacetylase in Helicobacter pylori.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 284 (2009) 6790-800.
  ORGANISM  Helicobacter pylori
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:19809250]
  AUTHORS   Popowska M, Kusio M, Szymanska P, Markiewicz Z
  TITLE     Inactivation of the wall-associated de-N-acetylase (PgdA) of Listeria monocytogenes results in greater susceptibility of the cells to induced autolysis.
  JOURNAL   J. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 19 (2009) 932-45.
  ORGANISM  Listeria monocytogenes
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:18990186]
  AUTHORS   Fittipaldi N, Sekizaki T, Takamatsu D, de la Cruz Dominguez-Punaro M, Harel J, Bui NK, Vollmer W, Gottschalk M
  TITLE     Significant contribution of the pgdA gene to the virulence of Streptococcus suis.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 70 (2008) 1120-35.
  ORGANISM  Streptococcus suis
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.5.1.104
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.5.1.104
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.5.1.104
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.5.1.104
///
