ENTRY       EC 3.5.1.105                Enzyme
NAME        chitin disaccharide deacetylase;
            chitobiose amidohydolase;
            COD;
            chitin oligosaccharide deacetylase;
            chitin oligosaccharide amidohydolase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on carbon-nitrogen bonds, other than peptide bonds;
            In linear amides
SYSNAME     2-(acetylamino)-4-O-[2-(acetylamino)-2-deoxy-beta-D-glucopyranosyl]-2-deoxy-D-glucopyranose acetylhydrolase
REACTION    2-(acetylamino)-4-O-[2-(acetylamino)-2-deoxy-beta-D-glucopyranosyl]-2-deoxy-beta-D-glucopyranose + H2O = 2-(acetylamino)-4-O-(2-amino-2-deoxy-beta-D-glucopyranosyl)-2-deoxy-beta-D-glucopyranose + acetate
SUBSTRATE   2-(acetylamino)-4-O-[2-(acetylamino)-2-deoxy-beta-D-glucopyranosyl]-2-deoxy-beta-D-glucopyranose;
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     2-(acetylamino)-4-O-(2-amino-2-deoxy-beta-D-glucopyranosyl)-2-deoxy-beta-D-glucopyranose;
            acetate [CPD:C00033]
COMMENT     Chitin oligosaccharide deacetylase is a key enzyme in the chitin catabolic cascade of chitinolytic Vibrio strains. Besides being a nutrient, the heterodisaccharide product 4-O-(N-acetyl-beta-D-glucosaminyl)-D-glucosamine is a unique inducer of chitinase production in Vibrio parahaemolyticus [2]. In contrast to EC 3.5.1.41 (chitin deacetylase) this enzyme is specific for the chitin disaccharide [1,3]. It also deacetylates the chitin trisaccharide with lower efficiency [3]. No activity with higher polymers of GlcNAc [1,3].
HISTORY     EC 3.5.1.105 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:17334758]
  AUTHORS   Kadokura K, Rokutani A, Yamamoto M, Ikegami T, Sugita H, Itoi S, Hakamata W, Oku T, Nishio T
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of Vibrio parahaemolyticus extracellular chitinase and chitin oligosaccharide deacetylase involved in the production of heterodisaccharide from chitin.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 75 (2007) 357-65.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:19553519]
  AUTHORS   Hirano T, Kadokura K, Ikegami T, Shigeta Y, Kumaki Y, Hakamata W, Oku T, Nishio T
  TITLE     Heterodisaccharide 4-O-(N-acetyl-beta-D-glucosaminyl)-D-glucosamine is a specific inducer of chitinolytic enzyme production in Vibrios harboring chitin oligosaccharide deacetylase genes.
  JOURNAL   Glycobiology. 19 (2009) 1046-53.
  ORGANISM  Vibrio campbellii
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   Ohishi, K., Yamagishi, M., Ohta, T., Motosugi, M., Izumida, H., Sano, H., Adachi, K., Miwa, T.
  TITLE     Purification and properties of two deacetylases produced by Vibrio alginolyticus H-8.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 61 (1997) 1113-1117.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16232910]
  AUTHORS   Ohishi K, Murase K, Ohta T, Etoh H
  TITLE     Cloning and sequencing of the deacetylase gene from Vibrio alginolyticus H-8.
  JOURNAL   J. Biosci. Bioeng. 90 (2000) 561-3.
  ORGANISM  Vibrio alginolyticus
  SEQUENCE  [vag:N646_1731]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.5.1.105
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.5.1.105
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.5.1.105
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.5.1.105
///
