ENTRY       EC 3.6.3.38                 Enzyme
NAME        capsular-polysaccharide-transporting ATPase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on acid anhydrides;
            Acting on acid anhydrides to catalyse transmembrane movement of substances
SYSNAME     ATP phosphohydrolase (capsular-polysaccharide-exporting)
REACTION    ATP + H2O + capsular polysaccharidein = ADP + phosphate + capsular polysaccharideout [RN:R00086]
ALL_REAC    R00086
SUBSTRATE   ATP [CPD:C00002];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            capsular polysaccharide [CPD:C06705]
PRODUCT     ADP [CPD:C00008];
            phosphate [CPD:C00009];
            capsular polysaccharide [CPD:C06705]
COMMENT     ABC-type (ATP-binding cassette-type) ATPase, characterized by the presence of two similar ATP-binding domains. Does not undergo phosphorylation during the transport process. An enzyme that exports capsular polysaccharide from Gram-negative bacteria.
HISTORY     EC 3.6.3.38 created 2000
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8302219]
  AUTHORS   Fath MJ, Kolter R.
  TITLE     ABC transporters: bacterial exporters.
  JOURNAL   Microbiol. Rev. 57 (1993) 995-1017.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9274022]
  AUTHORS   Paulsen IT, Beness AM, Saier MH Jr.
  TITLE     Computer-based analyses of the protein constituents of transport systems catalysing export of complex carbohydrates in bacteria.
  JOURNAL   Microbiology. 143 ( Pt 8) (1997) 2685-99.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli, Vibrio cholerae, Klebsiella pneumoniae, Haemophilus infiuenzae, Neisseria meningitidis, Salmonella typhi, Staphylococcus aureus, Streptococcus pneumoniae, Streptococcus agalactiae
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9513268]
  AUTHORS   Pigeon RP, Silver RP.
  TITLE     Analysis of the G93E mutant allele of KpsM, the membrane component of an ABC transporter involved in polysialic acid translocation in Escherichia coli K1.
  JOURNAL   FEMS. Microbiol. Lett. 156 (1997) 217-22.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9889977]
  AUTHORS   Saier MH Jr.
  TITLE     Molecular phylogeny as a basis for the classification of transport proteins from bacteria, archaea and eukarya.
  JOURNAL   Adv. Microb. Physiol. 40 (1998) 81-136.
  ORGANISM  bacteria
REFERENCE   5
  AUTHORS   Griffiths, J.K. and Sansom, C.E.
  TITLE     The Transporter Factsbook, Academic Press, San Diego, 1998.
ORTHOLOGY   K10832  capsular-polysaccharide-transporting ATPase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.6.3.38
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.6.3.38
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.6.3.38
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.6.3.38
///
