ENTRY       EC 3.6.4.10                 Enzyme
NAME        non-chaperonin molecular chaperone ATPase;
            molecular chaperone Hsc70 ATPase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on acid anhydrides;
            Acting on acid anhydrides to facilitate cellular and subcellular movement
SYSNAME     ATP phosphohydrolase (polypeptide-polymerizing)
REACTION    ATP + H2O = ADP + phosphate [RN:R00086]
ALL_REAC    R00086
SUBSTRATE   ATP [CPD:C00002];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     ADP [CPD:C00008];
            phosphate [CPD:C00009]
COMMENT     This is a highly diverse group of enzymes that perform many functions that are similar to those of chaperonins. They comprise a number of heat-shock-cognate proteins. They are also active in clathrin uncoating and in the oligomerization of actin.
HISTORY     EC 3.6.4.10 created 2000
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1356434]
  AUTHORS   Sadis S, Hightower LE.
  TITLE     Unfolded proteins stimulate molecular chaperone Hsc70 ATPase by accelerating ADP/ATP exchange.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 31 (1992) 9406-12.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8509407]
  AUTHORS   Blond-Elguindi S, Fourie AM, Sambrook JF, Gething MJ.
  TITLE     Peptide-dependent stimulation of the ATPase activity of the molecular chaperone BiP is the result of conversion of oligomers to active monomers.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 268 (1993) 12730-5.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:7743994]
  AUTHORS   Wawrzynow A, Wojtkowiak D, Marszalek J, Banecki B, Jonsen M, Graves B, Georgopoulos C, Zylicz M.
  TITLE     The ClpX heat-shock protein of Escherichia coli, the ATP-dependent substrate specificity component of the ClpP-ClpX protease, is a novel molecular chaperone.
  JOURNAL   EMBO. J. 14 (1995) 1867-77.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9083109]
  AUTHORS   Sriram M, Osipiuk J, Freeman B, Morimoto R, Joachimiak A.
  TITLE     Human Hsp70 molecular chaperone binds two calcium ions within the ATPase domain.
  JOURNAL   Structure. 5 (1997) 403-14.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:9477575]
  AUTHORS   Li X, Su RT, Hsu HT, Sze H.
  TITLE     The molecular chaperone calnexin associates with the vacuolar H(+)-ATPase from oat seedlings.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Cell. 10 (1998) 119-30.
  ORGANISM  Avena sativa
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.6.4.10
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.6.4.10
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.6.4.10
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.6.4.10
///
