ENTRY       EC 3.6.5.1                  Enzyme
NAME        heterotrimeric G-protein GTPase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on acid anhydrides;
            Acting on GTP to facilitate cellular and subcellular movement
SYSNAME     GTP phosphohydrolase (signalling)
REACTION    GTP + H2O = GDP + phosphate [RN:R00335]
ALL_REAC    R00335
SUBSTRATE   GTP [CPD:C00044];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     GDP [CPD:C00035];
            phosphate [CPD:C00009]
COMMENT     This group comprises GTP-hydrolysing systems, where GTP and GDP alternate in binding. This group includes stimulatory and inhibitory G-proteins such as Gs, Gi, Go and Golf, targetting adenylate cyclase and/or K+ and Ca2+ channels; Gq stimulating phospholipase C; transducin activating cGMP phosphodiesterase; gustducin activating cAMP phosphodiesterase. Golf is instrumental in odour perception, transducin in vision and gustducin in taste recognition. At least 16 different alpha subunits (39-52 kDa), 5 beta subunits (36 kDa) and 12 gamma subunits (6-9 kDa) are known.
HISTORY     EC 3.6.5.1 created 2000 as EC 3.6.1.46, transferred 2003 to EC 3.6.5.1
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:7834744]
  AUTHORS   Neer EJ.
  TITLE     Heterotrimeric G proteins: organizers of transmembrane signals.
  JOURNAL   Cell. 80 (1995) 249-57.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9242920]
  AUTHORS   Sprang SR.
  TITLE     G protein mechanisms: insights from structural analysis.
  JOURNAL   Annu. Rev. Biochem. 66 (1997) 639-78.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Bos taurus, Thermus thermophilus, Thermus aquaticus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9188484]
  AUTHORS   Bondarenko VA, Desai M, Dua S, Yamazaki M, Amin RH, Yousif KK, Kinumi T, Ohashi M, Komori N, Matsumoto H, Jackson KW, Hayashi F, Usukura J, Lipkin VM, Yamazaki A.
  TITLE     Residues within the polycationic region of cGMP phosphodiesterase gamma subunit crucial for the interaction with transducin alpha subunit. Identification by endogenous ADP-ribosylation and site-directed mutagenesis.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 272 (1997) 15856-64.
  ORGANISM  Rana catesbiana, Rana grylio
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9671782]
  AUTHORS   Ming D, Ruiz-Avila L, Margolskee RF.
  TITLE     Characterization and solubilization of bitter-responsive receptors that couple to gustducin.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 95 (1998) 8933-8.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
  SEQUENCE  [bta:516262]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.6.5.1
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.6.5.1
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.6.5.1
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.6.5.1
///
