ENTRY       EC 3.6.1.59                 Enzyme
NAME        5'-(N7-methyl 5'-triphosphoguanosine)-[mRNA] diphosphatase;
            DcpS;
            m7GpppX pyrophosphatase;
            m7GpppN m7GMP phosphohydrolase;
            m7GpppX diphosphatase;
            m7G5'ppp5'N m7GMP phosphohydrolase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on acid anhydrides;
            In phosphorus-containing anhydrides
SYSNAME     5'-(N7-methyl 5'-triphosphoguanosine)-[mRNA] N7-methylguanosine 5'-phosphate phosphohydrolase
REACTION    a 5'-(N7-methyl 5'-triphosphoguanosine)-[mRNA] + H2O = N7-methylguanosine 5'-phosphate + a 5'-diphospho-[mRNA]
ALL_REAC    (other) R04368
SUBSTRATE   5'-(N7-methyl 5'-triphosphoguanosine)-[mRNA] [CPD:C02339];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     N7-methylguanosine 5'-phosphate;
            5'-diphospho-[mRNA]
COMMENT     The enzyme removes (decaps) the N7-methylguanosine 5-phosphate cap from an mRNA degraded to a maximal length of 10 nucleotides [3,6]. Decapping is an important process in the control of eukaryotic mRNA degradation. The enzyme functions to clear the cell of cap structure following decay of the RNA body [2]. The nematode enzyme can also decap triply methylated substrates, 5'-(N2,N2,N7-trimethyl 5'-triphosphoguanosine)-[mRNA] [4].
HISTORY     EC 3.6.1.59 created 2012, modified 2013
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:16963086]
  AUTHORS   Malys N, McCarthy JE
  TITLE     Dcs2, a novel stress-induced modulator of m7GpppX pyrophosphatase activity that locates to P bodies.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 363 (2006) 370-82.
  ORGANISM  Saccharomyces cerevisiae
  SEQUENCE  [sce:YLR270W]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:18441014]
  AUTHORS   Liu SW, Rajagopal V, Patel SS, Kiledjian M
  TITLE     Mechanistic and kinetic analysis of the DcpS scavenger decapping enzyme.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 283 (2008) 16427-36.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:12198172]
  AUTHORS   Liu H, Rodgers ND, Jiao X, Kiledjian M
  TITLE     The scavenger mRNA decapping enzyme DcpS is a member of the HIT family of pyrophosphatases.
  JOURNAL   EMBO. J. 21 (2002) 4699-708.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Saccharomyces cerevisiae
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:28960] [sce:YLR270W]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:14523240]
  AUTHORS   van Dijk E, Le Hir H, Seraphin B
  TITLE     DcpS can act in the 5'-3' mRNA decay pathway in addition to the 3'-5' pathway.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 100 (2003) 12081-6.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Saccharomyces cerevisiae
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:28960] [sce:YLR270W]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15769464]
  AUTHORS   Chen N, Walsh MA, Liu Y, Parker R, Song H
  TITLE     Crystal structures of human DcpS in ligand-free and m7GDP-bound forms suggest a dynamic mechanism for scavenger mRNA decapping.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 347 (2005) 707-18.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:28960]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:15383679]
  AUTHORS   Cohen LS, Mikhli C, Friedman C, Jankowska-Anyszka M, Stepinski J, Darzynkiewicz E, Davis RE
  TITLE     Nematode m7GpppG and m3(2,2,7)GpppG decapping: activities in Ascaris embryos and  characterization of C. elegans scavenger DcpS.
  JOURNAL   RNA. 10 (2004) 1609-24.
  ORGANISM  Ascaris suum, Caenorhabditis elegans
  SEQUENCE  [up:D3K0N9] [cel:CELE_Y113G7A.9]
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:22985415]
  AUTHORS   Wypijewska A, Bojarska E, Lukaszewicz M, Stepinski J, Jemielity J, Davis RE, Darzynkiewicz E
  TITLE     7-methylguanosine diphosphate (m(7)GDP) is not hydrolyzed but strongly bound by decapping scavenger (DcpS) enzymes and potently inhibits their activity.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 51 (2012) 8003-13.
  ORGANISM  Ascaris suum, Caenorhabditis elegans, Homo sapiens, Saccharomyces cerevisiae
  SEQUENCE  [up:D3K0N9] [cel:CELE_Y113G7A.9] [hsa:28960] [sce:YLR270W]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.6.1.59
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.6.1.59
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.6.1.59
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.6.1.59
///
