ENTRY       EC 3.6.3.18                 Enzyme
NAME        oligosaccharide-transporting ATPase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on acid anhydrides;
            Acting on acid anhydrides to catalyse transmembrane movement of substances
SYSNAME     ATP phosphohydrolase (disaccharide-importing)
REACTION    ATP + H2O + oligosaccharideout = ADP + phosphate + oligosaccharidein [RN:R00086]
ALL_REAC    R00086
SUBSTRATE   ATP [CPD:C00002];
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            oligosaccharide [CPD:C00930]
PRODUCT     ADP [CPD:C00008];
            phosphate [CPD:C00009];
            oligosaccharide [CPD:C00930]
COMMENT     ABC-type (ATP-binding cassette-type) ATPase, characterized by the presence of two similar ATP-binding domains. Does not undergo phosphorylation during the transport process. A bacterial enzyme that imports lactose, melibiose and raffinose.
HISTORY     EC 3.6.3.18 created 2000
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1282354]
  AUTHORS   Higgins CF.
  TITLE     ABC transporters: from microorganisms to man.
  JOURNAL   Annu. Rev. Cell. Biol. 8 (1992) 67-113.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7569321]
  AUTHORS   Kuan G, Dassa E, Saurin W, Hofnung M, Saier MH Jr.
  TITLE     Phylogenetic analyses of the ATP-binding constituents of bacterial extracytoplasmic receptor-dependent ABC-type nutrient uptake permeases.
  JOURNAL   Res. Microbiol. 146 (1995) 271-8.
  ORGANISM  bacteria
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8336670]
  AUTHORS   Tam R, Saier MH Jr.
  TITLE     Structural, functional, and evolutionary relationships among extracellular solute-binding receptors of bacteria.
  JOURNAL   Microbiol. Rev. 57 (1993) 320-46.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli, Streptococcus sp., Salmonella typhimurium, Klebsiella aerogenes
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9889977]
  AUTHORS   Saier MH Jr.
  TITLE     Molecular phylogeny as a basis for the classification of transport proteins from bacteria, archaea and eukarya.
  JOURNAL   Adv. Microb. Physiol. 40 (1998) 81-136.
  ORGANISM  bacteria
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:1630315]
  AUTHORS   Williams SG, Greenwood JA, Jones CW.
  TITLE     Molecular analysis of the lac operon encoding the binding-protein-dependent lactose transport system and beta-galactosidase in Agrobacterium radiobacter.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 6 (1992) 1755-68.
  ORGANISM  Agrobacterium radiobacter
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.6.3.18
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.6.3.18
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.6.3.18
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.6.3.18
///
