ENTRY       EC 3.6.3.50                 Enzyme
NAME        protein-secreting ATPase
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on acid anhydrides;
            Acting on acid anhydrides to catalyse transmembrane movement of substances
SYSNAME     ATP phosphohydrolase (protein-secreting)
REACTION    ATP + H2O = ADP + phosphate [RN:R00086]
ALL_REAC    R00086
SUBSTRATE   ATP [CPD:C00002];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     ADP [CPD:C00008];
            phosphate [CPD:C00009]
COMMENT     A non-phosphorylated, non-ABC (ATP-binding cassette) ATPase that is involved in protein transport. There are several families of enzymes included here, e.g. ATP-hydrolysing enzymes of the general secretory pathway (Sec or Type II), of the virulence-related secretory pathway (Type III) and of the conjugal DNA-protein transfer pathway (Type IV). Type II enzymes occur in bacteria, archaea and eucarya, whereas type III and type IV enzymes occur in bacteria where they form components of a multi-subunit complex.
HISTORY     EC 3.6.3.50 created 2000
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8022262]
  AUTHORS   Saier MH Jr, Tam R, Reizer A, Reizer J.
  TITLE     Two novel families of bacterial membrane proteins concerned with nodulation, cell division and transport.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 11 (1994) 841-7.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Alcaligenes eutrophus, Sinorhizobium meliloti
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8969244]
  AUTHORS   Mecsas JJ, Strauss EJ.
  TITLE     Molecular mechanisms of bacterial virulence: type III secretion and pathogenicity islands.
  JOURNAL   Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2 (1996) 270-88.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli, Yersinia spp., S. typhimurium, Salmonella spp.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9084158]
  AUTHORS   Thomas JD, Reeves PJ, Salmond GP.
  TITLE     The general secretion pathway of Erwinia carotovora subsp. carotovora: analysis of the membrane topology of OutC and OutF.
  JOURNAL   Microbiology. 143 ( Pt 3) (1997) 713-20.
  ORGANISM  Erwinia carotovora
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9115193]
  AUTHORS   Baker B, Zambryski P, Staskawicz B, Dinesh-Kumar SP.
  TITLE     Signaling in plant-microbe interactions.
  JOURNAL   Science. 276 (1997) 726-33.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:9680212]
  AUTHORS   Martinez A, Ostrovsky P, Nunn DN.
  TITLE     Identification of an additional member of the secretin superfamily of proteins in Pseudomonas aeruginosa that is able to function in type II protein secretion.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 28 (1998) 1235-46.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas aeruginosa
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:10085046]
  AUTHORS   Schuch R, Maurelli AT.
  TITLE     The mxi-Spa type III secretory pathway of Shigella flexneri requires an outer membrane lipoprotein, MxiM, for invasin translocation.
  JOURNAL   Infect. Immun. 67 (1999) 1982-91.
  ORGANISM  Shigella flexneri
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.6.3.50
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.6.3.50
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.6.3.50
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.6.3.50
///
