ENTRY       EC 3.6.5.3                  Enzyme
NAME        protein-synthesizing GTPase;
            elongation factor (EF);
            initiation factor (IF);
            peptide-release or termination factor
CLASS       Hydrolases;
            Acting on acid anhydrides;
            Acting on GTP to facilitate cellular and subcellular movement
SYSNAME     GTP phosphohydrolase (mRNA-translation-assisting)
REACTION    GTP + H2O = GDP + phosphate [RN:R00335]
ALL_REAC    R00335
SUBSTRATE   GTP [CPD:C00044];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
PRODUCT     GDP [CPD:C00035];
            phosphate [CPD:C00009]
COMMENT     This enzyme comprises a family of proteins involved in prokaryotic as well as eukaryotic protein synthesis. In the initiation factor complex, it is IF-2b (98 kDa) that binds GTP and subsequently hydrolyses it in prokaryotes. In eukaryotes, it is eIF-2 (150 kDa) that binds GTP. In the elongation phase, the GTP-hydrolysing proteins are the EF-Tu polypeptide of the prokaryotic transfer factor (43 kDa), the eukaryotic elongation factor EF-1alpha (53 kDa), the prokaryotic EF-G (77 kDa), the eukaryotic EF-2 (70-110 kDa) and the signal recognition particle that play a role in endoplasmic reticulum protein synthesis (325 kDa). EF-Tu and EF-1alpha catalyse binding of aminoacyl-tRNA to the ribosomal A-site, while EF-G and EF-2 catalyse the translocation of peptidyl-tRNA from the A-site to the P-site. GTPase activity is also involved in polypeptide release from the ribosome with the aid of the pRFs and eRFs.
HISTORY     EC 3.6.5.3 created 2000 as EC 3.6.1.48, transferred 2003 to EC 3.6.5.3
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:6566615]
  AUTHORS   Kurzchalia TV, Bommer UA, Babkina GT, Karpova GG.
  TITLE     GTP interacts with the gamma-subunit of eukaryotic initiation factor eIF-2.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 175 (1984) 313-6.
  ORGANISM  Rattus norvegicus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:8722024]
  AUTHORS   Kisselev LL, Frolova LYu.
  TITLE     Termination of translation in eukaryotes.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Cell. Biol. 73 (1995) 1079-86.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens, Xenopus laevis
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8985244]
  AUTHORS   Rodnina MV, Savelsbergh A, Katunin VI, Wintermeyer W.
  TITLE     Hydrolysis of GTP by elongation factor G drives tRNA movement on the ribosome.
  JOURNAL   Nature. 385 (1997) 37-41.
  ORGANISM  Thermus thermophilus, Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9233821]
  AUTHORS   Freistroffer DV, Pavlov MY, MacDougall J, Buckingham RH, Ehrenberg M.
  TITLE     Release factor RF3 in E.coli accelerates the dissociation of release factors RF1 and RF2 from the ribosome in a GTP-dependent manner.
  JOURNAL   EMBO. J. 16 (1997) 4126-33.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:9838020]
  AUTHORS   Krab IM, Parmeggiani A.
  TITLE     EF-Tu, a GTPase odyssey.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1443 (1998) 1-22.
  ORGANISM  Thermus thermophilus, Thermus aquaticus, Salmonella typhimurium
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 3.6.5.3
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 3.6.5.3
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 3.6.5.3
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 3.6.5.3
///
