ENTRY       EC 4.1.1.88                 Enzyme
NAME        biotin-independent malonate decarboxylase;
            malonate decarboxylase (without biotin);
            malonate decarboxylase (ambiguous);
            MDC
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-carbon lyases;
            Carboxy-lyases
SYSNAME     malonate carboxy-lyase (biotin-independent)
REACTION    malonate + H+ = acetate + CO2 [RN:R09483]
ALL_REAC    R09483
SUBSTRATE   malonate [CPD:C00383];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
PRODUCT     acetate [CPD:C00033];
            CO2 [CPD:C00011]
COMMENT     Two types of malonate decarboxylase are currently known, both of which form multienzyme complexes. This enzyme is a cytosolic protein that is biotin-independent. The other type is a biotin-dependent, Na+-translocating enzyme that includes both soluble and membrane-bound components (cf. EC 4.1.1.89, biotin-dependent malonate decarboxylase). As free malonate is chemically rather inert, it has to be activated prior to decarboxylation. In both enzymes, this is achieved by exchanging malonate with an acetyl group bound to an acyl-carrier protiein (ACP), to form malonyl-ACP and acetate, with subsequent decarboxylation regenerating the acetyl-ACP. The ACP subunit of both enzymes differs from that found in fatty-acid biosynthesis by having phosphopantethine attached to a serine side-chain as 2-(5-triphosphoribosyl)-3-dephospho-CoA rather than as phosphopantetheine 4'-phosphate. The individual enzymes involved in carrying out the reaction of this enzyme complex are EC 2.3.1.187 (acetyl-S-ACP:malonate ACP transferase), EC 2.3.1.39 ([acyl-carrier-protein] S-malonyltransferase) and EC 4.1.1.87 (malonyl-S-ACP decarboxylase). The carboxy group is lost with retention of configuration [6].
HISTORY     EC 4.1.1.88 created 2008
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8620876]
  AUTHORS   Schmid M, Berg M, Hilbi H, Dimroth P
  TITLE     Malonate decarboxylase of Klebsiella pneumoniae catalyses the turnover of acetyl and malonyl thioester residues on a coenzyme-A-like prosthetic group.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 237 (1996) 221-8.
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Byun, H.S. and Kim, Y.S.
  TITLE     Subunit organization of bacterial malonate decarboxylases: the smallest delta subunit as an acyl-carrier protein.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. Mol. Biol. 30 (1997) 132-137.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9208947]
  AUTHORS   Hoenke S, Schmid M, Dimroth P
  TITLE     Sequence of a gene cluster from Klebsiella pneumoniae encoding malonate decarboxylase and expression of the enzyme in Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 246 (1997) 530-8.
  ORGANISM  Klebsiella pneumoniae
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9851033]
  AUTHORS   Chohnan S, Fujio T, Takaki T, Yonekura M, Nishihara H, Takamura Y
  TITLE     Malonate decarboxylase of Pseudomonas putida is composed of five subunits.
  JOURNAL   FEMS. Microbiol. Lett. 169 (1998) 37-43.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:11052676]
  AUTHORS   Hoenke S, Schmid M, Dimroth P.
  TITLE     Identification of the active site of phosphoribosyl-dephospho-coenzyme A transferase and relationship of the enzyme to an ancient class of nucleotidyltransferases.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 39 (2000) 13233-40.
  ORGANISM  Klebsiella pneumoniae
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:10496981]
  AUTHORS   Handa S, Koo JH, Kim YS, Floss HG
  TITLE     Stereochemical course of biotin-independent malonate decarboxylase catalysis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 370 (1999) 93-6.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:10561613]
  AUTHORS   Koo JH, Kim YS
  TITLE     Functional evaluation of the genes involved in malonate decarboxylation by Acinetobacter calcoaceticus.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 266 (1999) 683-90.
  ORGANISM  Acinetobacter calcoaceticus
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:12359084]
  AUTHORS   Kim YS
  TITLE     Malonate metabolism: biochemistry, molecular biology, physiology, and industrial application.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. Mol. Biol. 35 (2002) 443-51.
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:11902724]
  AUTHORS   Dimroth P, Hilbi H
  TITLE     Enzymic and genetic basis for bacterial growth on malonate.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 25 (1997) 3-10.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.1.1.88
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.1.1.88
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.1.1.88
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.1.1.88
///
