ENTRY       EC 4.1.2.48                 Enzyme
NAME        low-specificity L-threonine aldolase;
            LtaE
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-carbon lyases;
            Aldehyde-lyases
SYSNAME     L-threonine/L-allo-threonine acetaldehyde-lyase (glycine-forming)
REACTION    (1) L-threonine = glycine + acetaldehyde;
            (2) L-allo-threonine = glycine + acetaldehyde
SUBSTRATE   L-threonine [CPD:C00188];
            L-allo-threonine [CPD:C05519]
PRODUCT     glycine [CPD:C00037];
            acetaldehyde [CPD:C00084]
COMMENT     Requires pyridoxal phosphate. The low-specificity L-threonine aldolase can act on both L-threonine and L-allo-threonine [1,2]. The enzyme from Escherichia coli can also act on L-threo-phenylserine and L-erythro-phenylserine [4]. The enzyme can also catalyse the aldol condensation of glycolaldehyde and glycine to form 4-hydroxy-L-threonine, an intermediate of pyridoxal phosphate biosynthesis [3]. Different from EC 4.1.2.5, L-threonine aldolase, and EC 4.1.2.49, L-allo-threonine aldolase.
HISTORY     EC 4.1.2.48 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:5438301]
  AUTHORS   Yamada H, Kumagai H, Nagate T, Yoshida H
  TITLE     Crystalline threonine aldolase from Candida humicola.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 39 (1970) 53-8.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:5017702]
  AUTHORS   Kumagai H, Nagate T, Yoshida H, Yamada H.
  TITLE     Threonine aldolase from Candida humicola. II. Purification, crystallization and properties.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 258 (1972) 779-90.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9151955]
  AUTHORS   Liu JQ, Nagata S, Dairi T, Misono H, Shimizu S, Yamada H
  TITLE     The GLY1 gene of Saccharomyces cerevisiae encodes a low-specific L-threonine aldolase that catalyzes cleavage of L-allo-threonine and L-threonine to glycine--expression of the gene in Escherichia coli and purification and characterization of the enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 245 (1997) 289-93.
  ORGANISM  Saccharomyces cerevisiae
  SEQUENCE  [sce:YEL046C]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9692922]
  AUTHORS   Liu JQ, Dairi T, Itoh N, Kataoka M, Shimizu S, Yamada H
  TITLE     Gene cloning, biochemical characterization and physiological role of a thermostable low-specificity L-threonine aldolase from Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 255 (1998) 220-6.
  ORGANISM  Escherichia coli
  SEQUENCE  [eco:b0870]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:21119630]
  AUTHORS   Kim J, Kershner JP, Novikov Y, Shoemaker RK, Copley SD
  TITLE     Three serendipitous pathways in E. coli can bypass a block in pyridoxal-5'-phosphate synthesis.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Syst. Biol. 6 (2010) 436.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.1.2.48
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.1.2.48
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.1.2.48
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.1.2.48
///
