ENTRY       EC 4.1.99.13                Enzyme
NAME        (6-4)DNA photolyase;
            DNA photolyase;
            H64PRH;
            NF-10;
            phr (6-4);
            PL-(6-4);
            OtCPF1;
            (6-4) PHR;
            At64PHR
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-carbon lyases;
            Other carbon-carbon lyases
SYSNAME     (6-4) photoproduct pyrimidine-lyase
REACTION    (6-4) photoproduct (in DNA) = 2 pyrimidine residues (in DNA)
SUBSTRATE   (6-4) photoproduct (in DNA)
PRODUCT     pyrimidine residues (in DNA)
COMMENT     A flavoprotein (FAD). The overall repair reaction consists of two distinct steps, one of which is light-independent and the other one light-dependent. In the initial light-independent step, a 6-iminium ion is thought to be generated via proton transfer induced by two histidines highly conserved among the (6-4) photolyases. This intermediate spontaneously rearranges to form an oxetane intermediate by intramolecular nucleophilic attack. In the subsequent light-driven reaction, one electron is believed to be transferred from the fully reduced FAD cofactor (FADH-) to the oxetane intermediate thus forming a neutral FADH radical and an anionic oxetane radical, which spontaneously fractures. The excess electron is then back-transferred to the flavin radical restoring the fully reduced flavin cofactor and a pair of pyrimidine bases [2].
HISTORY     EC 4.1.99.13 created 2009
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:19359474]
  AUTHORS   Hitomi K, DiTacchio L, Arvai AS, Yamamoto J, Kim ST, Todo T, Tainer JA, Iwai S, Panda S, Getzoff ED
  TITLE     Functional motifs in the (6-4) photolyase crystal structure make a comparative framework for DNA repair photolyases and clock cryptochromes.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 106 (2009) 6962-7.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana
  SEQUENCE  [ath:AT3G15620]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:17164245]
  AUTHORS   Schleicher E, Hitomi K, Kay CW, Getzoff ED, Todo T, Weber S
  TITLE     Electron nuclear double resonance differentiates complementary roles for active site histidines in (6-4) photolyase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 282 (2007) 4738-47.
  ORGANISM  Xenopus laevis
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.1.99.13
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.1.99.13
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.1.99.13
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.1.99.13
            CAS: 37290-70-3
///
