ENTRY       EC 4.1.1.89                 Enzyme
NAME        biotin-dependent malonate decarboxylase;
            malonate decarboxylase (with biotin);
            malonate decarboxylase (ambiguous)
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-carbon lyases;
            Carboxy-lyases
SYSNAME     malonate carboxy-lyase (biotin-dependent)
REACTION    malonate + H+ = acetate + CO2 [RN:R09483]
ALL_REAC    R09483
SUBSTRATE   malonate [CPD:C00383];
            H+ [CPD:C00080]
PRODUCT     acetate [CPD:C00033];
            CO2 [CPD:C00011]
COMMENT     Two types of malonate decarboxylase are currently known, both of which form multienzyme complexes. The enzyme described here is a biotin-dependent, Na+-translocating enzyme that includes both soluble and membrane-bound components [6]. The other type is a biotin-independent cytosolic protein (cf. EC 4.1.1.88, biotin-independent malonate decarboxylase). As free malonate is chemically rather inert, it has to be activated prior to decarboxylation. Both enzymes achieve this by exchanging malonate with an acetyl group bound to an acyl-carrier protiein (ACP), to form malonyl-ACP and acetate, with subsequent decarboxylation regenerating the acetyl-bound form of the enzyme. The ACP subunit of both enzymes differs from that found in fatty-acid biosynthesis by having phosphopantethine attached to a serine side-chain as 2-(5-triphosphoribosyl)-3-dephospho-CoA rather than as phosphopantetheine 4'-phosphate. In the anaerobic bacterium Malonomonas rubra, the components of the multienzyme complex/enzymes involved in carrying out the reactions of this enzyme are as follows: MadA (EC 2.3.1.187, acetyl-S-ACP:malonate ACP transferase), MadB (EC 4.3.99.2, carboxybiotin decarboxylase), MadC/MadD (EC 2.1.3.10, malonyl-S-ACP:biotin-protein carboxyltransferase) and MadH (EC 6.2.1.35, ACP-SH:acetate ligase). Two other components that are involved are MadE, the acyl-carrier protein and MadF, the biotin protein. The carboxy group is lost with retention of configuration [5].
HISTORY     EC 4.1.1.89 created 2008
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1628643]
  AUTHORS   Hilbi H, Dehning I, Schink B, Dimroth P
  TITLE     Malonate decarboxylase of Malonomonas rubra, a novel type of biotin-containing acetyl enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 207 (1992) 117-23.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:18251085]
  AUTHORS   Hilbi H, Dimroth P
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of a cytoplasmic enzyme component of the Na+-activated malonate decarboxylase system of Malonomonas rubra: acetyl-S-acyl carrier protein: malonate acyl carrier protein-SH transferase.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Microbiol. 162 (1994) 48-56.
  ORGANISM  Malonomonas rubra
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8664258]
  AUTHORS   Berg M, Hilbi H, Dimroth P
  TITLE     The acyl carrier protein of malonate decarboxylase of Malonomonas rubra contains 2'-(5"-phosphoribosyl)-3'-dephosphocoenzyme A as a prosthetic group.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 35 (1996) 4689-96.
  ORGANISM  Malonomonas rubra
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9128730]
  AUTHORS   Berg M, Hilbi H, Dimroth P
  TITLE     Sequence of a gene cluster from Malonomonas rubra encoding components of the malonate decarboxylase Na+ pump and evidence for their function.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 245 (1997) 103-15.
  ORGANISM  Malonomonas rubra
  SEQUENCE  [up:O06930]
REFERENCE   5
  AUTHORS   Micklefield, J., Harris, K.J., Groger, S., Mocek, U., Hilbi, H., Dimroth, P. and Floss, H.G.
  TITLE     Stereochemical course of malonate decarboxylase in Malonomonas rubra has biotin decarboxylation with retention.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 117 (1995) 1153-1154.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:12359084]
  AUTHORS   Kim YS
  TITLE     Malonate metabolism: biochemistry, molecular biology, physiology, and industrial application.
  JOURNAL   J. Biochem. Mol. Biol. 35 (2002) 443-51.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:11902724]
  AUTHORS   Dimroth P, Hilbi H
  TITLE     Enzymic and genetic basis for bacterial growth on malonate.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 25 (1997) 3-10.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.1.1.89
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.1.1.89
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.1.1.89
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.1.1.89
///
