ENTRY       EC 4.1.2.42                 Enzyme
NAME        D-threonine aldolase;
            D-TA;
            DTA;
            low specificity D-TA;
            low specificity D-threonine aldolase
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-carbon lyases;
            Aldehyde-lyases
SYSNAME     D-threonine acetaldehyde-lyase (glycine-forming)
REACTION    (1) D-threonine = glycine + acetaldehyde [RN:R08195];
            (2) D-allothreonine = glycine + acetaldehyde [RN:R08196]
ALL_REAC    R08195 R08196
SUBSTRATE   D-threonine [CPD:C00820];
            D-allothreonine [CPD:C12317]
PRODUCT     glycine [CPD:C00037];
            acetaldehyde [CPD:C00084]
COMMENT     A pyridoxal-phosphate protein that is activated by divalent metal cations (e.g. Co2+, Ni2+, Mn2+ or Mg2+) [1,2]. The reaction is reversible, which can lead to the interconversion of D-threonine and D-allothreonine [1]. Several other D-beta-hydroxy-alpha-amino acids, such as D-beta-phenylserine, D-beta-hydroxy-alpha-aminovaleric acid and D-beta-3,4-dihydroxyphenylserine, can also act as substrate [1].
HISTORY     EC 4.1.2.42 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9346293]
  AUTHORS   Kataoka M, Ikemi M, Morikawa T, Miyoshi T, Nishi K, Wada M, Yamada H, Shimizu S.
  TITLE     Isolation and characterization of D-threonine aldolase, a pyridoxal-5'-phosphate-dependent enzyme from Arthrobacter sp. DK-38.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 248 (1997) 385-93.
  ORGANISM  Arthrobacter sp.
  SEQUENCE  [up:O82872]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9642221]
  AUTHORS   Liu JQ, Dairi T, Itoh N, Kataoka M, Shimizu S, Yamada H.
  TITLE     A novel metal-activated pyridoxal enzyme with a unique primary structure, low specificity D-threonine aldolase from Arthrobacter sp. Strain DK-38. Molecular cloning and cofactor characterization.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 273 (1998) 16678-85.
  ORGANISM  Arthrobacter sp.
  SEQUENCE  [up:O82872]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10390816]
  AUTHORS   Liu JQ, Odani M, Dairi T, Itoh N, Shimizu S, Yamada H.
  TITLE     A new route to L-threo-3-[4-(methylthio)phenylserine], a key intermediate for the synthesis of antibiotics: recombinant low-specificity D-threonine aldolase-catalyzed stereospecific resolution.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 51 (1999) 586-91.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:10952004]
  AUTHORS   Liu JQ, Odani M, Yasuoka T, Dairi T, Itoh N, Kataoka M, Shimizu S, Yamada H.
  TITLE     Gene cloning and overproduction of low-specificity D-threonine aldolase from Alcaligenes xylosoxidans and its application for production of a key intermediate for parkinsonism drug.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 54 (2000) 44-51.
  ORGANISM  Achromobacter xylosoxidans
REFERENCE   5
  AUTHORS   Liu, J.Q., Dairi, T., Itoh, N., Kataoka, M., Shimizu, S. and Yamada, H.
  TITLE     Diversity of microbial threonine aldolases and their application.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Catal. B 10 (2000) 107-115.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:12686135]
  AUTHORS   Paiardini A, Contestabile R, D'Aguanno S, Pascarella S, Bossa F.
  TITLE     Threonine aldolase and alanine racemase: novel examples of convergent evolution in the superfamily of vitamin B6-dependent enzymes.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1647 (2003) 214-9.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.1.2.42
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.1.2.42
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.1.2.42
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.1.2.42
///
