ENTRY       EC 4.2.3.24                 Enzyme
NAME        amorpha-4,11-diene synthase;
            amorphadiene synthase
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on phosphates
SYSNAME     (2E,6E)-farnesyl-diphosphate diphosphate-lyase (amorpha-4,11-diene-forming)
REACTION    (2E,6E)-farnesyl diphosphate = amorpha-4,11-diene + diphosphate [RN:R07630]
ALL_REAC    R07630
SUBSTRATE   (2E,6E)-farnesyl diphosphate [CPD:C00448]
PRODUCT     amorpha-4,11-diene [CPD:C16028];
            diphosphate [CPD:C00013]
COMMENT     Requires Mg2+ and Mn2+ for activity. This is a key enzyme in the biosynthesis of the antimalarial endoperoxide artemisinin [3]. Catalyses the formation of both olefinic [e.g. amorpha-4,11-diene, amorpha-4,7(11)-diene, gamma-humulene and beta-sesquiphellandrene] and oxygenated (e.g. amorpha-4-en-7-ol) sesquiterpenes, with amorpha-4,11-diene being the major product. When geranyl diphosphate is used as a substrate, no monoterpenes are produced [2].
HISTORY     EC 4.2.3.24 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:11289612]
  AUTHORS   Wallaart TE, Bouwmeester HJ, Hille J, Poppinga L, Maijers NC.
  TITLE     Amorpha-4,11-diene synthase: cloning and functional expression of a key enzyme in the biosynthetic pathway of the novel antimalarial drug artemisinin.
  JOURNAL   Planta. 212 (2001) 460-5.
  ORGANISM  Artemisia annua
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9AR04]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:11032404]
  AUTHORS   Mercke P, Bengtsson M, Bouwmeester HJ, Posthumus MA, Brodelius PE.
  TITLE     Molecular cloning, expression, and characterization of amorpha-4,11-diene synthase, a key enzyme of artemisinin biosynthesis in Artemisia annua L.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 381 (2000) 173-80.
  ORGANISM  Artemisia annua
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9AR04]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10626375]
  AUTHORS   Bouwmeester HJ, Wallaart TE, Janssen MH, van Loo B, Jansen BJ, Posthumus MA, Schmidt CO, De Kraker JW, Konig WA, Franssen MC.
  TITLE     Amorpha-4,11-diene synthase catalyses the first probable step in artemisinin biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Phytochemistry. 52 (1999) 843-54.
  ORGANISM  Artemisia annua
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:11185551]
  AUTHORS   Chang YJ, Song SH, Park SH, Kim SU.
  TITLE     Amorpha-4,11-diene synthase of Artemisia annua: cDNA isolation and bacterial expression of a terpene synthase involved in artemisinin biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 383 (2000) 178-84.
  ORGANISM  Artemisia annua
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9AR04]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:12778056]
  AUTHORS   Martin VJ, Pitera DJ, Withers ST, Newman JD, Keasling JD.
  TITLE     Engineering a mevalonate pathway in Escherichia coli for production of terpenoids.
  JOURNAL   Nat. Biotechnol. 21 (2003) 796-802.
  ORGANISM  Saccharomyces cerevisiae
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:16143293]
  AUTHORS   Picaud S, Mercke P, He X, Sterner O, Brodelius M, Cane DE, Brodelius PE.
  TITLE     Amorpha-4,11-diene synthase: mechanism and stereochemistry of the enzymatic cyclization of farnesyl diphosphate.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 448 (2006) 150-5.
  ORGANISM  Artemisia annua
PATHWAY     ec00909  Sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K14178  amorpha-4,11-diene synthase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.24
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.3.24
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.3.24
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.24
            CAS: 259213-60-0
///
