ENTRY       EC 4.2.2.10                 Enzyme
NAME        pectin lyase;
            pectin trans-eliminase;
            endo-pectin lyase;
            polymethylgalacturonic transeliminase;
            pectin methyltranseliminase;
            pectolyase;
            PL;
            PNL;
            PMGL
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on polysaccharides
SYSNAME     (1->4)-6-O-methyl-alpha-D-galacturonan lyase
REACTION    Eliminative cleavage of (1->4)-alpha-D-galacturonan methyl ester to give oligosaccharides with 4-deoxy-6-O-methyl-alpha-D-galact-4-enuronosyl groups at their non-reducing ends
COMMENT     Favours pectin, the methyl ester, over pectate, the anion (which is the preferred substrate of EC 4.2.2.2, pectate lyase). Demethylation progressively slows its action; it can nevertheless cleave on either side of a demethylated residue if the residue at the other end of the scissile bond is methylated.
HISTORY     EC 4.2.2.10 created 1972, modified 2002
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Albersheim, P., Neukom, H. and Deuel, H.
  TITLE     Uber die Bildung von ungesattigten Abbauprodukten durch ein pekinabbauendes Enzym.
  JOURNAL   Helv. Chim. Acta 43 (1960) 1422-1426.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9195887]
  AUTHORS   Mayans O, Scott M, Connerton I, Gravesen T, Benen J, Visser J, Pickersgill R, Jenkins J.
  TITLE     Two crystal structures of pectin lyase A from Aspergillus reveal a pH driven conformational change and striking divergence in the substrate-binding clefts of pectin and pectate lyases.
  JOURNAL   Structure. 5 (1997) 677-89.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus niger
  SEQUENCE  [ang:ANI_1_624124]
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   Kester, H.C.M and Visser, J.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of pectin lyase B, a novel pectinolytic enzyme from Aspergillus niger.
  JOURNAL   FEMS Microbiol. Lett. 120 (1994) 63-68.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12110197]
  AUTHORS   Mutenda KE, Korner R, Christensen TM, Mikkelsen J, Roepstorff P.
  TITLE     Application of mass spectrometry to determine the activity and specificity of pectin lyase A.
  JOURNAL   Carbohydr. Res. 337 (2002) 1217-27.
  ORGANISM  Aspergillus niger
ORTHOLOGY   K01732  
GENES       AFM: AFUA_2G00800 AFUA_5G10380 AFUA_7G05030
            ANG: ANI_1_624124(An14g04370)
            ECA: ECA1499(pnl)
            PSP: PSPPH_1424(hopAK1) PSPPH_3992(pnlA)
            BSU: BSU18650(pelB)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.2.10
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.2.10
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.2.10
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.2.10
            CAS: 9033-35-6
///
