ENTRY       EC 4.2.3.124                Enzyme
NAME        2-deoxy-scyllo-inosose synthase;
            btrC (gene name);
            neoC (gene name);
            kanC (gene name)
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on phosphates
SYSNAME     D-glucose-6-phosphate phosphate-lyase (2-deoxy-L-scyllo-inosose-forming)
REACTION    D-glucose 6-phosphate = 2-deoxy-L-scyllo-inosose + phosphate [RN:R08617]
ALL_REAC    R08617
SUBSTRATE   D-glucose 6-phosphate [CPD:C00092]
PRODUCT     2-deoxy-L-scyllo-inosose [CPD:C17209];
            phosphate [CPD:C00009]
COMMENT     Requires Co2+ [2]. Involved in the biosynthetic pathways of several clinically important aminocyclitol antibiotics, including kanamycin, butirosin, neomycin and ribostamycin. Requires an NAD+ cofactor, which is transiently reduced during the reaction [1,4]. The enzyme from the bacterium Bacillus circulans forms a complex with the glutamine amidotransferase subunit of pyridoxal 5'-phosphate synthase (EC 4.3.3.6), which appears to stabilize the complex [6,7].
HISTORY     EC 4.2.3.124 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9207913]
  AUTHORS   Kudo F, Yamauchi N, Suzuki R, Kakinuma K
  TITLE     Kinetic isotope effect and reaction mechanism of 2-deoxy-scyllo-inosose synthase  derived from butirosin-producing Bacillus circulans.
  JOURNAL   J. Antibiot. (Tokyo). 50 (1997) 424-8.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus circulans
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9S5E2]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:10344560]
  AUTHORS   Kudo F, Hosomi Y, Tamegai H, Kakinuma K
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of 2-deoxy-scyllo-inosose synthase derived from Bacillus circulans. A crucial carbocyclization enzyme in the biosynthesis of 2-deoxystreptamine-containing aminoglycoside antibiotics.
  JOURNAL   J. Antibiot. (Tokyo). 52 (1999) 81-8.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus circulans
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9S5E2]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10470681]
  AUTHORS   Kudo F, Tamegai H, Fujiwara T, Tagami U, Hirayama K, Kakinuma K
  TITLE     Molecular cloning of the gene for the key carbocycle-forming enzyme in the biosynthesis of 2-deoxystreptamine-containing aminocyclitol antibiotics and its comparison with dehydroquinate synthase.
  JOURNAL   J. Antibiot. (Tokyo). 52 (1999) 559-71.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus circulans
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9S5E2]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15788164]
  AUTHORS   Huang Z, Kakinuma K, Eguchi T
  TITLE     Stereospecificity of hydride transfer in NAD+-catalyzed 2-deoxy-scyllo-inosose synthase, the key enzyme in the biosynthesis of 2-deoxystreptamine-containing aminocyclitol antibiotics.
  JOURNAL   Bioorg. Chem. 33 (2005) 82-9.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus circulans
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9S5E2]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15928851]
  AUTHORS   Thuy ML, Kharel MK, Lamichhane R, Lee HC, Suh JW, Liou K, Sohng JK
  TITLE     Expression of 2-deoxy-scyllo-inosose synthase (kanA) from kanamycin gene cluster  in Streptomyces lividans.
  JOURNAL   Biotechnol. Lett. 27 (2005) 465-70.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces lividans
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:12224638]
  AUTHORS   Tamegai H, Nango E, Koike-Takeshita A, Kudo F, Kakinuma K
  TITLE     Significance of the 20-kDa subunit of heterodimeric 2-deoxy-scyllo-inosose synthase for the biosynthesis of butirosin antibiotics in Bacillus circulans.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 66 (2002) 1538-45.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus circulans
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:20530911]
  AUTHORS   Tamegai H, Sawada H, Nango E, Aoki R, Hirakawa H, Iino T, Eguchi T
  TITLE     Roles of a 20 kDa protein associated with a carbocycle-forming enzyme involved in aminoglycoside biosynthesis in primary and secondary metabolism.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 74 (2010) 1215-9.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus circulans
PATHWAY     ec00524  Butirosin and neomycin biosynthesis
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K13546  2-deoxy-scyllo-inosose synthase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.124
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.3.124
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.3.124
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.124
///
