ENTRY       EC 4.2.3.117                Enzyme
NAME        (-)-camphene synthase;
            CS
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on phosphates
SYSNAME     geranyl-diphosphate diphosphate-lyase [cyclizing, (-)-camphene-forming]
REACTION    geranyl diphosphate = (-)-camphene + diphosphate [RN:R09972]
ALL_REAC    R09972
SUBSTRATE   geranyl diphosphate [CPD:C00341]
PRODUCT     (-)-camphene [CPD:C06305];
            diphosphate [CPD:C00013]
COMMENT     (-)-Camphene is the major product in Abies grandis (grand fir) with traces of other monoterpenoids [1]. In Pseudotsuga menziesii (Douglas-fir) there are about equal parts of (-)-camphene and (-)-alpha-pinene with traces of four other monoterpenoids [2,3]. In Solanum lycopersicum (tomato) tricyclene, beta-myrcene, limonene, and traces of several other monoterpenoids are also formed [4]. See also EC 4.2.3.15 myrcene synthase, EC 4.2.3.16 (4S)-limonene synthase, EC 4.2.3.119 (-)-alpha-pinene synthase and EC 4.2.3.105 tricyclene synthase.
HISTORY     EC 4.2.3.117 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10441373]
  AUTHORS   Bohlmann J, Phillips M, Ramachandiran V, Katoh S, Croteau R
  TITLE     cDNA cloning, characterization, and functional expression of four new monoterpene synthase members of the Tpsd gene family from grand fir (Abies grandis).
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 368 (1999) 232-43.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q948Z0]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:15921711]
  AUTHORS   Huber DP, Philippe RN, Godard KA, Sturrock RN, Bohlmann J
  TITLE     Characterization of four terpene synthase cDNAs from methyl jasmonate-induced Douglas-fir, Pseudotsuga menziesii.
  JOURNAL   Phytochemistry. 66 (2005) 1427-39.
  ORGANISM  Pseudotsuga menziesii
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q4QSN4]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:15978541]
  AUTHORS   Hyatt DC, Croteau R
  TITLE     Mutational analysis of a monoterpene synthase reaction: altered catalysis through directed mutagenesis of (-)-pinene synthase from Abies grandis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 439 (2005) 222-33.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:21813655]
  AUTHORS   Falara V, Akhtar TA, Nguyen TT, Spyropoulou EA, Bleeker PM, Schauvinhold I, Matsuba Y, Bonini ME, Schilmiller AL, Last RL, Schuurink RC, Pichersky E
  TITLE     The tomato terpene synthase gene family.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 157 (2011) 770-89.
  ORGANISM  Solanum lycopersicum
  SEQUENCE  [sly:101245212]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.117
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.3.117
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.3.117
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.117
///
