ENTRY       EC 4.2.3.121                Enzyme
NAME        (+)-alpha-pinene synthase;
            (+)-alpha-pinene cyclase;
            cyclase I
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on phosphates
SYSNAME     geranyl-diphosphate diphosphate-lyase [cyclizing, (+)-alpha-pinene-forming]
REACTION    geranyl diphosphate = (+)-alpha-pinene + diphosphate [RN:R09974]
ALL_REAC    R09974
SUBSTRATE   geranyl diphosphate [CPD:C00341]
PRODUCT     (+)-alpha-pinene [CPD:C06306];
            diphosphate [CPD:C00013]
COMMENT     Cyclase I of Salvia officinalis (sage) gives about equal parts (+)-alpha-pinene and (+)-camphene, whereas cyclase III gives about equal parts of (+)-alpha-pinene and (+)-beta-pinene. (3R)-Linalyl diphosphate can also be used by the enzyme in preference to (3S)-linalyl diphosphate. The 4-pro-R-hydrogen of geranyl diphosphate is lost. Requires Mg2+ (preferred to Mn2+) [1-4]. With synthase II of Pinus taeda (loblolly pine) (+)-alpha-pinene was the only product [5,6]. Requires Mn2+ (preferred to Mg2+). See also EC 4.2.3.122, (+)-beta-pinene synthase, and EC 4.2.3.116, (+)-camphene synthase.
HISTORY     EC 4.2.3.121 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:6693393]
  AUTHORS   Gambliel H, Croteau R
  TITLE     Pinene cyclases I and II. Two enzymes from sage (Salvia officinalis) which catalyze stereospecific cyclizations of geranyl pyrophosphate to monoterpene olefins of opposite configuration.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 259 (1984) 740-8.
  ORGANISM  Salvia officinalis
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:3392006]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Satterwhite DM, Cane DE, Chang CC
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of monoterpenes. Enantioselectivity in the enzymatic cyclization of  (+)- and (-)-linalyl pyrophosphate to (+)- and (-)-pinene and (+)- and (-)-camphene.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 263 (1988) 10063-71.
  ORGANISM  Salvia officinalis
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8109978]
  AUTHORS   Wagschal KC, Pyun HJ, Coates RM, Croteau R.
  TITLE     Monoterpene biosynthesis: isotope effects associated with bicyclic olefin formation catalyzed by pinene synthases from sage (Salvia officinalis).
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 308 (1994) 477-87.
  ORGANISM  Salvia officinalis
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:8109979]
  AUTHORS   Pyun HJ, Wagschal KC, Jung DI, Coates RM, Croteau R
  TITLE     Stereochemistry of the proton elimination in the formation of (+)- and (-)-alpha-pinene by monoterpene cyclases from sage (Salvia officinalis).
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 308 (1994) 488-96.
  ORGANISM  Salvia officinalis
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:10562434]
  AUTHORS   Phillips MA, Savage TJ, Croteau R
  TITLE     Monoterpene synthases of loblolly pine (Pinus taeda) produce pinene isomers and enantiomers.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 372 (1999) 197-204.
  ORGANISM  Pinus taeda
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:12623076]
  AUTHORS   Phillips MA, Wildung MR, Williams DC, Hyatt DC, Croteau R
  TITLE     cDNA isolation, functional expression, and characterization of (+)-alpha-pinene synthase and (-)-alpha-pinene synthase from loblolly pine (Pinus taeda): stereocontrol in pinene biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 411 (2003) 267-76.
  ORGANISM  Pinus taeda
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q84KL3]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.121
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.3.121
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.3.121
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.121
///
