ENTRY       EC 4.2.2.19                 Enzyme
NAME        chondroitin B lyase;
            chondroitinase B;
            ChonB;
            ChnB
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on polysaccharides
SYSNAME     chondroitin B lyase
REACTION    Eliminative cleavage of dermatan sulfate containing (1->4)-beta-D-hexosaminyl and (1->3)-beta-D-glucurosonyl or (1->3)-alpha-L-iduronosyl linkages to disaccharides containing 4-deoxy-beta-D-gluc-4-enuronosyl groups to yield a 4,5-unsaturated dermatan-sulfate disaccharide (DeltaUA-GalNAc-4S).
COMMENT     This is the only lyase that is known to be specific for dermatan sulfate as substrate. The minimum substrate length required for catalysis is a tetrasaccharide [2]. In general, chondroitin sulfate (CS) and dermatan sulfate (DS) chains comprise a linkage region, a chain cap and a repeat region. The repeat region of CS is a repeating disaccharide of glucuronic acid (GlcA) and N-acetylgalactosamine (GalNAc) [-4)GlcA(beta1-3)GalNAc(beta1-]n, which may be O-sulfated on the C-4 and/or C-6 of GalNAc and C-2 of GlcA. GlcA residues of CS may be epimerized to iduronic acid (IdoA) forming the repeating disaccharide [-4)IdoA(alpha1-3)GalNAc(beta1-]n of DS. Both the concentrations and locations of sulfate-ester substituents vary with glucosaminoglycan source [5].
HISTORY     EC 4.2.2.19 created 2005
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8526872]
  AUTHORS   Gu K, Linhardt RJ, Laliberte M, Gu K, Zimmermann J.
  TITLE     Purification, characterization and specificity of chondroitin lyases and glycuronidase from Flavobacterium heparinum.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 312 ( Pt 2) (1995) 569-77.
  ORGANISM  Pedobacter heparinus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12063249]
  AUTHORS   Pojasek K, Raman R, Kiley P, Venkataraman G, Sasisekharan R.
  TITLE     Biochemical characterization of the chondroitinase B active site.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 277 (2002) 31179-86.
  ORGANISM  Pedobacter heparinus
  SEQUENCE  [phe:Phep_0789]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11500043]
  AUTHORS   Pojasek K, Shriver Z, Kiley P, Venkataraman G, Sasisekharan R.
  TITLE     Recombinant expression, purification, and kinetic characterization of chondroitinase AC and chondroitinase B from Flavobacterium heparinum.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 286 (2001) 343-51.
  ORGANISM  Pedobacter heparinus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12443044]
  AUTHORS   Suzuki K, Terasaki Y, Uyeda M.
  TITLE     Inhibition of hyaluronidases and chondroitinases by fatty acids.
  JOURNAL   J. Enzyme. Inhib. Med. Chem. 17 (2002) 183-6.
  ORGANISM  Pedobacter heparinus
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:427837]
  AUTHORS   Ototani N, Yosizawa Z.
  TITLE     Purification of chondroitinase B and chondroitinase C using glycosaminoglycan-bound AH-Sepharose 4B.
  JOURNAL   Carbohydr. Res. 70 (1979) 295-306.
  ORGANISM  Pedobacter heparinus
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:10618199]
  AUTHORS   Tkalec AL, Fink D, Blain F, Zhang-Sun G, Laliberte M, Bennett DC, Gu K, Zimmermann JJ, Su H.
  TITLE     Isolation and expression in Escherichia coli of cslA and cslB, genes coding for the chondroitin sulfate-degrading enzymes chondroitinase AC and chondroitinase B, respectively, from Flavobacterium heparinum.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 66 (2000) 29-35.
  ORGANISM  Pedobacter heparinus
  SEQUENCE  [phe:Phep_0789]
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:15155751]
  AUTHORS   Michel G, Pojasek K, Li Y, Sulea T, Linhardt RJ, Raman R, Prabhakar V, Sasisekharan R, Cygler M.
  TITLE     The structure of chondroitin B lyase complexed with glycosaminoglycan oligosaccharides unravels a calcium-dependent catalytic machinery.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 279 (2004) 32882-96.
  ORGANISM  Pedobacter heparinus
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:10216304]
  AUTHORS   Li Y, Matte A, Su H, Cygler M.
  TITLE     Crystallization and preliminary X-ray analysis of chondroitinase B from Flavobacterium heparinum.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 55 (1999) 1055-7.
  ORGANISM  Pedobacter heparinus
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:10600383]
  AUTHORS   Huang W, Matte A, Li Y, Kim YS, Linhardt RJ, Su H, Cygler M.
  TITLE     Crystal structure of chondroitinase B from Flavobacterium heparinum and its complex with a disaccharide product at 1.7 A resolution.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 294 (1999) 1257-69.
  ORGANISM  Pedobacter heparinus
  SEQUENCE  [phe:Phep_0789]
REFERENCE   10 [PMID:16336265]
  AUTHORS   Huckerby TN, Nieduszynski IA, Giannopoulos M, Weeks SD, Sadler IH, Lauder RM.
  TITLE     Characterization of oligosaccharides from the chondroitin/dermatan sulfates. 1H-NMR and 13C-NMR studies of reduced trisaccharides and hexasaccharides.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. J. 272 (2005) 6276-86.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.2.19
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.2.19
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.2.19
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.2.19
            CAS: 52227-83-5
///
