ENTRY       EC 4.2.1.111                Enzyme
NAME        1,5-anhydro-D-fructose dehydratase;
            1,5-anhydro-D-fructose 4-dehydratase;
            1,5-anhydro-D-fructose hydrolyase;
            1,5-anhydro-D-arabino-hex-2-ulose dehydratase;
            AFDH;
            AF dehydratase;
            1,5-anhydro-D-fructose hydro-lyase
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Hydro-lyases
SYSNAME     1,5-anhydro-D-fructose hydro-lyase (ascopyrone-M-forming)
REACTION    1,5-anhydro-D-fructose = 1,5-anhydro-4-deoxy-D-glycero-hex-3-en-2-ulose + H2O [RN:R09694]
ALL_REAC    R09694
SUBSTRATE   1,5-anhydro-D-fructose [CPD:C06485]
PRODUCT     1,5-anhydro-4-deoxy-D-glycero-hex-3-en-2-ulose [CPD:C19822];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     This enzyme catalyses one of the steps in the anhydrofructose pathway, which leads to the degradation of glycogen and starch via 1,5-anhydro-D-fructose [1,2]. The other enzymes involved in this pathway are EC 4.2.1.110 (aldos-2-ulose dehydratase), EC 4.2.2.13 [exo-(1->4)-alpha-D-glucan lyase] and EC 5.3.2.7 (ascopyrone tautomerase). Requires divalent (Ca2+ or Mg2+) or monovalent cations (Na+) for optimal activity. Unlike EC 4.2.1.110, the enzyme is specific for 1,5-anhydro-D-fructose as substrate and shows no activity towards aldose-2-uloses such as 2-dehydroglucose [1,2,3]. In addition, it is inhibited by its end-product ascopyrone M [2] and it cannot convert ascopyrone M into microthecin, as can EC 4.2.1.110.
HISTORY     EC 4.2.1.111 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:15110094]
  AUTHORS   Yu S, Refdahl C, Lundt I.
  TITLE     Enzymatic description of the anhydrofructose pathway of glycogen degradation; I. Identification and purification of anhydrofructose dehydratase, ascopyrone tautomerase and alpha-1,4-glucan lyase in the fungus Anthracobia melaloma.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1672 (2004) 120-9.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:16822618]
  AUTHORS   Yu S, Fiskesund R.
  TITLE     The anhydrofructose pathway and its possible role in stress response and signaling.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1760 (2006) 1314-22.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:15716041]
  AUTHORS   Yu S.
  TITLE     Enzymatic description of the anhydrofructose pathway of glycogen degradation II. Gene identification and characterization of the reactions catalyzed by aldos-2-ulose dehydratase that converts 1,5-anhydro-D-fructose to microthecin with ascopyrone M as the intermediate.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1723 (2005) 63-73.
  ORGANISM  Phanerochaete chrysosporium
  SEQUENCE  [up:P84193]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.1.111
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.1.111
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.1.111
            UM-BBD (Biocatalysis/Biodegradation Database): 4.2.1.111
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.1.111
///
