ENTRY       EC 4.2.3.120                Enzyme
NAME        (-)-beta-pinene synthase;
            beta-geraniolene synthase;
            (-)-(1S,5S)-pinene synthase;
            geranyldiphosphate diphosphate lyase (pinene forming)
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on phosphates
SYSNAME     geranyl-diphosphate diphosphate-lyase [cyclizing, (-)-beta-pinene-forming]
REACTION    geranyl diphosphate = (-)-beta-pinene + diphosphate [RN:R05766]
ALL_REAC    R05766
SUBSTRATE   geranyl diphosphate [CPD:C00341]
PRODUCT     (-)-beta-pinene [CPD:C06307];
            diphosphate [CPD:C00013]
COMMENT     Cyclase II of Salvia officinalis (sage) produces about equal parts (-)-alpha-pinene, (-)-beta-pinene and (-)-camphene, plus traces of other monoterpenoids. The enzyme, which requires Mg2+ (preferred to Mn2+), can also use (3S)-Linalyl diphosphate (preferred to (3R)-linalyl diphosphate) [1-4]. The enzyme from Abies grandis (grand fir) produces roughly equal parts of (-)-alpha-pinene and (-)-beta-pinene [6-9]. Cyclase IV from Pinus contorta (lodgepole pine) produces 63% (-)-beta-pinene, 26% 3-carene, and traces of alpha-pinene [10]. Synthase III from Pinus taeda (loblolly pine) forms (-)-beta-pinene with traces of alpha-pinene and requires Mn2+ and K+ (Mg2+ is ineffective) [11]. A cloned enzyme from Artemisia annua (sweet wormwood) gave (-)-beta-pinene with traces of (-)-alpha-pinene [5]. The enzyme from Picea sitchensis (Sika spruce) forms 30% (-)-beta-pinene and 70% (-)-alpha-pinene [12]. See also EC 4.2.3.119, (-)-alpha-pinene synthase, EC 4.2.3.117, (-)-camphene synthase, and EC 4.2.3.107 (+)-3-carene synthase.
HISTORY     EC 4.2.3.120 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3314988]
  AUTHORS   Croteau RB, Wheeler CJ, Cane DE, Ebert R, Ha HJ
  TITLE     Isotopically sensitive branching in the formation of cyclic monoterpenes: proof that (-)-alpha-pinene and (-)-beta-pinene are synthesized by the same monoterpene cyclase via deprotonation of a common intermediate.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 26 (1987) 5383-9.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:2768265]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Satterwhite DM
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of monoterpenes. Stereochemical implications of acyclic and monocyclic olefin formation by (+)- and (-)-pinene cyclases from sage.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 264 (1989) 15309-15.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:3392006]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Satterwhite DM, Cane DE, Chang CC
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of monoterpenes. Enantioselectivity in the enzymatic cyclization of  (+)- and (-)-linalyl pyrophosphate to (+)- and (-)-pinene and (+)- and (-)-camphene.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 263 (1988) 10063-71.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:8109979]
  AUTHORS   Pyun HJ, Wagschal KC, Jung DI, Coates RM, Croteau R
  TITLE     Stereochemistry of the proton elimination in the formation of (+)- and (-)-alpha-pinene by monoterpene cyclases from sage (Salvia officinalis).
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 308 (1994) 488-96.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:12226526]
  AUTHORS   Lu S, Xu R, Jia JW, Pang J, Matsuda SP, Chen XY
  TITLE     Cloning and functional characterization of a beta-pinene synthase from Artemisia  annua that shows a circadian pattern of expression.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 130 (2002) 477-86.
  ORGANISM  Artemisia annua
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q94G53]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:1898071]
  AUTHORS   Gijzen M, Lewinsohn E, Croteau R.
  TITLE     Characterization of the constitutive and wound-inducible monoterpene cyclases of grand fir (Abies grandis).
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 289 (1991) 267-73.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:1731633]
  AUTHORS   Lewinsohn E, Gijzen M, Croteau R
  TITLE     Wound-inducible pinene cyclase from grand fir: purification, characterization, and renaturation after SDS-PAGE.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 293 (1992) 167-73.
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:9268308]
  AUTHORS   Bohlmann J, Steele CL, Croteau R.
  TITLE     Monoterpene synthases from grand fir (Abies grandis). cDNA isolation, characterization, and functional expression of myrcene synthase, (-)-(4S)-limonene synthase, and (-)-(1S,5S)-pinene synthase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 272 (1997) 21784-92.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
  SEQUENCE  [up:O24475]
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:15978541]
  AUTHORS   Hyatt DC, Croteau R
  TITLE     Mutational analysis of a monoterpene synthase reaction: altered catalysis through directed mutagenesis of (-)-pinene synthase from Abies grandis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 439 (2005) 222-33.
REFERENCE   10 [PMID:7625832]
  AUTHORS   Savage TJ, Ichii H, Hume SD, Little DB, Croteau R
  TITLE     Monoterpene synthases from gymnosperms and angiosperms: stereospecificity and inactivation by cysteinyl- and arginyl-directed modifying reagents.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 320 (1995) 257-65.
REFERENCE   11 [PMID:10562434]
  AUTHORS   Phillips MA, Savage TJ, Croteau R
  TITLE     Monoterpene synthases of loblolly pine (Pinus taeda) produce pinene isomers and enantiomers.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 372 (1999) 197-204.
REFERENCE   12 [PMID:12970502]
  AUTHORS   McKay SA, Hunter WL, Godard KA, Wang SX, Martin DM, Bohlmann J, Plant AL
  TITLE     Insect attack and wounding induce traumatic resin duct development and gene expression of (-)-pinene synthase in Sitka spruce.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 133 (2003) 368-78.
  ORGANISM  Picea sitchensis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q6XDB5]
PATHWAY     ec00902  Monoterpenoid biosynthesis
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K07384  pinene synthase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.120
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.3.120
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.3.120
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.120
///
