ENTRY       EC 4.2.2.5                  Enzyme
NAME        chondroitin AC lyase;
            chondroitinase (ambiguous);
            chondroitin sulfate lyase;
            chondroitin AC eliminase;
            chondroitinase AC;
            ChnAC
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on polysaccharides
SYSNAME     chondroitin AC lyase
REACTION    Eliminative degradation of polysaccharides containing 1,4-beta-D-hexosaminyl and 1,3-beta-D-glucuronosyl linkages to disaccharides containing 4-deoxy-beta-D-gluc-4-enuronosyl groups
COMMENT     Acts on chondroitin 4-sulfate and chondroitin 6-sulfate, but less well on hyaluronate. In general, chondroitin sulfate (CS) and dermatan sulfate (DS) chains comprise a linkage region, a chain cap and a repeat region. The repeat region of CS is a repeating disaccharide of glucuronic acid (GlcA) and N-acetylgalactosamine (GalNAc) [-4)GlcA(beta1-3)GalNAc(beta1-]n, which may be O-sulfated on the C-4 and/or C-6 of GalNAc and C-2 of GlcA. GlcA residues of CS may be epimerized to iduronic acid (IdoA) forming the repeating disaccharide [-4)IdoA(alpha1-3)GalNAc(beta1-]n of DS. Both the concentrations and locations of sulfate-ester substituents vary with glucosaminoglycan source [4].
HISTORY     EC 4.2.2.5 created 1972 (EC 4.2.99.6 created 1965, part incorporated 1976)
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:13727579]
  AUTHORS   NAKADA HI, WOLFE JB.
  TITLE     Studies on the enzyme chondroitinase: product structure and ion effects.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 94 (1961) 244-51.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:11500043]
  AUTHORS   Pojasek K, Shriver Z, Kiley P, Venkataraman G, Sasisekharan R.
  TITLE     Recombinant expression, purification, and kinetic characterization of chondroitinase AC and chondroitinase B from Flavobacterium heparinum.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 286 (2001) 343-51.
  ORGANISM  Pedobacter heparinus
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:9761894]
  AUTHORS   Fethiere J, Shilton BH, Li Y, Allaire M, Laliberte M, Eggimann B, Cygler M.
  TITLE     Crystallization and preliminary analysis of chondroitinase AC from Flavobacterium heparinum.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 54 ( Pt 2) (1998) 279-80.
  ORGANISM  Pedobacter heparinus
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:16336265]
  AUTHORS   Huckerby TN, Nieduszynski IA, Giannopoulos M, Weeks SD, Sadler IH, Lauder RM.
  TITLE     Characterization of oligosaccharides from the chondroitin/dermatan sulfates. 1H-NMR and 13C-NMR studies of reduced trisaccharides and hexasaccharides.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. J. 272 (2005) 6276-86.
  ORGANISM  Bos taurus
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.2.5
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.2.5
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.2.5
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.2.5
            CAS: 9047-57-8
///
