ENTRY       EC 4.2.2.21                 Enzyme
NAME        chondroitin-sulfate-ABC exolyase;
            chondroitinase (ambiguous);
            chondroitin ABC eliminase (ambiguous);
            chondroitinase ABC (ambiguous);
            chondroitin ABC lyase (ambiguous);
            chondroitin sulfate ABC lyase (ambiguous);
            ChS ABC lyase (ambiguous);
            chondroitin sulfate ABC exoeliminase;
            chondroitin sulfate ABC exolyase;
            ChS ABC lyase II
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on polysaccharides
SYSNAME     chondroitin-sulfate-ABC exolyase
REACTION    Exolytic removal of Delta4-unsaturated disaccharide residues from the non-reducing ends of both polymeric chondroitin/dermatan sulfates and their oligosaccharide fragments.
COMMENT     This enzyme degrades a variety of glycosaminoglycans of the chondroitin-sulfate- and dermatan-sulfate type. Chondroitin sulfate, chondroitin-sulfate proteoglycan and dermatan sulfate are the best substrates but the enzyme can also act on hyaluronan at a much lower rate. Keratan sulfate, heparan sulfate and heparin are not substrates. The related enzyme EC 4.2.2.20, chondroitin-sulfate-ABC endolyase, has the same substrate specificity but produces a mixture of oligosaccharides of different sizes that are ultimately degraded to tetra- and disaccharides [4]. Both enzymes act by the removal of a relatively acidic C-5 proton of the uronic acid followed by the elimination of a 4-linked hexosamine, resulting in the formation of an unsaturated C4---C5 bond on the hexuronic acid moiety of the products [4,6].
HISTORY     EC 4.2.2.21 created 2006 (EC 4.2.2.4 created 1972, part-incorporated 2006 (EC 4.2.99.6 created 1965, part incorporated 1976)), modified 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:5647268]
  AUTHORS   Yamagata T, Saito H, Habuchi O, Suzuki S.
  TITLE     Purification and properties of bacterial chondroitinases and chondrosulfatases.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 243 (1968) 1523-35.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:4231029]
  AUTHORS   Saito H, Yamagata T, Suzuki S.
  TITLE     Enzymatic methods for the determination of small quantities of isomeric chondroitin sulfates.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 243 (1968) 1536-42.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:5647269]
  AUTHORS   Suzuki S, Saito H, Yamagata T, Anno K, Seno N, Kawai Y, Furuhashi T.
  TITLE     Formation of three types of disulfated disaccharides from chondroitin sulfates by chondroitinase digestion.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 243 (1968) 1543-50.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9083041]
  AUTHORS   Hamai A, Hashimoto N, Mochizuki H, Kato F, Makiguchi Y, Horie K, Suzuki S.
  TITLE     Two distinct chondroitin sulfate ABC lyases. An endoeliminase yielding tetrasaccharides and an exoeliminase preferentially acting on oligosaccharides.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 272 (1997) 9123-30.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris
  SEQUENCE  [up:C7S340]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:16336265]
  AUTHORS   Huckerby TN, Nieduszynski IA, Giannopoulos M, Weeks SD, Sadler IH, Lauder RM.
  TITLE     Characterization of oligosaccharides from the chondroitin/dermatan sulfates. 1H-NMR and 13C-NMR studies of reduced trisaccharides and hexasaccharides.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. J. 272 (2005) 6276-86.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:18992215]
  AUTHORS   Zhang Z, Park Y, Kemp MM, Zhao W, Im AR, Shaya D, Cygler M, Kim YS, Linhardt RJ
  TITLE     Liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry to study chondroitin lyase action pattern.
  JOURNAL   Anal. Biochem. 385 (2009) 57-64.
ORTHOLOGY   K08961  chondroitin-sulfate-ABC endolyase/exolyase
GENES       SES: SARI_02380
            YPE: YPO0824
            YPK: y3211
            YPA: YPA_0445
            YPN: YPN_3027
            YPM: YP_2832
            YPP: YPDSF_0688
            YPG: YpAngola_A3277
            YPZ: YPZ3_0887
            YPT: A1122_00920
            YPD: YPD4_0844
            YPX: YPD8_0842
            YPH: YPC_0996
            YPS: YPTB3073
            YPI: YpsIP31758_0946
            YPY: YPK_0997
            YPB: YPTS_3194
            PMR: PMI2127
            EIC: NT01EI_3294
            ETR: ETAE_2917
            ETD: ETAF_2650
            SRO: Sros_2256
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.2.21
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.2.21
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.2.21
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.2.21
            CAS: 1000607-06-6
///
