ENTRY       EC 4.2.3.7                  Enzyme
NAME        pentalenene synthase;
            pentalenene synthetase
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on phosphates
SYSNAME     (2E,6E)-farnesyl-diphosphate diphosphate-lyase (cyclizing, pentalenene-forming)
REACTION    (2E,6E)-farnesyl diphosphate = pentalenene + diphosphate [RN:R02305]
ALL_REAC    R02305
SUBSTRATE   (2E,6E)-farnesyl diphosphate [CPD:C00448]
PRODUCT     pentalenene [CPD:C01841];
            diphosphate [CPD:C00013]
COMMENT     Isolated from Streptomyces avermitilis. The enzyme is involved in the biosynthesis of pentalenolactone and related antibiotics. The 9si hydrogen of farnesyl diphosphate undergoes a 1,2-hydride shift where it becomes the 1alpha hydrogen of pentalenene.
HISTORY     EC 4.2.3.7 created 1989 as EC 4.6.1.5, transferred 2000 to EC 4.2.3.7
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:6642060]
  AUTHORS   Cane DE.
  TITLE     Cell-free studies of monoterpene and sesquiterpene biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Soc. Trans. 11 (1983) 510-5.
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Cane, D.E. and Tillman, A.M.
  TITLE     Pentalenene biosynthesis and the enzymic cyclization of farnesyl pyrophosphate.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 105 (1983) 122-124.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8180213]
  AUTHORS   Cane DE, Sohng JK, Lamberson CR, Rudnicki SM, Wu Z, Lloyd MD, Oliver JS, Hubbard BR.
  TITLE     Pentalenene synthase. Purification, molecular cloning, sequencing, and high-level expression in Escherichia coli of a terpenoid cyclase from Streptomyces UC5319.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 33 (1994) 5846-57.
  ORGANISM  Streptomyces sp.
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q55012]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:1678531]
  AUTHORS   Cane DE, Abell C, Harrison PH, Hubbard BR, Kane CT, Lattman R, Oliver JS, Weiner SW
  TITLE     Terpenoid biosynthesis and the stereochemistry of enzyme-catalysed allylic addition-elimination reactions.
  JOURNAL   Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B. Biol. Sci. 332 (1991) 123-9.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:9295272]
  AUTHORS   Lesburg CA, Zhai G, Cane DE, Christianson DW
  TITLE     Crystal structure of pentalenene synthase: mechanistic insights on terpenoid cyclization reactions in biology.
  JOURNAL   Science. 277 (1997) 1820-4.
  ORGANISM  streptomyces sp.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:22738258]
  AUTHORS   Zu L, Xu M, Lodewyk MW, Cane DE, Peters RJ, Tantillo DJ
  TITLE     Effect of isotopically sensitive branching on product distribution for pentalenene synthase: support for a mechanism predicted by quantum chemistry.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 134 (2012) 11369-71.
PATHWAY     ec00909  Sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis
ORTHOLOGY   K12250  pentalenene synthase
GENES       SMA: SAV_2998(ptlA)
            SBH: SBI_09679
            SCI: B446_29695
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.7
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.3.7
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.3.7
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.7
            CAS: 90597-46-9
///
