ENTRY       EC 4.2.3.119                Enzyme
NAME        (-)-alpha-pinene synthase;
            (-)-alpha-pinene/(-)-camphene synthase;
            (-)-alpha-pinene cyclase
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on phosphates
SYSNAME     geranyl-diphosphate diphosphate-lyase [cyclizing, (-)-alpha-pinene-forming]
REACTION    geranyl diphosphate = (-)-alpha-pinene + diphosphate [RN:R05765]
ALL_REAC    R05765
SUBSTRATE   geranyl diphosphate [CPD:C00341]
PRODUCT     (-)-alpha-pinene [CPD:C06308];
            diphosphate [CPD:C00013]
COMMENT     Cyclase II of Salvia officinalis (sage) gives about equal parts (-)-alpha-pinene, (-)-beta-pinene and (-)-camphene, plus traces of other monoterpenoids. (3S)-Linalyl diphosphate can also be used by the enzyme in preference to (3R)-linalyl diphosphate. The 4-pro-S-hydrogen of geranyl diphosphate is lost. Requires Mg2+ (preferred to Mn2+) [1-6]. The enzyme from Abies grandis (grand fir) gives roughly equal parts (-)-alpha-pinene and (-)-beta-pinene. However the clone ag11 gave 35% (-)-limonene, 24% (-)-alpha-pinene and 20% (-)-beta-phellandrene. It requires Mn2+ and K+ (Mg2+ is ineffective) [7-10]. Synthase I from Pinus taeda (loblolly pine) produces (-)-alpha-pinene with traces of (-)-beta-pinene and requires Mn2+ (preferred to Mg2+) [11,12]. The enzyme from Picea sitchensis (Sika spruce) forms 70% (-)-alpha-pinene and 30% (-)-beta-pinene [13]. The recombinant PmeTPS1 enzyme from Pseudotsuga menziesii (Douglas fir) gave roughly equal proportions of (-)-alpha-pinene and (-)-camphene plus traces of other monoterpenoids [14]. See also EC 4.2.3.120, (-)-beta-pinene synthase; EC 4.2.3.117, (-)-camphene synthase; EC 4.2.3.16, (-)-limonene synthase; and EC 4.2.3.52, (-)-beta-phellandrene synthase.
HISTORY     EC 4.2.3.119 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:6693393]
  AUTHORS   Gambliel H, Croteau R
  TITLE     Pinene cyclases I and II. Two enzymes from sage (Salvia officinalis) which catalyze stereospecific cyclizations of geranyl pyrophosphate to monoterpene olefins of opposite configuration.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 259 (1984) 740-8.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:3314988]
  AUTHORS   Croteau RB, Wheeler CJ, Cane DE, Ebert R, Ha HJ
  TITLE     Isotopically sensitive branching in the formation of cyclic monoterpenes: proof that (-)-alpha-pinene and (-)-beta-pinene are synthesized by the same monoterpene cyclase via deprotonation of a common intermediate.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 26 (1987) 5383-9.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:3392006]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Satterwhite DM, Cane DE, Chang CC
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of monoterpenes. Enantioselectivity in the enzymatic cyclization of  (+)- and (-)-linalyl pyrophosphate to (+)- and (-)-pinene and (+)- and (-)-camphene.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 263 (1988) 10063-71.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:2768265]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Satterwhite DM
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of monoterpenes. Stereochemical implications of acyclic and monocyclic olefin formation by (+)- and (-)-pinene cyclases from sage.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 264 (1989) 15309-15.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:8109979]
  AUTHORS   Pyun HJ, Wagschal KC, Jung DI, Coates RM, Croteau R
  TITLE     Stereochemistry of the proton elimination in the formation of (+)- and (-)-alpha-pinene by monoterpene cyclases from sage (Salvia officinalis).
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 308 (1994) 488-96.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:12226526]
  AUTHORS   Lu S, Xu R, Jia JW, Pang J, Matsuda SP, Chen XY
  TITLE     Cloning and functional characterization of a beta-pinene synthase from Artemisia  annua that shows a circadian pattern of expression.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 130 (2002) 477-86.
  ORGANISM  Artemisia annua
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q94G53]
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:1731633]
  AUTHORS   Lewinsohn E, Gijzen M, Croteau R
  TITLE     Wound-inducible pinene cyclase from grand fir: purification, characterization, and renaturation after SDS-PAGE.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 293 (1992) 167-73.
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:9268308]
  AUTHORS   Bohlmann J, Steele CL, Croteau R.
  TITLE     Monoterpene synthases from grand fir (Abies grandis). cDNA isolation, characterization, and functional expression of myrcene synthase, (-)-(4S)-limonene synthase, and (-)-(1S,5S)-pinene synthase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 272 (1997) 21784-92.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
  SEQUENCE  [up: O24475]
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:10441373]
  AUTHORS   Bohlmann J, Phillips M, Ramachandiran V, Katoh S, Croteau R
  TITLE     cDNA cloning, characterization, and functional expression of four new monoterpene synthase members of the Tpsd gene family from grand fir (Abies grandis).
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 368 (1999) 232-43.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9M7C9]
REFERENCE   10 [PMID:15978541]
  AUTHORS   Hyatt DC, Croteau R
  TITLE     Mutational analysis of a monoterpene synthase reaction: altered catalysis through directed mutagenesis of (-)-pinene synthase from Abies grandis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 439 (2005) 222-33.
REFERENCE   11 [PMID:10562434]
  AUTHORS   Phillips MA, Savage TJ, Croteau R
  TITLE     Monoterpene synthases of loblolly pine (Pinus taeda) produce pinene isomers and enantiomers.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 372 (1999) 197-204.
REFERENCE   12 [PMID:12623076]
  AUTHORS   Phillips MA, Wildung MR, Williams DC, Hyatt DC, Croteau R
  TITLE     cDNA isolation, functional expression, and characterization of (+)-alpha-pinene synthase and (-)-alpha-pinene synthase from loblolly pine (Pinus taeda): stereocontrol in pinene biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 411 (2003) 267-76.
  ORGANISM  Pinus taeda
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q84KL6]
REFERENCE   13 [PMID:12970502]
  AUTHORS   McKay SA, Hunter WL, Godard KA, Wang SX, Martin DM, Bohlmann J, Plant AL
  TITLE     Insect attack and wounding induce traumatic resin duct development and gene expression of (-)-pinene synthase in Sitka spruce.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 133 (2003) 368-78.
  ORGANISM  Picea sitchensis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q6XDB5]
REFERENCE   14 [PMID:15921711]
  AUTHORS   Huber DP, Philippe RN, Godard KA, Sturrock RN, Bohlmann J
  TITLE     Characterization of four terpene synthase cDNAs from methyl jasmonate-induced Douglas-fir, Pseudotsuga menziesii.
  JOURNAL   Phytochemistry. 66 (2005) 1427-39.
  ORGANISM  Pseudotsuga menziesii
PATHWAY     ec00902  Monoterpenoid biosynthesis
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K07384  pinene synthase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.119
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.3.119
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.3.119
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.119
///
