ENTRY       EC 4.2.3.9                  Enzyme
NAME        aristolochene synthase;
            sesquiterpene cyclase;
            trans,trans-farnesyl diphosphate aristolochene-lyase;
            trans,trans-farnesyl-diphosphate diphosphate-lyase (cyclizing, aristolochene-forming)
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on phosphates
SYSNAME     (2E,6E)-farnesyl-diphosphate diphosphate-lyase (cyclizing, aristolochene-forming)
REACTION    (2E,6E)-farnesyl diphosphate = aristolochene + diphosphate [RN:R02307]
ALL_REAC    R02307
SUBSTRATE   (2E,6E)-farnesyl diphosphate [CPD:C00448]
PRODUCT     aristolochene [CPD:C02004];
            diphosphate [CPD:C00013]
COMMENT     The initial internal cyclization produces the monocyclic intermediate germacrene A; further cyclization and methyl transfer converts the intermediate into aristolochene. While in some species germacrene A remains as an enzyme-bound intermediate, it has been shown to be a minor product of the reaction in Penicillium roqueforti [5] (see also EC 4.2.3.23, germacrene-A synthase). The enzyme from Penicillium roqueforti requires Mg2+. Mn2+ can partially substitute, at low concentrations. Aristolochene is the likely parent compound for a number of sesquiterpenes produced by filamentous fungi.
HISTORY     EC 4.2.3.9 created 1992 as EC 2.5.1.40, transferred 1999 to EC 4.1.99.7, transferred 2000 to EC 4.2.3.9, modified 2006
REFERENCE   1
  AUTHORS   Cane, D.E., Prabhakaran, P.C., Oliver, J.S. and McIlwaine, D.B.
  TITLE     Aristolochene biosynthesis. Stereochemistry of the deprotonation steps in the enzymatic cyclization of farnesyl pyrophosphate.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 112 (1990) 3209-3210.
REFERENCE   2
  AUTHORS   Cane, D.E., Prabhakaran, P.C., Salaski, E.J., Harrison, P.M.H., Noguchi, H. and Rawlings, B.J.
  TITLE     Aristolochene biosynthesis and enzymatic cyclization of farnesyl pyrophosphate.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 111 (1989) 8914-8916.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:2544140]
  AUTHORS   Hohn TM, Plattner RD.
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of the sesquiterpene cyclase aristolochene synthase from Penicillium roqueforti.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 272 (1989) 137-43.
  ORGANISM  Penicillium roqueforti
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:8440737]
  AUTHORS   Proctor RH, Hohn TM.
  TITLE     Aristolochene synthase. Isolation, characterization, and bacterial expression of a sesquiterpenoid biosynthetic gene (Ari1) from Penicillium roqueforti.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 268 (1993) 4543-8.
  ORGANISM  Penicillium roqueforti
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q03471]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:12296728]
  AUTHORS   Calvert MJ, Ashton PR, Allemann RK.
  TITLE     Germacrene A is a product of the aristolochene synthase-mediated conversion of farnesylpyrophosphate to aristolochene.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 124 (2002) 11636-41.
  ORGANISM  Penicillium roqueforti
PATHWAY     ec00909  Sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K14180  aristolochene synthase
GENES       PAN: PODANSg557
            ANI: AN3277.2
            AOR: AOR_1_182054(AO090011000103)
            ACT: ACLA_063920
            PCS: Pc12g06310
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.9
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.3.9
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.3.9
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.9
            CAS: 94185-89-4
///
