ENTRY       EC 4.2.3.27                 Enzyme
NAME        isoprene synthase;
            ISPC;
            ISPS
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on phosphates
SYSNAME     dimethylallyl-diphosphate diphosphate-lyase (isoprene-forming)
REACTION    dimethylallyl diphosphate = isoprene + diphosphate [RN:R08199]
ALL_REAC    R08199
SUBSTRATE   dimethylallyl diphosphate [CPD:C00235]
PRODUCT     isoprene [CPD:C16521];
            diphosphate [CPD:C00013]
COMMENT     Requires Mg2+ or Mn2+ for activity. This enzyme is located in the chloroplast of isoprene-emitting plants, such as poplar and aspen, and may be activitated by light-dependent changes in chloroplast pH and Mg2+ concentration [2,8].
HISTORY     EC 4.2.3.27 created 2007
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:16668590]
  AUTHORS   Silver GM, Fall R.
  TITLE     Enzymatic Synthesis of Isoprene from Dimethylallyl Diphosphate in Aspen Leaf Extracts.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 97 (1991) 1588-1591.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7768893]
  AUTHORS   Silver GM, Fall R.
  TITLE     Characterization of aspen isoprene synthase, an enzyme responsible for leaf isoprene emission to the atmosphere.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 270 (1995) 13010-6.
  ORGANISM  Populus tremuloides
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:12226383]
  AUTHORS   Wildermuth MC, Fall R.
  TITLE     Light-Dependent Isoprene Emission (Characterization of a Thylakoid-Bound Isoprene Synthase in Salix discolor Chloroplasts).
  JOURNAL   Plant. Physiol. 112 (1996) 171-182.
REFERENCE   4
  AUTHORS   Schnitzler, J.P., Arenz, R., Steinbrecher, R. and Lehming, A.
  TITLE     Characterization of an isoprene synthase from leaves of Quercus petraea.
  JOURNAL   Bot. Acta 109 (1996) 216-221.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:11506373]
  AUTHORS   Miller B, Oschinski C, Zimmer W.
  TITLE     First isolation of an isoprene synthase gene from poplar and successful expression of the gene in Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   Planta. 213 (2001) 483-7.
  ORGANISM  Populus tremuloides
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9AR86]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:12054742]
  AUTHORS   Sivy TL, Shirk MC, Fall R.
  TITLE     Isoprene synthase activity parallels fluctuations of isoprene release during growth of Bacillus subtilis.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 294 (2002) 71-5.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:15848197]
  AUTHORS   Sasaki K, Ohara K, Yazaki K.
  TITLE     Gene expression and characterization of isoprene synthase from Populus alba.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. Lett. 579 (2005) 2514-8.
  ORGANISM  Populus alba
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q50L36]
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:16052321]
  AUTHORS   Schnitzler JP, Zimmer I, Bachl A, Arend M, Fromm J, Fischbach RJ.
  TITLE     Biochemical properties of isoprene synthase in poplar (Populus x canescens).
  JOURNAL   Planta. 222 (2005) 777-86.
PATHWAY     ec00900  Terpenoid backbone biosynthesis
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K12742  isoprene synthase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.27
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.3.27
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.3.27
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.27
            CAS: 139172-14-8
///
