ENTRY       EC 4.2.3.132                Enzyme
NAME        neoabietadiene synthase;
            AgAS;
            PtTPS-LAS
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on phosphates
SYSNAME     (+)-copaly-diphosphate diphosphate-lyase (cyclizing, neoabietadiene-forming)
REACTION    (+)-copalyl diphosphate = neoabietadiene + diphosphate [RN:R06303]
ALL_REAC    R06303
SUBSTRATE   (+)-copalyl diphosphate [CPD:C11901]
PRODUCT     neoabietadiene [CPD:C11880];
            diphosphate [CPD:C00013]
COMMENT     Isolated from Abies grandis (grand fir) [1]. This class I enzyme forms about equal proportions of abietadiene, levopimaradiene and neoabietadiene. See also EC 4.2.3.18, abieta-7,13-diene synthase and EC 4.2.3.32, levopimaradiene synthase. An X-ray study of this multifunctional enzyme showed that the class I activity is in the alpha domain, while (+)-copalyl diphosphate synthase activity (EC 5.5.1.12, a class II activity) is in the beta and gamma domains [2]. In Pinus taeda (loblolly pine) the major product is levopimaradiene, with less abietadiene and neoabietadiene [3].
HISTORY     EC 4.2.3.132 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:11112547]
  AUTHORS   Peters RJ, Flory JE, Jetter R, Ravn MM, Lee HJ, Coates RM, Croteau RB.
  TITLE     Abietadiene synthase from grand fir (Abies grandis): characterization and mechanism of action of the &quot;pseudomature&quot; recombinant enzyme.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 39 (2000) 15592-602.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q38710]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:22219188]
  AUTHORS   Zhou K, Gao Y, Hoy JA, Mann FM, Honzatko RB, Peters RJ
  TITLE     Insights into diterpene cyclization from structure of bifunctional abietadiene synthase from Abies grandis.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 287 (2012) 6840-50.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q38710]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16497345]
  AUTHORS   Ro DK, Bohlmann J.
  TITLE     Diterpene resin acid biosynthesis in loblolly pine (Pinus taeda): functional characterization of abietadiene/levopimaradiene synthase (PtTPS-LAS) cDNA and subcellular targeting of PtTPS-LAS and abietadienol/abietadienal oxidase (PtAO, CYP720B1).
  JOURNAL   Phytochemistry. 67 (2006) 1572-8.
  ORGANISM  Pinus taeda
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q50EK2]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.132
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.3.132
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.3.132
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.132
///
