ENTRY       EC 4.2.3.107                Enzyme
NAME        (+)-car-3-ene synthase;
            3-carene cyclase;
            3-carene synthase;
            3CAR;
            (+)-3-carene synthase
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on phosphates
SYSNAME     geranyl-diphosphate diphosphate-lyase [cyclizing, (+)-car-3-ene-forming]
REACTION    geranyl diphosphate = (+)-car-3-ene + diphosphate [RN:R09963]
ALL_REAC    R09963
SUBSTRATE   geranyl diphosphate [CPD:C00341]
PRODUCT     (+)-car-3-ene [CPD:C11382];
            diphosphate [CPD:C00013]
COMMENT     The enzyme reacts with (3S)-linalyl diphosphate twice as rapidly as geranyl diphosphate, but 25 times as rapidly as (3R)-linalyl diphosphate. It is assumed that (3S)-linalyl diphosphate is normally formed as an enzyme bound intermediate in the reaction. In the reaction the 5-pro-R hydrogen of geranyl diphosphate is eliminated during cyclopropane ring formation [1,2]. In Picea abies (Norway spruce) and Picea sitchensis (Sitka spruce) terpinolene is also formed [4,6]. See EC 4.2.3.113 terpinolene synthase. (+)-Car-3-ene is associated with resistance of Picea sitchensis (Sitka spruce) to white pine weevil [6].
HISTORY     EC 4.2.3.107 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:8373196]
  AUTHORS   Savage TJ, Croteau R
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of monoterpenes: regio- and stereochemistry of (+)-3-carene biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 305 (1993) 581-7.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:7625832]
  AUTHORS   Savage TJ, Ichii H, Hume SD, Little DB, Croteau R
  TITLE     Monoterpene synthases from gymnosperms and angiosperms: stereospecificity and inactivation by cysteinyl- and arginyl-directed modifying reagents.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 320 (1995) 257-65.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:8307957]
  AUTHORS   Savage TJ, Hatch MW, Croteau R
  TITLE     Monoterpene synthases of Pinus contorta and related conifers. A new class of terpenoid cyclase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 269 (1994) 4012-20.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12602896]
  AUTHORS   Faldt J, Martin D, Miller B, Rawat S, Bohlmann J
  TITLE     Traumatic resin defense in Norway spruce (Picea abies): methyl jasmonate-induced  terpene synthase gene expression, and cDNA cloning and functional characterization of (+)-3-carene synthase.
  JOURNAL   Plant. Mol. Biol. 51 (2003) 119-33.
  ORGANISM  Picea abies
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q84SM8]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:19656416]
  AUTHORS   Hamberger B, Hall D, Yuen M, Oddy C, Hamberger B, Keeling CI, Ritland C, Ritland K, Bohlmann J
  TITLE     Targeted isolation, sequence assembly and characterization of two white spruce (Picea glauca) BAC clones for terpenoid synthase and cytochrome P450 genes involved in conifer defence reveal insights into a conifer genome.
  JOURNAL   BMC. Plant. Biol. 9 (2009) 106.
  ORGANISM  Picea glauca
  SEQUENCE  [up:C7ASI9]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:21323772]
  AUTHORS   Hall DE, Robert JA, Keeling CI, Domanski D, Quesada AL, Jancsik S, Kuzyk MA, Hamberger B, Borchers CH, Bohlmann J
  TITLE     An integrated genomic, proteomic and biochemical analysis of (+)-3-carene biosynthesis in Sitka spruce (Picea sitchensis) genotypes that are resistant or susceptible to white pine weevil.
  JOURNAL   Plant. J. 65 (2011) 936-48.
  ORGANISM  Picea sitchensis
  SEQUENCE  [up:F1CKI6 F1CKI8 F1CKI9]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.107
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.3.107
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.3.107
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.3.107
///
