ENTRY       EC 4.2.2.20                 Enzyme
NAME        chondroitin-sulfate-ABC endolyase;
            chondroitinase (ambiguous);
            chondroitin ABC eliminase (ambiguous);
            chondroitinase ABC (ambiguous);
            chondroitin ABC lyase (ambiguous);
            chondroitin sulfate ABC lyase (ambiguous);
            ChS ABC lyase (ambiguous);
            chondroitin sulfate ABC endoeliminase;
            chondroitin sulfate ABC endolyase;
            ChS ABC lyase I
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Acting on polysaccharides
SYSNAME     chondroitin-sulfate-ABC endolyase
REACTION    Endolytic cleavage of (1->4)-beta-galactosaminic bonds between N-acetylgalactosamine and either D-glucuronic acid or L-iduronic acid to produce a mixture of Delta4-unsaturated oligosaccharides of different sizes that are ultimately degraded to Delta4-unsaturated tetra- and disaccharides
COMMENT     This enzyme degrades a variety of glycosaminoglycans of the chondroitin-sulfate- and dermatan-sulfate type. Chondroitin sulfate, chondroitin-sulfate proteoglycan and dermatan sulfate are the best substrates but the enzyme can also act on hyaluronan at a much lower rate. Keratan sulfate, heparan sulfate and heparin are not substrates. In general, chondroitin sulfate (CS) and dermatan sulfate (DS) chains comprise a linkage region, a chain cap and a repeat region. The repeat region of CS is a repeating disaccharide of glucuronic acid (GlcA) and N-acetylgalactosamine (GalNAc) [-4)GlcA(beta1-3)GalNAc(beta1-]n, which may be O-sulfated on the C-4 and/or C-6 of GalNAc and C-2 of GlcA. GlcA residues of CS may be epimerized to iduronic acid (IdoA) forming the repeating disaccharide [-4)IdoA(alpha1-3)GalNAc(beta1-]n of DS. Both the concentrations and locations of sulfate-ester substituents vary with glucosaminoglycan source [5]. The related enzyme EC 4.2.2.21, chondroitin-sulfate-ABC exolyase, has the same substrate specificity but removes disaccharide residues from the non-reducing ends of both polymeric chondroitin sulfates and their oligosaccharide fragments produced by EC 4.2.2.20 [4].
HISTORY     EC 4.2.2.20 created 2006 (EC 4.2.2.4 created 1972, part-incorporated 2006 (EC 4.2.99.6 created 1965, part incorporated 1976))
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:5647268]
  AUTHORS   Yamagata T, Saito H, Habuchi O, Suzuki S.
  TITLE     Purification and properties of bacterial chondroitinases and chondrosulfatases.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 243 (1968) 1523-35.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris, Flavobacterium heparinum
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:4231029]
  AUTHORS   Saito H, Yamagata T, Suzuki S.
  TITLE     Enzymatic methods for the determination of small quantities of isomeric chondroitin sulfates.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 243 (1968) 1536-42.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris, Flavobacterium heparinum
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:5647269]
  AUTHORS   Suzuki S, Saito H, Yamagata T, Anno K, Seno N, Kawai Y, Furuhashi T.
  TITLE     Formation of three types of disulfated disaccharides from chondroitin sulfates by chondroitinase digestion.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 243 (1968) 1543-50.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris, Flavobacterium heparinum
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:9083041]
  AUTHORS   Hamai A, Hashimoto N, Mochizuki H, Kato F, Makiguchi Y, Horie K, Suzuki S.
  TITLE     Two distinct chondroitin sulfate ABC lyases. An endoeliminase yielding tetrasaccharides and an exoeliminase preferentially acting on oligosaccharides.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 272 (1997) 9123-30.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris
  SEQUENCE  [up:P59807]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:16336265]
  AUTHORS   Huckerby TN, Nieduszynski IA, Giannopoulos M, Weeks SD, Sadler IH, Lauder RM.
  TITLE     Characterization of oligosaccharides from the chondroitin/dermatan sulfates. 1H-NMR and 13C-NMR studies of reduced trisaccharides and hexasaccharides.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. J. 272 (2005) 6276-86.
  ORGANISM  Proteus vulgaris
ORTHOLOGY   K08961  chondroitin-sulfate-ABC endolyase/exolyase
GENES       SES: SARI_02380
            YPE: YPO0824
            YPK: y3211
            YPA: YPA_0445
            YPN: YPN_3027
            YPM: YP_2832
            YPP: YPDSF_0688
            YPG: YpAngola_A3277
            YPZ: YPZ3_0887
            YPT: A1122_00920
            YPD: YPD4_0844
            YPX: YPD8_0842
            YPH: YPC_0996
            YPS: YPTB3073
            YPI: YpsIP31758_0946
            YPY: YPK_0997
            YPB: YPTS_3194
            PMR: PMI2127
            EIC: NT01EI_3294
            ETR: ETAE_2917
            ETD: ETAF_2650
            SRO: Sros_2256
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.2.20
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.2.20
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.2.20
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.2.20
            CAS: 9024-13-9
///
