ENTRY       EC 4.2.1.110                Enzyme
NAME        aldos-2-ulose dehydratase;
            pyranosone dehydratase;
            AUDH;
            1,5-anhydro-D-fructose dehydratase (microthecin-forming)
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Hydro-lyases
SYSNAME     1,5-anhydro-D-fructose hydro-lyase (microthecin-forming)
REACTION    1,5-anhydro-D-fructose = 2-hydroxy-2-(hydroxymethyl)-2H-pyran-3(6H)-on + H2O (overall reaction) [RN:R09696];
            (1a) 1,5-anhydro-D-fructose = 1,5-anhydro-4-deoxy-D-glycero-hex-3-en-2-ulose + H2O [RN:R09694];
            (1b) 1,5-anhydro-4-deoxy-D-glycero-hex-3-en-2-ulose = 2-hydroxy-2-(hydroxymethyl)-2H-pyran-3(6H)-one [RN:R09695]
ALL_REAC    R09694 R09695 R09696
SUBSTRATE   1,5-anhydro-D-fructose [CPD:C06485];
            1,5-anhydro-4-deoxy-D-glycero-hex-3-en-2-ulose [CPD:C19822]
PRODUCT     2-hydroxy-2-(hydroxymethyl)-2H-pyran-3(6H)-on;
            H2O [CPD:C00001];
            1,5-anhydro-4-deoxy-D-glycero-hex-3-en-2-ulose [CPD:C19822];
            2-hydroxy-2-(hydroxymethyl)-2H-pyran-3(6H)-one [CPD:C19821]
COMMENT     This enzyme catalyses two of the steps in the anhydrofructose pathway, which leads to the degradation of glycogen and starch via 1,5-anhydro-D-fructose [1,2]. Aldose-2-uloses such as 2-dehydroglucose can also act as substrates, but more slowly [1,2,4]. This is a bifunctional enzyme that acts as both a lyase and as an isomerase [2]. Differs from EC 4.2.1.111, which can carry out only reaction (1a), is inhibited by its product and requires metal ions for activity [1].
HISTORY     EC 4.2.1.110 created 2006
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:16822618]
  AUTHORS   Yu S, Fiskesund R.
  TITLE     The anhydrofructose pathway and its possible role in stress response and signaling.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1760 (2006) 1314-22.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:15716041]
  AUTHORS   Yu S.
  TITLE     Enzymatic description of the anhydrofructose pathway of glycogen degradation II. Gene identification and characterization of the reactions catalyzed by aldos-2-ulose dehydratase that converts 1,5-anhydro-D-fructose to microthecin with ascopyrone M as the intermediate.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1723 (2005) 63-73.
  ORGANISM  Phanerochaete chrysosporium
  SEQUENCE  [up:P84193]
REFERENCE   3
  AUTHORS   Broberg, A., Kenne, L. and Pedersen, M.
  TITLE     Presence of microthecin in the red alga Gracilariopsis lemaneiformis and its formation from 1,5-anhydro-D-fructose.
  JOURNAL   Phytochemistry 41 (1996) 151-154.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:8352649]
  AUTHORS   Gabriel J, Volc J, Sedmera P, Daniel G, Kubatova E.
  TITLE     Pyranosone dehydratase from the basidiomycete Phanerochaete chrysosporium: improved purification, and identification of 6-deoxy-D-glucosone and D-xylosone reaction products.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Microbiol. 160 (1993) 27-34.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15110094]
  AUTHORS   Yu S, Refdahl C, Lundt I.
  TITLE     Enzymatic description of the anhydrofructose pathway of glycogen degradation; I. Identification and purification of anhydrofructose dehydratase, ascopyrone tautomerase and alpha-1,4-glucan lyase in the fungus Anthracobia melaloma.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1672 (2004) 120-9.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.1.110
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.1.110
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.1.110
            UM-BBD (Biocatalysis/Biodegradation Database): 4.2.1.110
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.1.110
            CAS: 101920-80-3
///
