ENTRY       EC 4.2.1.119                Enzyme
NAME        enoyl-CoA hydratase 2;
            2-enoyl-CoA hydratase 2;
            AtECH2;
            ECH2;
            MaoC;
            MFE-2;
            PhaJAc;
            D-3-hydroxyacyl-CoA hydro-lyase;
            D-specific 2-trans-enoyl-CoA hydratase
CLASS       Lyases;
            Carbon-oxygen lyases;
            Hydro-lyases
SYSNAME     (3R)-3-hydroxyacyl-CoA hydro-lyase
REACTION    (3R)-3-hydroxyacyl-CoA = (2E)-2-enoyl-CoA + H2O [RN:R09698]
ALL_REAC    R09698
SUBSTRATE   (3R)-3-hydroxyacyl-CoA [CPD:C01086]
PRODUCT     (2E)-2-enoyl-CoA [CPD:C00658];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     This enzyme catalyses a hydration step in peroxisomal beta-oxidation. The human multifunctional enzyme type 2 (MFE-2) is a 79000 Da enzyme composed of three functional units: (3R)-hydroxyacyl-CoA dehydrogenase, 2-enoyl-CoA hydratase 2 and sterol carrier protein 2-like units [1]. The enzymes from Aeromonas caviae [4] and Arabidopsis thaliana [5] are monofunctional enzymes. 2-Enoyl-CoA hydratase 3 from Candida tropicalis is a part from multifunctional enzyme type 2 [3].
HISTORY     EC 4.2.1.119 created 2009
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:15644212]
  AUTHORS   Koski KM, Haapalainen AM, Hiltunen JK, Glumoff T
  TITLE     Crystal structure of 2-enoyl-CoA hydratase 2 from human peroxisomal multifunctional enzyme type 2.
  JOURNAL   J. Mol. Biol. 345 (2005) 1157-69.
  ORGANISM  Homo sapiens
  SEQUENCE  [hsa:3295]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9457873]
  AUTHORS   Fukui T, Shiomi N, Doi Y
  TITLE     Expression and characterization of (R)-specific enoyl coenzyme A hydratase involved in polyhydroxyalkanoate biosynthesis by Aeromonas caviae.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 180 (1998) 667-73.
  ORGANISM  Aeromonas caviae
  SEQUENCE  [up:O32472]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:12832794]
  AUTHORS   Koski MK, Haapalainen AM, Hiltunen JK, Glumoff T
  TITLE     Crystallization and preliminary crystallographic data of 2-enoyl-CoA hydratase 2  domain of Candida tropicalis peroxisomal multifunctional enzyme type 2.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 59 (2003) 1302-5.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:11134939]
  AUTHORS   Hisano T, Fukui T, Iwata T, Doi Y
  TITLE     Crystallization and preliminary X-ray analysis of (R)-specific enoyl-CoA hydratase from Aeromonas caviae involved in polyhydroxyalkanoate biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 57 (2001) 145-7.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:16982622]
  AUTHORS   Goepfert S, Hiltunen JK, Poirier Y
  TITLE     Identification and functional characterization of a monofunctional peroxisomal enoyl-CoA hydratase 2 that participates in the degradation of even cis-unsaturated fatty acids in Arabidopsis thaliana.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 281 (2006) 35894-903.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana
  SEQUENCE  [ath:AT1G76150]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:1879422]
  AUTHORS   Engeland K, Kindl H
  TITLE     Evidence for a peroxisomal fatty acid beta-oxidation involving D-3-hydroxyacyl-CoAs. Characterization of two forms of hydro-lyase that convert D-(-)-3-hydroxyacyl-CoA into 2-trans-enoyl-CoA.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 200 (1991) 171-8.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.2.1.119
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.2.1.119
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.2.1.119
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.2.1.119
///
