ENTRY       EC 4.6.1.15                 Enzyme
NAME        FAD-AMP lyase (cyclizing);
            FMN cyclase;
            FAD AMP-lyase (cyclic-FMN-forming)
CLASS       Lyases;
            Phosphorus-oxygen lyases;
            Phosphorus-oxygen lyases (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     FAD AMP-lyase (riboflavin-cyclic-4',5'-phosphate-forming)
REACTION    FAD = AMP + riboflavin cyclic-4',5'-phosphate [RN:R07636]
ALL_REAC    R07636
SUBSTRATE   FAD [CPD:C00016]
PRODUCT     AMP [CPD:C00020];
            riboflavin cyclic-4',5'-phosphate [CPD:C16071]
COMMENT     Requires Mn2+ or Co2+. While FAD was the best substrate tested [2], the enzyme also splits ribonucleoside diphosphate-X compounds in which X is an acyclic or cyclic monosaccharide or derivative bearing an X-OH group that is able to attack internally the proximal phosphorus with the geometry necessary to form a P=X product; either a five-atom monocyclic phosphodiester or a cis-bicyclic phosphodiester-pyranose fusion. The reaction is strongly inhibited by ADP or ATP but is unaffected by the presence of the product, cFMN.
HISTORY     EC 4.6.1.15 created 2002
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9480905]
  AUTHORS   Fraiz FJ, Pinto RM, Costas MJ, Aavalos M, Canales J, Cabezas A, Cameselle JC.
  TITLE     Enzymic formation of riboflavin 4',5'-cyclic phosphate from FAD: evidence for a specific low-Km FMN cyclase in rat liver1.
  JOURNAL   Biochem. J. 330 ( Pt 2) (1998) 881-8.
  ORGANISM  Rattus norvegicus
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:11695920]
  AUTHORS   Cabezas A, Pinto RM, Fraiz F, Canales J, Gonzalez-Santiago S, Cameselle JC.
  TITLE     Purification, characterization, and substrate and inhibitor structure-activity studies of rat liver FAD-AMP lyase (cyclizing): preference for FAD and specificity for splitting ribonucleoside diphosphate-X into ribonucleotide and a five-atom cyclic phosphodiester of X, either a monocyclic compound or a cis-bicyclic phosphodiester-pyranose fusion.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 40 (2001) 13710-22.
  ORGANISM  Rattus norvegicus
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q4KLZ6]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.6.1.15
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.6.1.15
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.6.1.15
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.6.1.15
            CAS: 208349-48-8
///
