ENTRY       EC 4.6.1.14                 Enzyme
NAME        glycosylphosphatidylinositol diacylglycerol-lyase;
            (glycosyl)phosphatidylinositol-specific phospholipase C;
            GPI-PLC;
            GPI-specific phospholipase C;
            VSG-lipase;
            glycosyl inositol phospholipid anchor-hydrolyzing enzyme;
            glycosylphosphatidylinositol-phospholipase C;
            glycosylphosphatidylinositol-specific phospholipase C;
            variant-surface-glycoprotein phospholipase C;
            6-(alpha-D-glucosaminyl)-1-phosphatidyl-1D-myo-inositol diacylglycerol-lyase (1,2-cyclic-phosphate-forming)
CLASS       Lyases;
            Phosphorus-oxygen lyases;
            Phosphorus-oxygen lyases (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     6-(alpha-D-glucosaminyl)-1-phosphatidyl-1D-myo-inositol 1,2-diacyl-sn-glycerol-lyase [6-(alpha-D-glucosaminyl)-1D-myo-inositol 1,2-cyclic phosphate-forming]
REACTION    6-(alpha-D-glucosaminyl)-1-phosphatidyl-1D-myo-inositol = 6-(alpha-D-glucosaminyl)-1D-myo-inositol 1,2-cyclic phosphate + 1,2-diacyl-sn-glycerol [RN:R07635]
ALL_REAC    R07635;
            (other) R04459
SUBSTRATE   6-(alpha-D-glucosaminyl)-1-phosphatidyl-1D-myo-inositol [CPD:C04248]
PRODUCT     6-(alpha-D-glucosaminyl)-1D-myo-inositol 1,2-cyclic phosphate [CPD:C16070];
            1,2-diacyl-sn-glycerol [CPD:C00641]
COMMENT     This enzyme is also active when O-4 of the glucosamine is substituted by carrying the oligosaccharide that can link a protein to the structure. It therefore cleaves proteins from the lipid part of the glycosylphostphatidylinositol (GPI) anchors. In some cases, the long-chain acyl group at the sn-1 position of glycerol is replaced by an alkyl or alk-1-enyl group. In other cases, the diacylglycerol is replaced by ceramide (see Lip-1.4 and Lip-1.5 for definition). The only characterized enzyme with this specificity is from Trypanosoma brucei, where the acyl groups are myristoyl, but the function of the trypanosome enzyme is unknown. Substitution on O-2 of the inositol blocks action of this enzyme. It is not identical with EC 3.1.4.50, glycosylphosphatidylinositol phospholipase D.
HISTORY     EC 4.6.1.14 created 1989 as EC 3.1.4.47, transferred 2002 to EC 4.6.1.14
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:3759991]
  AUTHORS   Hereld D, Krakow JL, Bangs JD, Hart GW, Englund PT.
  TITLE     A phospholipase C from Trypanosoma brucei which selectively cleaves the glycolipid on the variant surface glycoprotein.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 261 (1986) 13813-9.
  ORGANISM  Trypanosoma brucei
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9476790]
  AUTHORS   Carnall N, Webb H, Carrington M.
  TITLE     Mutagenesis study of the glycosylphosphatidylinositol phospholipase C of Trypanosoma brucei.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Biochem. Parasitol. 90 (1997) 423-32.
  ORGANISM  Trypanosoma brucei
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10764777]
  AUTHORS   Armah DA, Mensa-Wilmot K.
  TITLE     Tetramerization of glycosylphosphatidylinositol-specific phospholipase C from Trypanosoma brucei.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 275 (2000) 19334-42.
  ORGANISM  Trypanosoma brucei
ORTHOLOGY   K06038  variant-surface-glycoprotein phospholipase C
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.6.1.14
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.6.1.14
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.6.1.14
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.6.1.14
            CAS: 129070-68-4
///
