ENTRY       EC 4.99.1.5                 Enzyme
NAME        aliphatic aldoxime dehydratase;
            OxdA;
            aliphatic aldoxime hydro-lyase
CLASS       Lyases;
            Other lyases;
            Sole sub-subclass for lyases that do not belong in the other subclasses
SYSNAME     aliphatic aldoxime hydro-lyase (aliphatic-nitrile-forming)
REACTION    an aliphatic aldoxime = an aliphatic nitrile + H2O [RN:R02827]
ALL_REAC    R02827
SUBSTRATE   aliphatic aldoxime [CPD:C02658]
PRODUCT     aliphatic nitrile [CPD:C16072];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     The enzyme from Pseudomonas chlororaphis contains Ca2+ and protoheme IX, the iron of which must be in the form Fe(II) for activity. The enzyme exhibits a strong preference for aliphatic aldoximes, such as butyraldoxime and acetaldoxime, over aromatic aldoximes, such as pyridine-2-aldoxime, which is a poor substrate. No activity was found with the aromatic aldoximes benzaldoxime and pyridine-4-aldoxime.
HISTORY     EC 4.99.1.5 created 2004
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:12773527]
  AUTHORS   Oinuma K, Hashimoto Y, Konishi K, Goda M, Noguchi T, Higashibata H, Kobayashi M.
  TITLE     Novel aldoxime dehydratase involved in carbon-nitrogen triple bond synthesis of Pseudomonas chlororaphis B23. Sequencing, gene expression, purification, and characterization.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 278 (2003) 29600-8.
  ORGANISM  Pseudomonas chlororaphis
  SEQUENCE  [ncbi-gi:33456984]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:14556637]
  AUTHORS   Xie SX, Kato Y, Komeda H, Yoshida S, Asano Y.
  TITLE     A gene cluster responsible for alkylaldoxime metabolism coexisting with nitrile hydratase and amidase in Rhodococcus globerulus A-4.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 42 (2003) 12056-66.
  ORGANISM  Rhodococcus globerulus
  SEQUENCE  [ncbi-gi:37718700]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:16233624]
  AUTHORS   Kato Y, Yoshida S, Xie SX, Asano Y.
  TITLE     Aldoxime dehydratase co-existing with nitrile hydratase and amidase in the iron-type nitrile hydratase-producer Rhodococcus sp. N-771.
  JOURNAL   J. Biosci. Bioeng. 97 (2004) 250-9.
  ORGANISM  Rhodococcus sp.
PATHWAY     ec01100  Metabolic pathways
ORTHOLOGY   K13028  aldoxime dehydratase
GENES       EBI: EbC_pEb17201260
            PVA: Pvag_pPag20172(oxd)
            PAO: Pat9b_4157
            PPF: Pput_2724
            PSB: Psyr_0006
            PFS: PFLU3206
            ACI: ACIAD1620
            SWD: Swoo_0211
            BCN: Bcen_4080
            BCH: Bcen2424_4286
            BCM: Bcenmc03_3231
            BAM: Bamb_6546
            BAC: BamMC406_6260
            BGD: bgla_2g08590
            AAA: Acav_2428
            VAP: Vapar_2540
            VPE: Varpa_3386
            HSE: Hsero_0929(oxdA)
            BBT: BBta_4765
            XAU: Xaut_1560
            SWI: Swit_0988
            RHA: RHA1_ro00358
            RER: RER_59190
            AAU: AAur_1899(oxdA)
            AMI: Amir_0081
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.99.1.5
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.99.1.5
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.99.1.5
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.99.1.5
///
