ENTRY       EC 4.99.1.7                 Enzyme
NAME        phenylacetaldoxime dehydratase;
            PAOx dehydratase;
            arylacetaldoxime dehydratase;
            OxdB;
            (Z)-phenylacetaldehyde-oxime hydro-lyase
CLASS       Lyases;
            Other lyases;
            Sole sub-subclass for lyases that do not belong in the other subclasses
SYSNAME     (Z)-phenylacetaldehyde-oxime hydro-lyase (phenylacetonitrile-forming)
REACTION    (Z)-phenylacetaldehyde oxime = phenylacetonitrile + H2O [RN:R07638]
ALL_REAC    R07638
SUBSTRATE   (Z)-phenylacetaldehyde oxime [CPD:C16075]
PRODUCT     phenylacetonitrile [CPD:C16074];
            H2O [CPD:C00001]
COMMENT     The enzyme from Bacillus sp. OxB-1 contains protoheme IX, the iron of which must be in the form iron(II) for activity. (Z)-Phenylacetaldoxime binds to ferric heme (the iron(III) form) via the oxygen atom whereas it binds to the active ferrous form via the nitrogen atom. In this way, the oxidation state of the heme controls the coordination stucture of the substrate---heme complex, which regulates enzyme activity [2]. The enzyme is active towards several (Z)-arylacetaldoximes and (E/Z)-alkylaldoximes as well as towards arylalkylaldoximes such as 3-phenylpropionaldoxime and 4-phenylbutyraldoxime. However, it is inactive with phenylacetaldoximes that have a substituent group at an alpha-site of an oxime group, for example, with (E/Z)-2-phenylpropionaldoxime and (E/Z)-mandelaldoxime. The activity of the enzyme is inhibited completely by the heavy-metal cations Cu+, Cu2+, Ag+ and Hg+ whereas Fe2+ and Sn2+ have an activatory effect.
HISTORY     EC 4.99.1.7 created 2005
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:10651646]
  AUTHORS   Kato Y, Nakamura K, Sakiyama H, Mayhew SG, Asano Y.
  TITLE     Novel heme-containing lyase, phenylacetaldoxime dehydratase from Bacillus sp. strain OxB-1: purification, characterization, and molecular cloning of the gene.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 39 (2000) 800-9.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus sp.
  SEQUENCE  [up:P82604]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:15596434]
  AUTHORS   Kobayashi K, Yoshioka S, Kato Y, Asano Y, Aono S.
  TITLE     Regulation of aldoxime dehydratase activity by redox-dependent change in the coordination structure of the aldoxime-heme complex.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 280 (2005) 5486-90.
  ORGANISM  Bacillus sp.
PATHWAY     ec00460  Cyanoamino acid metabolism
            ec00643  Styrene degradation
            ec01120  Microbial metabolism in diverse environments
ORTHOLOGY   K10566  phenylacetaldoxime dehydratase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 4.99.1.7
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 4.99.1.7
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 4.99.1.7
            UM-BBD (Biocatalysis/Biodegradation Database): 4.99.1.7
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 4.99.1.7
            CAS: 203210-76-8
///
