ENTRY       EC 5.1.99.5                 Enzyme
NAME        hydantoin racemase;
            5'-monosubstituted-hydantoin racemase;
            HyuA;
            HyuE
CLASS       Isomerases;
            Racemases and epimerases;
            Acting on other compounds
SYSNAME     D-5-monosubstituted-hydantoin racemase
REACTION    D-5-monosubstituted hydantoin = L-5-monosubstituted hydantoin [RN:R09704]
ALL_REAC    R09704
SUBSTRATE   D-5-monosubstituted hydantoin [CPD:C19824]
PRODUCT     L-5-monosubstituted hydantoin [CPD:C19825]
COMMENT     This enzyme, along with N-carbamoylase (EC 3.5.1.77 and EC 3.5.1.87) and hydantoinase, forms part of the reaction cascade known as the "hydantoinase process", which allows the total conversion of D,L-5-monosubstituted hydantoins into optically pure D- or L-amino acids [7]. The enzyme from Pseudomonas sp. (HyuE) has a preference for hydantoins with aliphatic substituents, e.g. D- and L-5-(2-methylthioethyl)hydantoin, whereas that from Arthrobacter aurescens shows highest activity with arylalkyl substituents, especially 5-benzylhydantoin, at the 5-position [2]. In the enzyme from Sinorhizobium meliloti, Cys76 is responsible for recognition and proton retrieval of D-isomers, while Cys181 is responsible for L-isomer recognition and racemization [6].
HISTORY     EC 5.1.99.5 created 2008
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1459947]
  AUTHORS   Watabe K, Ishikawa T, Mukohara Y, Nakamura H
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of the hydantoin racemase of Pseudomonas sp. strain NS671 expressed in Escherichia coli.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 174 (1992) 7989-95.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:10949312]
  AUTHORS   Wiese A, Pietzsch M, Syldatk C, Mattes R, Altenbuchner J
  TITLE     Hydantoin racemase from Arthrobacter aurescens DSM 3747: heterologous expression, purification and characterization.
  JOURNAL   J. Biotechnol. 80 (2000) 217-30.
  ORGANISM  Arthrobacter aurescens
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:14711700]
  AUTHORS   Martinez-Rodriguez S, Las Heras-Vazquez FJ, Mingorance-Cazorla L, Clemente-Jimenez JM, Rodriguez-Vico F
  TITLE     Molecular cloning, purification, and biochemical characterization of hydantoin racemase from the legume symbiont Sinorhizobium meliloti CECT 4114.
  JOURNAL   Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 70 (2004) 625-30.
  ORGANISM  Sinorhizobium meliloti
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:15016445]
  AUTHORS   Martinez-Rodriguez S, Las Heras-Vazquez FJ, Clemente-Jimenez JM, Rodriguez-Vico F
  TITLE     Biochemical characterization of a novel hydantoin racemase from Agrobacterium tumefaciens C58.
  JOURNAL   Biochimie. 86 (2004) 77-81.
  ORGANISM  Agrobacterium tumefaciens
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15784981]
  AUTHORS   Suzuki S, Onishi N, Yokozeki K
  TITLE     Purification and characterization of hydantoin racemase from Microbacterium liquefaciens AJ 3912.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 69 (2005) 530-6.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:17132860]
  AUTHORS   Martinez-Rodriguez S, Andujar-Sanchez M, Neira JL, Clemente-Jimenez JM, Jara-Perez V, Rodriguez-Vico F, Las Heras-Vazquez FJ
  TITLE     Site-directed mutagenesis indicates an important role of cysteines 76 and 181 in the catalysis of hydantoin racemase from Sinorhizobium meliloti.
  JOURNAL   Protein. Sci. 15 (2006) 2729-38.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:11849938]
  AUTHORS   Altenbuchner J, Siemann-Herzberg M, Syldatk C
  TITLE     Hydantoinases and related enzymes as biocatalysts for the synthesis of unnatural chiral amino acids.
  JOURNAL   Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 12 (2001) 559-63.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 5.1.99.5
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 5.1.99.5
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 5.1.99.5
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 5.1.99.5
///
