ENTRY       EC 5.4.99.41                Enzyme
NAME        lupeol synthase;
            LUPI;
            BPW;
            RcLUS
CLASS       Isomerases;
            Intramolecular transferases;
            Transferring other groups
SYSNAME     (3S)-2,3-epoxy-2,3-dihydrosqualene mutase (cyclizing, lupeol-forming)
REACTION    (3S)-2,3-epoxy-2,3-dihydrosqualene = lupeol [RN:R06466]
ALL_REAC    R06466
SUBSTRATE   (3S)-2,3-epoxy-2,3-dihydrosqualene [CPD:C01054]
PRODUCT     lupeol [CPD:C08628]
COMMENT     Also forms some beta-amyrin. The recombinant enzyme from Arabidopsis thaliana [3] gives a 1:1 mixture of lupeol and lupan-3beta,20-diol with small amounts of beta-amyrin, germanicol, taraxasterol and psi-taraxasterol. See EC 4.2.1.128 (lupan-3beta,20-diol synthase).
HISTORY     EC 5.4.99.41 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:9883589]
  AUTHORS   Herrera JB, Bartel B, Wilson WK, Matsuda SP
  TITLE     Cloning and characterization of the Arabidopsis thaliana lupeol synthase gene.
  JOURNAL   Phytochemistry. 49 (1998) 1905-11.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana
  SEQUENCE  [ath:AT1G78970]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:10542078]
  AUTHORS   Shibuya M, Zhang H, Endo A, Shishikura K, Kushiro T, Ebizuka Y
  TITLE     Two branches of the lupeol synthase gene in the molecular evolution of plant oxidosqualene cyclases.
  JOURNAL   Eur. J. Biochem. 266 (1999) 302-7.
  ORGANISM  Olea europaea, Taraxacum officinale
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10930257]
  AUTHORS   Segura MJ, Meyer MM, Matsuda SP
  TITLE     Arabidopsis thaliana LUP1 converts oxidosqualene to multiple triterpene alcohols  and a triterpene diol.
  JOURNAL   Org. Lett. 2 (2000) 2257-9.
  ORGANISM  Arabidopsis thaliana
  SEQUENCE  [ath:AT1G78970]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12736505]
  AUTHORS   Zhang H, Shibuya M, Yokota S, Ebizuka Y
  TITLE     Oxidosqualene cyclases from cell suspension cultures of Betula platyphylla var. japonica: molecular evolution of oxidosqualene cyclases in higher plants.
  JOURNAL   Biol. Pharm. Bull. 26 (2003) 642-50.
  ORGANISM  Betula platyphylla
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q8W3Z2]
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:15256745]
  AUTHORS   Hayashi H, Huang P, Takada S, Obinata M, Inoue K, Shibuya M, Ebizuka Y
  TITLE     Differential expression of three oxidosqualene cyclase mRNAs in Glycyrrhiza glabra.
  JOURNAL   Biol. Pharm. Bull. 27 (2004) 1086-92.
  ORGANISM  Glycyrrhiza glabra
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q764T8]
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:16445885]
  AUTHORS   Guhling O, Hobl B, Yeats T, Jetter R
  TITLE     Cloning and characterization of a lupeol synthase involved in the synthesis of epicuticular wax crystals on stem and hypocotyl surfaces of Ricinus communis.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 448 (2006) 60-72.
  ORGANISM  Ricinus communis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q2XPU7]
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:17803686]
  AUTHORS   Basyuni M, Oku H, Tsujimoto E, Kinjo K, Baba S, Takara K
  TITLE     Triterpene synthases from the Okinawan mangrove tribe, Rhizophoraceae.
  JOURNAL   FEBS. J. 274 (2007) 5028-42.
  ORGANISM  Bruguiera gymnorhiza
  SEQUENCE  [up:A8CDT3]
PATHWAY     ec00909  Sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K15815  lupeol synthase 2
            K15816  lupeol synthase 1
GENES       ATH: AT1G78960(LUP2) AT1G78970(LUP1)
            ALY: ARALYDRAFT_477065 ARALYDRAFT_894488 ARALYDRAFT_895800
            CRB: CARUB_v10019849mg CARUB_v10021777mg
            EUS: EUTSA_v10018166mg
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 5.4.99.41
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 5.4.99.41
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 5.4.99.41
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 5.4.99.41
///
