ENTRY       EC 5.5.1.22                 Enzyme
NAME        (-)-bornyl diphosphate synthase;
            bornyl pyrophosphate synthase;
            bornyl pyrophosphate synthetase;
            (-)-bornyl pyrophosphate cyclase;
            bornyl diphosphate synthase;
            geranyl-diphosphate cyclase (ambiguous)
CLASS       Isomerases;
            Intramolecular lyases;
            Intramolecular lyases (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     (-)-bornyl-diphosphate lyase (decyclizing)
REACTION    geranyl diphosphate = (-)-bornyl diphosphate [RN:R10509]
ALL_REAC    R10509
SUBSTRATE   geranyl diphosphate [CPD:C00341]
PRODUCT     (-)-bornyl diphosphate [CPD:C20664]
COMMENT     Requires Mg2+. The enzyme from Tanacetum vulgare (tansy) can also use (3S)-linalyl diphosphate or more slowly neryl diphosphate in vitro. The reaction proceeds via isomeration of geranyl diphosphate to (3S)-linalyl diphosphate [3]. The oxygen and phosphorus originally linked to C-1 of geranyl diphosphate end up linked to C-2 of (-)-bornyl diphosphate [4]. cf. EC 5.5.1.8 (+)-bornyl diphosphate synthase.
HISTORY     EC 5.5.1.22 created 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:2178556]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Gershenzon J, Wheeler CJ, Satterwhite DM
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of monoterpenes: stereochemistry of the coupled isomerization and cyclization of geranyl pyrophosphate to camphane and isocamphane monoterpenes.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 277 (1990) 374-81.
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:3970524]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Shaskus J
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of monoterpenes: demonstration of a geranyl pyrophosphate:(-)-bornyl pyrophosphate cyclase in soluble enzyme preparations from tansy (Tanacetum vulgare).
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 236 (1985) 535-43.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:3997807]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Felton NM, Wheeler CJ
  TITLE     Stereochemistry at C-1 of geranyl pyrophosphate and neryl pyrophosphate in the cyclization to (+)- and (-)-bornyl pyrophosphate.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 260 (1985) 5956-62.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:4084562]
  AUTHORS   Croteau RB, Shaskus JJ, Renstrom B, Felton NM, Cane DE, Saito A, Chang C
  TITLE     Mechanism of the pyrophosphate migration in the enzymatic cyclization of geranyl  and linalyl pyrophosphates to (+)- and (-)-bornyl pyrophosphates.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 24 (1985) 7077-85.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:9747540]
  AUTHORS   Adam KP, Croteau R
  TITLE     Monoterpene biosynthesis in the liverwort Conocephalum conicum: demonstration of  sabinene synthase and bornyl diphosphate synthase.
  JOURNAL   Phytochemistry. 49 (1998) 475-80.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.22
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 5.5.1.22
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 5.5.1.22
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.22
            CAS: 110639-17-3
///
