ENTRY       EC 5.5.1.14                 Enzyme
NAME        syn-copalyl-diphosphate synthase;
            OsCyc1;
            OsCPSsyn;
            syn-CPP synthase;
            syn-copalyl diphosphate synthase
CLASS       Isomerases;
            Intramolecular lyases;
            Intramolecular lyases (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     9alpha-copalyl-diphosphate lyase (decyclizing)
REACTION    geranylgeranyl diphosphate = 9alpha-copalyl diphosphate [RN:R06312]
ALL_REAC    R06312
SUBSTRATE   geranylgeranyl diphosphate [CPD:C00353]
PRODUCT     9alpha-copalyl diphosphate [CPD:C11902]
COMMENT     Requires a divalent metal ion, preferably Mg2+, for activity. This class II terpene synthase produces syn-copalyl diphosphate, a precursor of several rice phytoalexins, including oryzalexin S and momilactones A and B. Phytoalexins are diterpenoid secondary metabolites that are involved in the defense mechanism of the plant, and are produced in response to pathogen attack through the perception of elicitor signal molecules such as chitin oligosaccharide, or after exposure to UV irradiation. The enzyme is constitutively expressed in the roots of plants where one of its products, momilactone B, acts as an allelochemical (a molecule released into the environment to suppress the growth of neighbouring plants). In other tissues the enzyme is upregulated by conditions that stimulate the biosynthesis of phytoalexins.
HISTORY     EC 5.5.1.14 created 2008
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:15341631]
  AUTHORS   Otomo K, Kenmoku H, Oikawa H, Konig WA, Toshima H, Mitsuhashi W, Yamane H, Sassa T, Toyomasu T.
  TITLE     Biological functions of ent- and syn-copalyl diphosphate synthases in rice: key enzymes for the branch point of gibberellin and phytoalexin biosynthesis.
  JOURNAL   Plant. J. 39 (2004) 886-93.
  ORGANISM  Oryza sativa
  SEQUENCE  [osa:4335090]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:15255861]
  AUTHORS   Xu M, Hillwig ML, Prisic S, Coates RM, Peters RJ.
  TITLE     Functional identification of rice syn-copalyl diphosphate synthase and its role in initiating biosynthesis of diterpenoid phytoalexin/allelopathic natural products.
  JOURNAL   Plant. J. 39 (2004) 309-18.
  ORGANISM  Oryza sativa
  SEQUENCE  [osa:4335090]
PATHWAY     ec00904  Diterpenoid biosynthesis
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K12928  aphidicolan-16beta-ol synthase/syn-copalyl-diphosphate synthase
            K14043  syn-copalyl-diphosphate synthase
GENES       OSA: 4335090
            SBI: SORBI_05g022290(SORBIDRAFT_05g022290)
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.14
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 5.5.1.14
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 5.5.1.14
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.14
///
