ENTRY       EC 5.5.1.8                  Enzyme
NAME        (+)-bornyl diphosphate synthase;
            bornyl pyrophosphate synthase;
            bornyl pyrophosphate synthetase;
            (+)-bornylpyrophosphate cyclase;
            geranyl-diphosphate cyclase (ambiguous)
CLASS       Isomerases;
            Intramolecular lyases;
            Intramolecular lyases (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     (+)-bornyl-diphosphate lyase (decyclizing)
REACTION    geranyl diphosphate = (+)-bornyl diphosphate [RN:R02007]
ALL_REAC    R02007
SUBSTRATE   geranyl diphosphate [CPD:C00341]
PRODUCT     (+)-bornyl diphosphate [CPD:C03190]
COMMENT     Requires Mg2+. The enzyme from Salvia officinalis (sage) can also use (3R)-linalyl diphosphate or more slowly neryl diphosphate in vitro [3]. The reaction proceeds via isomeration of geranyl diphosphate to (3R)-linalyl diphosphate. The oxygen and phosphorus originally linked to C-1 of geranyl diphosphate end up linked to C-2 of (+)-bornyl diphosphate [3]. cf. EC 5.5.1.22 [(-)-bornyl diphosphate synthase].
HISTORY     EC 5.5.1.8 created 1984, modified 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:42356]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Karp F.
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of monoterpenes: preliminary characterization of bornyl pyrophosphate synthetase from sage (Salvia officinalis) and demonstration that Geranyl pyrophosphate is the preferred substrate for cyclization.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 198 (1979) 512-22.
  ORGANISM  Salvia officinalis
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:2178556]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Gershenzon J, Wheeler CJ, Satterwhite DM
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of monoterpenes: stereochemistry of the coupled isomerization and cyclization of geranyl pyrophosphate to camphane and isocamphane monoterpenes.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 277 (1990) 374-81.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:3759972]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Satterwhite DM, Cane DE, Chang CC
  TITLE     Biosynthesis of monoterpenes. Enantioselectivity in the enzymatic cyclization of  (+)- and (-)-linalyl pyrophosphate to (+)- and (-)-bornyl pyrophosphate.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 261 (1986) 13438-45.
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:3997807]
  AUTHORS   Croteau R, Felton NM, Wheeler CJ
  TITLE     Stereochemistry at C-1 of geranyl pyrophosphate and neryl pyrophosphate in the cyclization to (+)- and (-)-bornyl pyrophosphate.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 260 (1985) 5956-62.
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:4084562]
  AUTHORS   Croteau RB, Shaskus JJ, Renstrom B, Felton NM, Cane DE, Saito A, Chang C
  TITLE     Mechanism of the pyrophosphate migration in the enzymatic cyclization of geranyl  and linalyl pyrophosphates to (+)- and (-)-bornyl pyrophosphates.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 24 (1985) 7077-85.
REFERENCE   6  [PMID:7872777]
  AUTHORS   McGeady P, Croteau R
  TITLE     Isolation and characterization of an active-site peptide from a monoterpene cyclase labeled with a mechanism-based inhibitor.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 317 (1995) 149-55.
REFERENCE   7  [PMID:9614092]
  AUTHORS   Wise ML, Savage TJ, Katahira E, Croteau R.
  TITLE     Monoterpene synthases from common sage (Salvia officinalis). cDNA isolation, characterization, and functional expression of (+)-sabinene synthase, 1,8-cineole synthase, and (+)-bornyl diphosphate synthase.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 273 (1998) 14891-9.
  ORGANISM  Salvia officinalis
  SEQUENCE  [up:O81192]
REFERENCE   8  [PMID:12432096]
  AUTHORS   Whittington DA, Wise ML, Urbansky M, Coates RM, Croteau RB, Christianson DW.
  TITLE     Bornyl diphosphate synthase: structure and strategy for carbocation manipulation by a terpenoid cyclase.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 99 (2002) 15375-80.
  ORGANISM  Salvia officinalis
  SEQUENCE  [up:O81192]
REFERENCE   9  [PMID:12941302]
  AUTHORS   Peters RJ, Croteau RB
  TITLE     Alternative termination chemistries utilized by monoterpene cyclases: chimeric analysis of bornyl diphosphate, 1,8-cineole, and sabinene synthases.
  JOURNAL   Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 417 (2003) 203-11.
PATHWAY     ec00902  Monoterpenoid biosynthesis
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K15098  bornyl diphosphate synthase
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.8
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 5.5.1.8
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 5.5.1.8
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.8
            CAS: 72668-91-8
///
