ENTRY       EC 5.5.1.20                 Enzyme
NAME        prosolanapyrone-III cycloisomerase;
            Sol5 (ambiguous);
            SPS (ambiguous);
            solanapyrone synthase (bifunctional enzyme: prosolanapyrone II oxidase/prosolanapyrone III cyclosiomerase)
CLASS       Isomerases;
            Intramolecular lyases;
            Intramolecular lyases (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     prosolanapyrone-III:(-)-solanapyrone A isomerase
REACTION    prosolanapyrone III = (-)-solanapyrone A [RN:R09918]
ALL_REAC    R09918
SUBSTRATE   prosolanapyrone III [CPD:C19934]
PRODUCT     (-)-solanapyrone A [CPD:C20201]
COMMENT     The enzyme is involved in the biosynthesis of the phytotoxin solanapyrone in some fungi. The bifunctional enzyme catalyses the oxidation of prosolanapyrone II and the subsequent Diels Alder cycloisomerization of the product prosolanapyrone III to (-)-solanapyrone A (cf. EC 1.1.3.42, prosolanapyrone II oxidase).
HISTORY     EC 5.5.1.20 created 2011
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:20486243]
  AUTHORS   Kasahara K, Miyamoto T, Fujimoto T, Oguri H, Tokiwano T, Oikawa H, Ebizuka Y, Fujii I
  TITLE     Solanapyrone synthase, a possible Diels-Alderase and iterative type I polyketide  synthase encoded in a biosynthetic gene cluster from Alternaria solani.
  JOURNAL   Chembiochem. 11 (2010) 1245-52.
  ORGANISM  Alternaria solani
  SEQUENCE  [up:D7UQ40]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9659400]
  AUTHORS   Katayama K, Kobayashi T, Oikawa H, Honma M, Ichihara A
  TITLE     Enzymatic activity and partial purification of solanapyrone synthase: first enzyme catalyzing Diels-Alder reaction.
  JOURNAL   Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1384 (1998) 387-95.
  ORGANISM  Alternaria solani
  SEQUENCE  [up:D7UQ40]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:18256508]
  AUTHORS   Katayama K, Kobayashi T, Chijimatsu M, Ichihara A, Oikawa H
  TITLE     Purification and N-terminal amino acid sequence of solanapyrone synthase, a natural Diels-Alderase from Alternaria solani.
  JOURNAL   Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem. 72 (2008) 604-7.
  ORGANISM  Alternaria solani
  SEQUENCE  [up:D7UQ40]
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.20
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 5.5.1.20
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 5.5.1.20
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.20
///
