ENTRY       EC 5.5.1.15                 Enzyme
NAME        terpentedienyl-diphosphate synthase;
            terpentedienol diphosphate synthase;
            Cyc1;
            clerodadienyl diphosphate synthase
CLASS       Isomerases;
            Intramolecular lyases;
            Intramolecular lyases (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     terpentedienyl-diphosphate lyase (decyclizing)
REACTION    geranylgeranyl diphosphate = terpentedienyl diphosphate [RN:R09714]
ALL_REAC    R09714
SUBSTRATE   geranylgeranyl diphosphate [CPD:C00353]
PRODUCT     terpentedienyl diphosphate [CPD:C19815]
COMMENT     Requires Mg2+. Contains a DXDD motif, which is a characteristic of diterpene cylases whose reactions are initiated by protonation at the 14,15-double bond of geranylgeranyl diphosphate (GGDP) [2]. The triggering proton is lost at the end of the cyclization reaction [3]. The product of the reaction, terpentedienyl diphosphate, is the substrate for EC 4.2.3.36, terpentetriene synthase and is a precursor of the diterpenoid antibiotic terpentecin.
HISTORY     EC 5.5.1.15 created 2008
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:11567009]
  AUTHORS   Dairi T, Hamano Y, Kuzuyama T, Itoh N, Furihata K, Seto H.
  TITLE     Eubacterial diterpene cyclase genes essential for production of the isoprenoid antibiotic terpentecin.
  JOURNAL   J. Bacteriol. 183 (2001) 6085-94.
  ORGANISM  Kitasatospora griseola
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9AJE4]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:12138123]
  AUTHORS   Hamano Y, Kuzuyama T, Itoh N, Furihata K, Seto H, Dairi T.
  TITLE     Functional analysis of eubacterial diterpene cyclases responsible for biosynthesis of a diterpene antibiotic, terpentecin.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 277 (2002) 37098-104.
  ORGANISM  Kitasatospora griseola
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q9AJE4]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:12839434]
  AUTHORS   Eguchi T, Dekishima Y, Hamano Y, Dairi T, Seto H, Kakinuma K.
  TITLE     A new approach for the investigation of isoprenoid biosynthesis featuring pathway switching, deuterium hyperlabeling, and 1H NMR spectroscopy. The reaction mechanism of a novel streptomyces diterpene cyclase.
  JOURNAL   J. Org. Chem. 68 (2003) 5433-8.
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.15
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 5.5.1.15
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 5.5.1.15
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.15
///
