ENTRY       EC 5.5.1.12                 Enzyme
NAME        copalyl diphosphate synthase
CLASS       Isomerases;
            Intramolecular lyases;
            Intramolecular lyases (only sub-subclass identified to date)
SYSNAME     (+)-copalyl-diphosphate lyase (decyclizing)
REACTION    geranylgeranyl diphosphate = (+)-copalyl diphosphate [RN:R06298]
ALL_REAC    R06298
SUBSTRATE   geranylgeranyl diphosphate [CPD:C00353]
PRODUCT     (+)-copalyl diphosphate [CPD:C11901]
COMMENT     In some plants, such as Salvia miltiorrhiza, this enzyme is monofunctional. In other plants this activity is often a part of a bifunctional enzyme. For example, in Selaginella moellendorffii this activity is catalysed by a bifunctional enzyme that also catalyses EC 4.2.3.131, miltiradiene synthase, while in the tree Abies grandis (grand fir) it is catalysed by a bifunctional enzyme that also catalyses EC 4.2.3.18, abietadiene synthase.
HISTORY     EC 5.5.1.12 created 2002, modified 2012
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:11552804]
  AUTHORS   Peters RJ, Ravn MM, Coates RM, Croteau RB.
  TITLE     Bifunctional abietadiene synthase: free diffusive transfer of the (+)-copalyl diphosphate intermediate between two distinct active sites.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 123 (2001) 8974-8.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
  SEQUENCE  [up: Q38710]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:22027823]
  AUTHORS   Sugai Y, Ueno Y, Hayashi K, Oogami S, Toyomasu T, Matsumoto S, Natsume M, Nozaki H, Kawaide H
  TITLE     Enzymatic (13)C labeling and multidimensional NMR analysis of miltiradiene synthesized by bifunctional diterpene cyclase in Selaginella moellendorffii.
  JOURNAL   J. Biol. Chem. 286 (2011) 42840-7.
  ORGANISM  Selaginella moellendorffii
  SEQUENCE  [smo:SELMODRAFT_450918]
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:11805316]
  AUTHORS   Peters RJ, Croteau RB.
  TITLE     Abietadiene synthase catalysis: mutational analysis of a prenyl diphosphate ionization-initiated cyclization and rearrangement.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 99 (2002) 580-4.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
  SEQUENCE  [up: Q38710]
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:12059223]
  AUTHORS   Ravn MM, Peters RJ, Coates RM, Croteau R.
  TITLE     Mechanism of abietadiene synthase catalysis: stereochemistry and stabilization of the cryptic pimarenyl carbocation intermediates.
  JOURNAL   J. Am. Chem. Soc. 124 (2002) 6998-7006.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:11827528]
  AUTHORS   Peters RJ, Croteau RB.
  TITLE     Abietadiene synthase catalysis: conserved residues involved in protonation-initiated cyclization of geranylgeranyl diphosphate to (+)-copalyl diphosphate.
  JOURNAL   Biochemistry. 41 (2002) 1836-42.
  ORGANISM  Abies grandis
  SEQUENCE  [up:Q38710]
PATHWAY     ec00904  Diterpenoid biosynthesis
            ec01100  Metabolic pathways
            ec01110  Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites
ORTHOLOGY   K12927  abietadiene synthase/copalyl diphosphate synthase
            K14041  levopimaradiene synthase /copalyl diphosphate synthase
            K14042  isopimara-7,15-diene synthase /copalyl diphosphate synthase
            K18113  miltiradiene synthase / copalyl diphosphate synthase
GENES       SMO: SELMODRAFT_450918
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.12
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 5.5.1.12
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 5.5.1.12
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 5.5.1.12
            CAS: 157972-08-2
///
