ENTRY       EC 6.3.2.35                 Enzyme
NAME        D-alanine---D-serine ligase;
            VanC;
            VanE;
            VanG
CLASS       Ligases;
            Forming carbon-nitrogen bonds;
            Acid-D-amino-acid ligases (peptide synthases)
SYSNAME     D-alanine:D-serine ligase (ADP-forming)
REACTION    D-alanine + D-serine + ATP = D-alanyl-D-serine + ADP + phosphate [RN:R09595]
ALL_REAC    R09595
SUBSTRATE   D-alanine [CPD:C00133];
            D-serine [CPD:C00740];
            ATP [CPD:C00002]
PRODUCT     D-alanyl-D-serine [CPD:C19719];
            ADP [CPD:C00008];
            phosphate [CPD:C00009]
COMMENT     The product of this enzyme, D-alanyl-D-serine, can be incorporated into the peptidoglycan pentapeptide instead of the usual D-alanyl-D-alanine dipeptide, which is formed by EC 6.3.2.4, D-alanine---D-alanine ligase. The resulting peptidoglycan does not bind the glycopeptide antibiotics vancomycin and teicoplanin, conferring resistance on the bacteria.
HISTORY     EC 6.3.2.35 created 2010
REFERENCE   1  [PMID:1551598]
  AUTHORS   Dutka-Malen S, Molinas C, Arthur M, Courvalin P
  TITLE     Sequence of the vanC gene of Enterococcus gallinarum BM4174 encoding a D-alanine:D-alanine ligase-related protein necessary for vancomycin resistance.
  JOURNAL   Gene. 112 (1992) 53-8.
  ORGANISM  Enterococcus gallinarum
  SEQUENCE  [up:P29753]
REFERENCE   2  [PMID:9294159]
  AUTHORS   Park IS, Lin CH, Walsh CT
  TITLE     Bacterial resistance to vancomycin: overproduction, purification, and characterization of VanC2 from Enterococcus casseliflavus as a D-Ala-D-Ser ligase.
  JOURNAL   Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 94 (1997) 10040-4.
REFERENCE   3  [PMID:10471558]
  AUTHORS   Fines M, Perichon B, Reynolds P, Sahm DF, Courvalin P
  TITLE     VanE, a new type of acquired glycopeptide resistance in Enterococcus faecalis BM4405.
  JOURNAL   Antimicrob. Agents. Chemother. 43 (1999) 2161-4.
  ORGANISM  Enterococcus faecalis
REFERENCE   4  [PMID:14617152]
  AUTHORS   Depardieu F, Bonora MG, Reynolds PE, Courvalin P
  TITLE     The vanG glycopeptide resistance operon from Enterococcus faecalis revisited.
  JOURNAL   Mol. Microbiol. 50 (2003) 931-48.
  ORGANISM  Enterococcus faecalis
REFERENCE   5  [PMID:19216682]
  AUTHORS   Watanabe S, Kobayashi N, Quinones D, Hayakawa S, Nagashima S, Uehara N, Watanabe N
  TITLE     Genetic diversity of the low-level vancomycin resistance gene vanC-2/vanC-3 and identification of a novel vanC subtype (vanC-4) in Enterococcus casseliflavus.
  JOURNAL   Microb. Drug. Resist. 15 (2009) 1-9.
  ORGANISM  Enterococcus casseliflavus
DBLINKS     ExplorEnz - The Enzyme Database: 6.3.2.35
            IUBMB Enzyme Nomenclature: 6.3.2.35
            ExPASy - ENZYME nomenclature database: 6.3.2.35
            BRENDA, the Enzyme Database: 6.3.2.35
///
